<document title="Supported C compilers" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>supported C compilers</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>C compilers, support</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Unix/Linux Users:
		</heading>
		<paragraph>EiffelStudio supports `gcc' on most platforms and the native`cc' compiler if it is an ANSI C compiler.</paragraph>
		<paragraph> </paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Microsoft Visual C++ Users
		</heading>
		<paragraph>EiffelStudio supports only version 6.0 and higher of the Microsoft Visual C++ environment. You can still use older versions of the Microsoft C++ environment (version 4.1, 4.2 or 5.0) as long as you have the latest Platform SDK from Microsoft, but this won't be supported by Eiffel Software.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Normally it will automatically detect the location of the C compiler. In case it wouldn't, make sure that the Microsoft tools are correctly setup to run from the MS-DOS prompt. To do that you need to set the environment variable PATH, LIB and INCLUDE to the value specified in the file`vcvars32.bat' from the `bin' directory of the VC installation.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Borland C++ Users:
		</heading>
		<paragraph>EiffelStudio only supports version 5.5.1 of Borland C++ which is included in the installation of EiffelStudio. We do not support any other versions.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>By default the installation program will set in the registry keys the ISE_C_COMPILER key to `bcb'.</paragraph>
		<paragraph> </paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Changing your C compiler on Windows
		</heading>
		<paragraph>You can do it in two different ways. The first one is using the registry keys of the Windows&#174; operating system, the second one modifies the environment variables.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>When modifying the registry keys, simply create a `compiler.reg' file with the following content: </paragraph>
		<code_block>REGEDIT4

[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\Software\ISE\Eiffel55]

[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\Software\ISE\Eiffel55\ec]
"ISE_C_COMPILER"="C_COMPILER"

[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\Software\ISE\Eiffel55\finish_freezing]
"ISE_C_COMPILER"="C_COMPILER"

[HKEY_LOCAL_MACHINE\Software\ISE\Eiffel55\wizard]
"ISE_C_COMPILER"="C_COMPILER"</code_block>
		<paragraph>Where you can replace "C_COMPILER" by either:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>msc for Microsoft Visual C++</item>
			<item>bcb for Borland C++</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>Then import the file and everything will be ready to use your new C compiler.</paragraph>
		<note><bold>Note:</bold> Replace Eiffel55 by the appropriate value matching the version number of EiffelStudio. For example EiffelStudio 6.5 will have a value of Eiffel65</note>
		<paragraph> </paragraph>
		<paragraph>When modifying the environment variables, simply defines ISE_C_COMPILER to be either:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item> msc for Microsoft Visual C++</item>
			<item>bcb for Borland C++</item>
		</list>
	</paragraph></document>
