<document title="Feature call auto complete" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>Editor, Feature call autocomplete</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>EiffelStudio editor now offers the possibility to complete feature calls automatically. This means that when the user types " 
			<italic>an_identifier.an_incomplete_feature_name</italic>" and then triggers the auto-complete, the editor will propose a list of possible feature names correct in this situation.
			<line_break/>To be more precise, a window will pop up and display the list of features that can be called on 
			<italic>an_identifier</italic> and that match 
			<italic>an_incomplete_feature_name</italic>. The user can accept the suggested name, choose another name (in the list or not), or simply cancel the auto-complete.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelstudio/editor_auto_completion_window.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>To trigger the auto complete, press the key combination "Ctrl+Space" or click on 
			<bold>Complete word</bold> in the 
			<bold>Advanced</bold> sub-menu of the
			<bold/>
			<link>
				<url>../80_edit_menu_commands.xml</url>
				<label>menu</label>
			</link>. If automatic completion is possible, there are two cases : if only one name matches, this name will be inserted in the editor. If there are no matching names or several ones a window will appear. This window will contain a text field and a list. The text field will be filled with the beginning of the feature name that was entered. The first item in the list, if any, will be selected.
			<line_break/> To complete your code with the selected item, press "Enter" or "Ctrl+Space".
			<line_break/> To choose another item, use keyboard Up and Down arrows or the mouse. You can also modify the content of the text field. The list will be updated automatically. To validate your choice, press "Enter" or "Ctrl+Space". If there is no selected item, the content of the text field will be inserted.
			<line_break/> To cancel the auto-complete, press "Esc" at any time.
		</paragraph>
		<tip>
			<bold>Tips</bold>:
		</tip>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>If the selected feature is a query, you can call the auto-complete again right after the previous completion. There is no need to type a dot.</item>
			<item>You can call the auto-complete without an identifier. The auto-complete window will then show the features of the current class.</item>
			<item>The keyboard shortcut for automatic completion can be changed in the 
				<link>
					<url>../../85_preferences/eiffelstudio/40_editor/20_keyboard_shortcuts_preferences.xml</url>
					<label>editor preferences</label>
				</link>.
			</item>
			<item>Typing a non-alphanumeric character in the completion window automatically closes it. You can therefore type '.', ' ' or '(' to close the completion window and start typing the next token straight away.</item>
		</list>
		<note>
			<bold>Notes</bold>:
		</note>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Only identifiers that were already defined when the class was compiled for the last time can be completed, except for local entity names that can always be completed.</item>
			<item>Only compiled features will appear in the auto-complete window.</item>
			<item>By default, features from class ANY will be ignored by the auto-complete window. This can be changed in the 
				<link>
					<url>../../85_preferences/eiffelstudio/40_editor/10_general_editor_preferences.xml</url>
					<label>editor preferences</label>
				</link>.
			</item>
		</list>
	</paragraph></document>
