<document output="envision" title="International Versions of Microsoft's Windows XP">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>International Versions of Microsoft's Windows XP</envision_title>
				<envision_pseudo_name>30</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>International Versions of Windows XP</term>
				</keyword>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Known Issues, International Versions of Windows XP</term>
				</keyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		The documentation provided in this section instructs you on how to circumvent the Microsoft
		Visual Studio .NET installation issue on non-English versions of Microsoft's Windows XP to enable the use of EiffelEnvision from within Visual Studio
		.NET 2003 successfully.
		<anchor>bypassing</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Patching Visual Studio .NET 2003</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
		The problem lies in the registration of <italic>msenvp.dll</italic>, located in your Windows XP installation 
		<bold>Common Files</bold> folder. On English versions of Windows XP, this folder is typically located 
		in '<code>C:\Program Files\Common Files.'</code> However, the French version of Windows 
		XP is typically located in '<code>C:\Program Files\Fichiers communs</code>,' and it is this translation that the Visual
		Studio .NET 2003 installation does not account for.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
		To correct this issue, you will need to reregister <italic>msenvp.dll</italic> manually. To 
		do this, open a command line console. This can be done using the <bold>Start Menu</bold> &gt;  
		<bold>Run</bold> (or use Ctrl+R), and typing
		</paragraph>
		<code_block>cmd.exe</code_block>
		<paragraph>
		in the field provided, and clicking <bold>Ok</bold>.
		</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph>
		From the command-line console, navigate to your Windows XP <bold>Common Files</bold> folder
		, which should be a direct translation of Common Files in your chosen installation language. 
		For the French edition of Windows XP you would navigate to this folder by typing the following into the command-line  
		console and pressing Enter.
		</paragraph>
		<code_block>cd "C:\Program Files\Fichiers communs"</code_block>
		<paragraph>
		Now continue navigating to the 'Microsoft Shared\MSEnv' sub-folder.
		</paragraph>
		<code_block>cd "Microsoft Shared\MSEnv"</code_block>
		<paragraph>
		Located in the current folder should now be a file call <italic>msenvp.dll</italic>. You 
		can confirm this by typing the 'dir' command followed by pressing Enter.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
		To register the DLL you will need to use the <italic>regsvr32.exe</italic> Windows registration tool. 
		Type the following into the console and press Enter.
		</paragraph>
		<code_block>regsvr32 msenvp.dll</code_block>
		<paragraph>
		If registration succeeded, you will be presented with a Windows information dialog box confirming 
		the success of the registration. Discard the dialog by clicking <bold>Ok</bold>. You will now be able to use  
		EiffelEnvision successfully from within Visual Studio .NET 2003.
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>
