<document output="envision" title="Known Bugs and Issues">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Known Bugs and Issues</envision_title>
				<envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Known EiffelEnvision Bugs and Issues</term>
				</keyword>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>EiffelEnvision, Known Bugs and Issues</term>
				</keyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			This document contains a consise run down of the known EiffelEnvision bugs and issues surrounding its usage.
		</paragraph>

		<anchor>bugs</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			Known Bugs
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>
					International versions of Windows XP may prevent EiffelEnvision from building in <bold>Microsoft Visual Studio .NET 2003</bold>. This is 
					a Visual Studio .NET installation bug. If you cannot build your <italic>first</italic> project using EiffelEnvision, after installation  
					or after modifying the Visual Studio .NET installation, then this is 
					very likely to be the problem.
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Solution</bold>: To manually patch the Visual Studio .NET bug please read <link><url>international_bug.xml</url>
						<label>International Windows XP Patch</label></link>.
					</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					The Eiffel editor installed with EiffelEnvision shows a syntax error when a class only contains the most basic 
					inheritance clause for a class, with no features.
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Solution</bold>: Ignore syntax error or add the <code><keyword>end</keyword></code> after the inherited class name declaration.
					</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					Accessing the Examples Directory from the Welcome page shown after installation fails to 
					link to the correct examples and does not display correctly when using Mozilla Firefox or similar Web browsers.
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Solution</bold>: Access the Examples Directory from the installed Start Menu shortcut.
					</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					On very rare occassions the Eiffel Editor display incorrectly, adding additional color and symbols that should not be present.
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Solution</bold>: Close the Eiffel document and reopen it.
					</paragraph>
				</item>
			</list>
		</paragraph>

		<anchor>issues</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			Known Issues
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<list ordered="false">
			<item>Due to the introduction of a new EiffelEnvision <link><url/><label>*Solution Explorer</label></link> and configuration 
			changes, older Eiffel ENViSioN! 2.01 or less cannot be opened in EiffelEnvision.</item>
			</list>
		</paragraph>
				
		<anchor>reporting_bug</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			Reporting Bugs
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			Whilst EiffelSoftware maintains a high level of robustness in the software that it produces, some bugs always slip through the 
			proverbial net. If you discover a bug in EiffelEnvision please report it to our bug reporting system at 
			<link><url>http://support.eiffel.com</url><label>http://support.eiffel.com</label></link>. For our Enterprise customers, please
			use the submitter ID provide to you when purchasing <bold>EiffelEnvision</bold>. For all other users please use the submitter ID <italic>"Unknown".
			</italic>
		</paragraph>
		
		<anchor>see_also</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Related Sections</content>
		</heading>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See also</bold>:
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>history.xml</url><label>Version History</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>vxurfSolutionExplorerDialog</url><label>*Visual Studio Solution Explorer</label></link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
