<document title="Interactive command line: Introduction" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>command line interactive mode</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
	If you need to use 
		<bold>ec</bold> to execute a number of successive operations on a system, you do not need to restart the command each time; instead you may use the -loop option, which will interactively prompt you for successive operations.
		<paragraph>If you launch 
			<bold>ec</bold> with this option, you will get the interactive version's Main Menu:
		</paragraph>
		<code_block>
==== ISE EiffelStudio - Interactive Batch Version (v5.5.0926 Enterprise Edition) ===
    (C) Class : class formats and information.
    (I) Compile : compile or run the system.
    (F) Feature : feature formats and information.
    (S) System : Config and cluster details.
    (P) Profile : information about a profiled run.
    (D) Documentation: create documents from the system.

    (H) Help : show list of commands.
    (Q) Quit : terminate session.
    (Y) Yank : yank (save) output of last command to a file.
Command =&gt;</code_block>
		<line_break></line_break>The revision number in the first line may be different in your case to indicate that you have a more recent delivery. In this menu, and in all subsequent ones, the commands appear in two groups.
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>commands in the first group are specific to each menu</item>
			<item>commands in the second group H (Help) to repeat the list of choices, Y (Yank) to save the output of the last command to a file that you will be prompted to name, and Q (Quit) to quit appear in all menus, and will be complemented in the Item Menus below by the M (Main) command which returns to the main menu.</item>
		</list>By typing one of the letters shown in the Main Menu's first group, you can go to one of the Item Menus: 
		<link>
			<url>20_class_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Class</label>
		</link>, 
		<link>
			<url>10_compile_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Compile</label>
		</link>, 
		<link>
			<url>30_feature_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Feature</label>
		</link>, 
		<link>
			<url>40_system_menu.xml</url>
			<label>System</label>
		</link>, 
		<link>
			<url>50_profile_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Profile</label>
		</link> and 
		<link>
			<url>60_documentation_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Documentation</label>
		</link>. 
		<link>
			<url>10_compile_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Compile</label>
		</link> enables you to compile a system and execute the result; the next three enable you to obtain information about your project. 
		<link>
			<url>50_profile_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Profile</label>
		</link> will enable you to exploit profiling information. Finally, 
		<link>
			<url>60_documentation_menu.xml</url>
			<label>Documentation</label>
		</link> will enable you to generate HTML documentation about your project.
	</paragraph></document>
