<document title="MANUAL IDENTIFICATION AND COPYRIGHT: Invitation">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\A Guide to Eiffel for .NET\Invitation to Eiffel</envision_location>
				<envision_pseudo_name>99</envision_pseudo_name>
				<envision_title>Manual Indentification and Copyright</envision_title>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>Title: 
			Invitation to Eiffel,  Eiffel Software  Technical Report TR-EI-67/IV.  
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Publication history</content>
		</heading>First published 1987.  Some revisions (in particular Web versions) have used the title "Eiffel in a Nutshell"
		<line_break></line_break>This version: July 2001.  Introduces coverage of agents; several other improvements.  Corresponds to release 5.0 of the EiffelStudio environment.  
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Author</content>
		</heading>Bertrand Meyer
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Software Credits</content>
		</heading>See acknowledgments in book 
			<link>
				<url>http://www.eiffel.com/doc/page.html</url><anchor_name>etl</anchor_name>
				<label>Eiffel: The Language</label>
			</link>.
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Cover Design</content>
		</heading>Rich Ayling.  
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Copyright notice and proprietary information</content>
		</heading>Copyright Interactive Software Engineering Inc.  (Eiffel Software), 2001.  May not be reproduced in any form (including electronic storage) without the written permission of  Eiffel Software .  "Eiffel Power" and the Eiffel Power logo are trademarks of  Eiffel Software .  All uses of the product documented here are subject to the terms and conditions of the  Eiffel Software  Eiffel user license.  Any other use or duplication is a violation of the applicable laws on copyright, trade secrets and intellectual property.  
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Special duplication permission for educational institutions</content>
		</heading>Degree-granting educational institutions using  Eiffel Software  Eiffel for teaching purposes as part of the 
			<link>
				<url> http://www.eiffel.com/educators/resources.html</url>
				<label>Eiffel University Partnership Program</label>
			</link> 
		may be permitted under certain conditions to copy specific parts of this book.  Contact  Eiffel Software  for details.  
		<info>About  Eiffel Software  (Interactive Software Engineering) helps you produce software better, faster and cheaper.   Eiffel Software  provides a wide range of products and services based on object technology, including  Eiffel Software  Eiffel, a complete development environment for the full system life cycle.  Eiffel Software's training courses, available worldwide, cover key management and technical topics.  Eiffel Software's consultants are available to address your project needs at all levels.  Eiffel Software's TOOLS (Technology of Object-Oriented Languages and Systems) conferences, 
			<link>
				<url>http://www.tools-conferences.com</url>
				<label>http://www.tools-conferences.com</label>
			</link>, are the meeting point for anyone interested in the software technologies of the future.   Eiffel Software  originated one of the earliest .  NET products and offers a full range of .  NET services and training at 
			<link>
				<url>http://www.dotnetexperts.com</url>
				<label>http://www.dotnetexperts.com</label>
			</link>. </info>
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>
				<content>For more information</content>
			</heading>
			Interactive Software Engineering Inc.
			<line_break></line_break>
			 Eiffel Software  Building,
			<line_break></line_break>356 Storke Road,
			<line_break></line_break>Goleta,
			<line_break></line_break>CA, 93117
			<line_break></line_break>USA.
			<line_break></line_break>
			<line_break></line_break>Telephone 805-685-1006,
			<line_break></line_break>Fax 805-685-6869 
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>
				<content>Internet and email</content>
			</heading> Eiffel Software  maintains a rich source of information at 
			<link>
				<url>http://eiffel.com</url>
				<label>http://eiffel.com</label>
			</link>, with more than 1200 Web pages including online documentation, downloadable files, product descriptions, links to  Eiffel Software  partners, University Partnership program, mailing list archives, announcements, press coverage, Frequently Asked Questions, Support pages, and much more.  Visit 
			<link>
				<url>http://www.eiffel.com/general/contact_details.html</url>
				<label>http://www.eiffel.com/general/contact_details.html</label>
			</link> to request information about products and services.  To subscribe to the  Eiffel Software  Eiffel user list, go to 
			<link>
				<url>http://groups.eiffel.com/join</url>
				<label>http://groups.eiffel.com/join</label>
			</link>.  
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>
				<content>Support programs</content>
			</heading> Eiffel Software  offers a variety of support options tailored to the diverse needs of its customers.  See 
			<link>
				<url>http://support.eiffel.com</url>
				<label>http://support.eiffel.com</label>
			</link> for details.  				
		</paragraph>
	</document>
