<document title="Eiffel language: The One-Minute Summary">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\A Guide to Eiffel for .NET</envision_location>
				<envision_title>Eiffel: The One-Minute Summary</envision_title>
				<envision_pseudo_name>10</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>For the truly hurried here is a capsule overview of Eiffel:
		<line_break/>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>A comprehensive approach to the construction of successful software.  </item>
			<item>The goal: 
				<bold>cheaper </bold> (spend less on development, debugging, maintenance); 
				<bold>better </bold> (get the bugs before they get you); 
				<bold>faster</bold> (bring your products out before anyone else); and 
				<bold>easier </bold> to maintain, reuse and extend.
			</item>
			<item>The only approach that covers analysis, design, implementation and maintenance in a single framework.  </item>
			<item>Includes a 
				<bold>language</bold>, a 
				<bold>methodology</bold>, and a complete graphical development 
				<bold>environment</bold>.
			</item>
			<item>Language: widely recognized as the best and simplest implementation of object-oriented concepts.  Clean, simple, readable, powerful, easy to learn.  </item>
			<item>Methodology: based on 
				<bold>Design by Contract -- </bold>building reliable software by defining precise contracts between its various components, and making sure the software construction process enforces these contracts.
			</item>
			<item>Powerful graphical environment supporting lightning-fast compilation (
				<bold>Melting Ice Technology</bold>) and unique facilities for analysis (CASE), documentation, exploration ("browsing"), documentation, HTML, XML and UML generation.
			</item>
			<item>Complete portability across major industry platforms: Windows 98/Me/XP/NT/2000, major Unix versions, Linux, even VMS.  Portable graphics with native look-and-feel on each platform.  </item>
			<item>One of the very first commercial environments to be available on the .  NET framework, as a result of a partnership with Microsoft.  </item>
			<item>Sophisticated mechanisms for contract monitoring, inheritance (single, multiple and repeated), exception handling, genericity.  </item>
			<item>Generation of C code for portability and efficiency; speed of executables rivals native C.  </item>
			<item>Rich set of libraries covering graphics, the Web, networking, fundamental algorithms and data structures, lexical analysis, parsing, etc.  </item>
			<item>Proven track record of successful projects, including some of the largest successful O-O projects ever built anywhere: finance, telecommunications, CAD-CAM, CASE, education etc.  </item>
			<item>The most effective solution available today for the professional software developer.</item>
		</list></paragraph>
		<paragraph>For a more detailed overview see 
			<link>
				<url>../language/invitation-00.xml</url>
				<label>An Invitation to Eiffel</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph></document>
