<document title="EiffelStudio: Creating a new project" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>The first thing to do to start Eiffeling is to create a project. Most commands are disabled when no project is created.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>When opening EiffelStudio, by default a dialog is popped up that proposes to create or open a project:</paragraph>
		<image>
			<url>/images/eiffelstudio/dialogs_and_wizards/startup_dialog.png</url>
		</image>
		<paragraph>Under 
			<bold>Create project</bold>, several options are offered, which depend on the platform you are on.
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>
				<bold>Basic application</bold> is the most basic new project that can be generated. It only includes the 
				<link>
					<url>/libraries/base/index.xml</url>
					<label>base library</label>
				</link> and by default only creates the frame of the project. This is the ideal choice to start a textual (console) application, or to discover Eiffel. Indeed, the project is very light and includes only things that are essential in any project. It is available on all platforms.
			</item>
			<item>
				<bold>.NET application</bold> has by default all essential components to start a project targeting the Microsoft .NET platform. Of course, it is only available on Windows, and only if you have chosen to install the .NET support during the installation.
			</item>
			<item>
				<bold>Vision2 application</bold> creates a new project that includes the 
				<link>
					<url>/libraries/vision2/00_introduction.xml</url>
					<label>Eiffel Vision2 library</label>
				</link>. This is the perfect choice to start a platform-independent graphic application, or even any graphic application, since EiffelVision2 is easier to use than platform-specific libraries. This option is available on all platforms.
			</item>
			<item>
				<bold>WEL application</bold> generates a project using the 
				<link>
					<url>/libraries/wel/index.xml</url>
					<label>Windows Eiffel Library(WEL)</label>
				</link>. This option is recommended for projects needing advanced Windows features, or Windows applications that are time-critical, since the graphic functionality provided by WEL is more efficient than the one provided by Vision2, which on the other hand provides a platform-independent abstract interface. This wizard is only available on Windows.
			</item>
		</list>All those options are also available in the 
		<bold> File</bold>/ 
		<bold>New project...</bold> menu. This pops up a dialog with all the options to generate a new project:
		<image>
			<url>/images/eiffelstudio/dialogs_and_wizards/create_a_project.png</url>
		</image>
		<tip>
			<bold>Tip</bold>: If you checked the "Don't show this dialog at startup" checkbox in the start-up dialog but want to get it back, you can use the 
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/85_preferences/eiffelstudio/20_interface/20_discardable_dialogs.xml</url>
				<label>Preferences dialog</label>
			</link> to reset the default value.
		</tip>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/> 
			<link>
				<url>20_retrieving_a_project_from_an_ace_file.xml</url>
				<label>Retrieving a project from an configuration file</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
