 <document output="envision" title="Project Settings">  
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Project Settings</envision_title>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\Tools\Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker\Using the Compliance Checker</envision_location>
				<envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker, Project settings</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data> 
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The <bold>Project Settings</bold> tab is used to specify a compliance-checker project's settings. There are only two configurable project settings:		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item><bold>Assembly</bold>: This is the location of assembly you would like to check for conformance. You may either type the path to the assembly in the available field or use the adjacent browse button, to browse/search for an assembly. The <bold>Assembly</bold> field will flag an error, indicated by a <image><url>../images/error.ico</url></image>, when the entered path is not valid. For more information about why the specified path is not valid, examine the tool tip shown when hovering your cursor over the <image><url>../images/error.ico</url></image>.<line_break/><line_break/></item>
			<item><bold>Reference Paths</bold>: The reference paths are a list of paths to lookup any assembly, specified in the <bold>Assembly</bold> field, dependencies. More often than not there will be no need to specify any paths, however when developing .NET components dependencies may not be located in the same directory as the specified or are present in the Global Assembly Cache (GAC).</item>
		</list>
				
		<anchor>adding_removing_references</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Adding, Removing and Modifying Reference Paths</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			To add a new reference path click the <bold>Add</bold> button and a folder browser dialog will appear. Select a desired path and click <bold>Ok</bold>. The selected path will then be added to the list of <bold>Reference Paths</bold>.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			If you need to modify a previously added reference path, either click on the <image><url>../images/open.ico</url></image> icon, located at the far right of the path item in the <bold>Reference Paths</bold> list. This will show a folder browser dialog so you may select a new path. Clicking <bold>Ok</bold> will replace the current path with the new path, <bold>Cancel</bold> will not change anything. Alternatively you can double-left mouse click the path you wish to change and an editable field will appear, or simple select the path and press the F2 shortcut key. You may confirm your editions by pressing ENTER or mouse clicking elsewhere. To discard any changes press ESCAPE.
		</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: A reference path may show a <image><url>../images/error.ico</url></image> to the left of the specified path. This indicates that the path could not be found.
		</note>
		<paragraph>
			To remove an existing reference path, select the path you wish to remove and press the <bold>Remove</bold> button. Alternatively use the DELETE shortcut key.
		</paragraph>
		
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>:
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>../index.xml</url><label>Compliance Checker Overview</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>index.xml</url><label>Using the Compliance Checker</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>../20_projects/index.xml</url><label>Compliance Projects</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>30_compliance_checker.xml</url><label>Compliance Checker Tab</label></link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
