<document title="EiffelStudio window overview" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>Overview</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>Context tool</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Window layout
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Unlike its predecessor EiffelBench, in EiffelStudio all windows have the same components. However, components to be displayed are chosen by the user. Moreover, windows have two modes: the edition mode and the debug mode. Basically, a standard window looks likethis:</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelstudio/general_edition_mode.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>As you can see, it is divided in several parts: a top section, a left panel, a right panel and a status bar.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The top part is rather not surprising. It first contains a menu bar, which adapts itself to the context of the current project. It also contains two toolbars (the main toolbar and the project toolbar). Between the toolbars is located the main address bar.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The left panel contains various 
			<italic>tools</italic> that help the navigation in the system.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The right panel contains two major tools: the editor and the context tool.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The status bar supplies various information:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Its first field gives punctual information concerning a recent operation (such as loading a project, syntax errors in a class text, etc.).</item>
			<item>The second field contains the name of the current project, which can come quite handy if you work on several projects simultaneously.</item>
			<item>The next field contains the current line and column in the main editor of the window (lines and columns start at position 1).</item>
			<item>The last three fields contain icons representing the state of the project, according to several points of view.
				<list ordered="false">
					<item>The first icon indicates whether some class files have been edited since the last compilation. This makes it easy to know whether you have changes to take into account (
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_editing.gif</url>
						</image> or
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_exe_up_to_date.gif</url>
						</image> ) and whether you should recompile.
					</item>
					<item>The second icon gives the compilation state of the project. It may indicate either that the last compilation was successful
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_compiled.gif</url>
						</image>, or that it failed
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_compilation_error.gif</url>
						</image> or that the project is being compiled
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_compiling_2.gif</url>
						</image>.
					</item>
					<item>The last icon gives the state of the debugger. It may indicate that the application is running
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_running_2.gif</url>
						</image>, paused
						<image>
							<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_stopped.gif</url>
						</image> or dead (no icon).
					</item>
				</list>
			</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>In debug mode, a window looks like this:</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelstudio/general_debug_mode.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>In debug mode, the same tools are present, but there are three extra tools. Two are located in the left panel, which display respectively the call stack and the dynamic value of expressions. The other is in the right panel and can be use to view the state of objects while debugging.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Layout configuration
		</heading>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Tool configuration
		</heading>
		<paragraph>All tools have similar controls to give their display options. It is possible to minimize, restore and maximize all tools by using the proper button in their top right-hand corner. Most tools can also be closed. These tools have a close button in the corner.</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>The minimize button
				<image>
					<height>8</height>
					<width>8</width>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_minimize_color.gif</url>
				</image>
			</item>
			<item>The maximize button
				<image>
					<height>8</height>
					<width>8</width>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_maximize_color.gif</url>
				</image>
			</item>
			<item>The restore button
				<image>
					<height>8</height>
					<width>8</width>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_restore_color.gif</url>
				</image>
			</item>
			<item>The close button
				<image>
					<height>8</height>
					<width>8</width>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_close_color.gif</url>
				</image>
			</item>
		</list>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: No more than three tools can be displayed at the same time in the left panel. Trying to add more will automatically minimize one of the displayed tools, in order to make room for the new tool.
		</note>
		<paragraph>Tools that can be closed have a corresponding entry in the 
			<bold>View/Explorer Bar</bold> menu. They also have a corresponding button in the main toolbar.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The only tools that cannot be closed are the editor, and when in debug mode the debug tools.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Toolbar configuration
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Both main toolbars can be customized. This allows to select buttons that should be displayed in the toolbars, as well as whether an explanatory text should be displayed next to icons.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Context tool
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The context tool, located in the right panel, is a major part of EiffelStudio. It itself contains several tabs that each correspond to some powerful functionality.</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>The 
				<bold>Output</bold> tab is where general information and error messages are displayed
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<bold>Diagram</bold> tab uses the BON notation to analyze and design a project
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<bold>Class</bold> tab gives advanced information concerning a class
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<bold>Feature</bold> tab gives advanced information concerning a feature
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<bold>Metrics</bold> tab provides quantitative information concerning a system or some of its components
			</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>By default, the context tool is unlinked from the rest of the window, which means all left tools refer to the object that is in the editor and the main toolbar, while the context tool (and the debug tools if they are present) displays information concerning a different object. It is possible to link the context tool, so that the whole development window displays information relative to the same development object.</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/guided_tour/index.xml</url>
				<label>EiffelStudio Guided Tour</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../10_browsing_tools/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Browsing tools</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>30_main_toolbars.xml</url>
				<label>Toolbar customization</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../20_editor/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Editor reference</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../80_formatters/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Formatted information about compiled classes and features</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../50_diagram_tool/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Diagram reference</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../60_metric_tool/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Metrics reference</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>