<document output="envision" title="Configuring Projects">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Configuring Projects</envision_title>
				<envision_pseudo_name>10</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Projects, Configuring</term>
				</keyword>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Configuring projects</term>
				</keyword>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>EiffelEnvision, Configuring projects</term>
				</keyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			A project's properties specify how a project is <link><url>../../../compiling_projects/index.xml</url><label>Built</label></link> and <link><url>../../../debugging/index.xml</url><label>Debugged</label></link>. EiffelEnvision splits project configuration's into two factions: <bold>Common Properties</bold> and <bold>Configuration Properties</bold>.
		</paragraph>

		<paragraph>
			Project build configurations can be added, removed and edited through the <help_link>
				<keywords>vxurfConfigurationManagerDialogBoxS</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Configuration Manager
			</help_link> dialog box.
		</paragraph>

		<anchor>accessing</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Accessing Project Properties</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			EiffelEnvision property pages are only available when the project is selected in Solution Explorer; property pages are not available for individual files for a EiffelEnvision project. However, you can access a file's properties in the <bold>Properties</bold> window.
		</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph>
			To access project properties:
			<list ordered="true">
				<item>With a project selected in <help_link>
					<keywords>vxurfSolutionExplorerDialog</keywords>
					<tab_index>0</tab_index>
					Solution Explorer
				</help_link>, click the <bold>Project</bold>, <italic>&lt;ProjectName&gt;</italic> <bold>Properties</bold> menu.</item>
				<item>Notice the two folders in the EiffelEnvision project's <bold>Property Pages</bold> dialog box: <bold>Common Properties</bold> and <bold>Configuration Properties</bold>. Only the properties in <bold>Configuration Properties</bold> can be set by project configuration.</item>
				<item>Using the <bold>Configuration</bold> drop-down list box and with the <bold>Configuration Properties</bold> folder selected, select the configuration for which you want to set this project's properties. If you have the <bold>Common Properties</bold> folder selected, the <bold>Configuration</bold> drop-down list box is unavailable.</item>
				<item>In the left pane, select a folder and property page.</item>
				<item>In the right pane, set the available properties.</item>
				<item>
					Click <bold>OK</bold> to save the settings. If you want a change to take effect immediately, click <bold>Apply</bold>. 
					<note>
						<bold>Note</bold>: Properties that are grayed are defined when the project is created; they are displayed for information only.
					</note>
				</item>
				<item>Properties are saved in the project's .eifp file</item>
				<item></item>
			</list>
		</paragraph>


		<anchor>descriptions</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Property Descriptions</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			A small amount of help is available in the descriptions pane beneath the project properties. Some of the descriptions begin with <bold>[Rebuild Required]</bold>. This indicates changing the property and clicking <bold>Apply</bold> will rebuild the entire project. Properties marked in this way require a project be rebuilt from scratch instead of the regular incremental compilation to make the changes take affect.
		</paragraph>
		
		<anchor>also_see</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Related Sections</content>
		</heading>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>index.xml</url><label>Configuring EiffelEnvision Projects</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>general.xml</url><label>General Properties</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<help_link>
				<keywords>vxconProjectBuilds</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Default and Custom Build
			</help_link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>../structure/index.xml</url><label>EiffelEnvision Projects</label></link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
