<document output="envision" title="Externals Properties">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Externals Properties</envision_title>
				<envision_pseudo_name>80</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Properties, Externals</term>
				</keyword>
				<keyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Externals Properties</term>
				</keyword>
				<keyword>
					<index>F</index>
					<term>ee.vs.project.configuration.config.externals</term>
				</keyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The <bold>Externals</bold> property page in the <bold>Configuration Properties</bold> folder contains contains a configurable property page for specifying include files (C/C++ header files) and object files (C/C++ <italic>*.obj</italic> and <italic>*.lib</italic>). The page is different in appearance and functionality to other property pages in the project <bold>Configuration Properties</bold>.
			<note>
				<bold>Note</bold>: Externals refer to calls into unmanaged code, which require the <link><url>build.xml</url><anchor_name>compile_unmanaged_code</anchor_name><label>Compile Unmanaged Code</label></link> property to be set to <bold>Yes</bold>. If your code does not call any unmanaged code and you have deemed it appropriate to not compile the unmanaged code during a <link><url>../../../compiling_projects/index.xml</url><label>Build</label></link>, there is no need for you to configure your project's externals properties.
			</note>
		</paragraph>
		
		<anchor>configuring</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Configuring Externals</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
The externals property page is split vertically into two sections. The top section, labeled Include Paths is to be used to specify include paths for locating C/C++ header files (<italic>*.h</italic>). The bottom section, labeled Object/Library Files, is used to individually specify Visual C/C++ compiled object files (<italic>*.obj</italic> or <italic>*.lib</italic>). 
		</paragraph>

		<anchor>adding</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Adding Externals</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			To add an external either enter the location of the external in the provided external text field adjacent to the browse ellipse button (<bold>...</bold>). Alternative use the ellipse button to locate the external using the Windows browse dialogs. Using the ellipse buttons for <bold>Include Paths</bold> will present a folder browse dialog, whereas the <bold>Object/Library Files</bold> will present a file browse dialog. Using the browse dialogs will populate the text field with your selection. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			After entering or selecting a desired external the corresponding Add button will become active. Click Add to add the specified external to the list of externals.
		</paragraph>

		<anchor>removing</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Removing Externals</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			To remove an external simply select the external path or file to be remove and click the corresponding <bold>Remove</bold> button, located below the list of externals.
		</paragraph>

		<anchor>modifying</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Modifying Existing Externals</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			To make a modification to an external already present in a list, slow double-left mouse click (the same as renaming files in Microsoft Windows Explorer) on the external in the list to modify. A line editor will appear with the selected external highlighted. Make the desired adjustments and either click outside of the line editor or press Enter. Pressing <bold>Escape</bold> will discard any changes made and closes the line editor.
		</paragraph>
				
		<anchor>also_see</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Related Sections</content>
		</heading>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>index.xml</url><label>Configuring EiffelEnvision Projects</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>debugger.xml</url><label>Debugger Properties</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>../../../compiling_projects/unmanaged_code.xml</url><label>Unmanaged Code</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<help_link>
				<keywords>vxconProjectBuilds</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Default and Custom Build
			</help_link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>../structure/index.xml</url><label>EiffelEnvision Projects</label></link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
