<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document output="envision" title="Working with Multiple Versions of the .NET Framework">
  <meta_data>
    <help>
      <toc>
        <envision_title>Working with Multiple Versions of the .NET Framework</envision_title>
        <envision_pseudo_name>90</envision_pseudo_name>
      </toc>
      <xml>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>Working with Multiple Versions of the .NET Framework</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
      </xml>
    </help>
  </meta_data>
  <paragraph>
    <paragraph>
		By default, managed applications created with Visual Studio .NET 2003 or later require version 1.1 of the <bold>Common Language Runtime</bold> (CLR) in order to run. There may be some cases where you want your application to target an earlier version of the runtime. For example, if all of your customers have only installed version 1.0 or the CLR, or deploying version 1.1 is just not feasible, you may want to target version 1.0. EiffelEnvision, unlike languages such as Visual C# and Visual Basic .NET, provides <link><url>index.xml</url><label>Project Configuration</label></link> properties to be configured achieve this.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>switching_versions</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Switching Versions</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
		To change the version of the CLR, the Eiffel for .NET compiler targets, simply change the <link><url>general.xml</url><anchor_name>target_clr_version</anchor_name><label>Target CLR Version</label></link> project configuration property. EiffelEnvision will automatically handle changing the project's assembly references for you. However, EiffelEnvision can only change those assemblies installed with the Microsoft .NET framework. Any third party assembly references must be change manually because no specification or standard exists for determining CLR version specific assembly locations.
		</paragraph>
    <warning>Referencing assemblies compiled for version 1.1 of the CLR when targeting version 1.0 may cause compilation to fail because of differences in 1.0 and 1.1. To ensure successful compilation targeting 1.0 must reference strictly components compiled for version 1.0 of the CLR.
		</warning>
    <anchor>also_see</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Related Sections</content>
    </heading>
    <seealso>
      <bold>See also</bold>:
			<line_break /><link><url>index.xml</url><label>Configuring EiffelEnvision Projects</label></link><line_break /><link><url>general.xml</url><label>General Properties</label></link><line_break /><link><url>ms-help//MS.VSCC.2003/MS.MSDNQTR.2003FEB.1033/cpguide/html/cpconside-by-sideexecution.htm</url><label>Using Side-by-Side Execution</label></link></seealso>
  </paragraph>
</document>