<document title="Preferences Sample">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>		
		<line_break/>
		<line_break/>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Compiling
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
				<list ordered="true">
					<item>Launch EiffelStudio.</item>
					<item>Select <bold>Use existing Ace (control file)</bold> and click <bold>OK</bold></item>
					<item>Browse to <italic>$ISE_EIFFEL\examples\preferences\</italic></item>
					<item>Choose the Ace file.  For saving the preferences to the Windows registry choose ace.windows.ace, for saving to XML choose ace.windows.xml.ace on Windows, otherwise ace.unix.ace</item>
					<item>Choose the directory where the project will be compiled, by default the same directory containing the Ace file.</item>
					<item>Click <bold>OK</bold>.</item>
				</list>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Running
		</heading>
		<paragraph> After launching the application, you will see a window displayed with 2 buttons.  When clicked each will display a window showing the preferences, one is the default view provided with the library, the other is a custom view for purposes of example.  The default view looks like:</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image> 
				<url>normal.png</url> 
				<alt_text>preferences_example_normal_view</alt_text>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The custom view looks like:			
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image> 
				<url>custom.png</url> 
				<alt_text>preferences_example_normal_view</alt_text>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph> In each dialog you can select the preferences and alter the values.
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>Under the Hood
			</heading>
			<paragraph>
				This example shows you how to achieve the following tasks:
				
			</paragraph>
<paragraph>
<list ordered="false"><item>Create preferences using the library supplied preference types and associated views</item>
<item>Use the default widget for viewing preferences and manipulating their values</item>
<item>Create a custom preference (a preference for storing correctly formatted directory path names)</item>
<item>Create a widget to view and change the custom preference type value</item>
<item>Create a custom manager to register custom types to the system</item>
<item>Create a custom dialog for viewing all the preferences</item>
</list></paragraph>

		</paragraph>
	</paragraph></document>
