<document title="Compiling an Eiffel system for CECIL" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>CECIL from Eiffel</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Compiling your Eiffel system for CECIL
		</heading>It is very simple to "Cecilize" your Eiffel system, that is to say make its features available from the outside through CECIL. You will compile it as you normally would - either freeze it or finalize it. The only supplementary precaution is to protect from the dead-code remover any Eiffel features that are not called from the Eiffel system's root, and might thus be dead-code-removed by the optimization mechanism.
		<paragraph>To do this, include the appropriate features and classes in the 
			<italic>visible</italic> clause of the Ace file, as in
		</paragraph>
		<code_block>
	<keyword>system</keyword>
		<italic>system_name</italic>
	<keyword>root</keyword>
		...
	<keyword>default</keyword>
		...
	<keyword>cluster</keyword>
		...
		<italic>your_cluste</italic>r<symbol>:</symbol> "..."
			<keyword>adapt</keyword>
			...
			<keyword>visible</keyword>
				<italic>CLASS1;</italic>
                			<italic>CLASS2</italic>
				<keyword>creation</keyword>
					"<italic>other_make</italic>"
				<keyword>export</keyword>
					"<italic>other_make</italic>", "<italic>feat1</italic>", "<italic>feat2</italic>"
				<keyword>end</keyword>
			<keyword>end</keyword>
	
		... Other clusters ...
	
	...
	<keyword>end</keyword></code_block>
		Here all features of 
		<italic>CLASS1</italic> are available to the external software; for 
		<italic>CLASS2</italic>, only 
		<italic>other_make</italic> (for creation) and 
		<italic>feat1</italic> and 
		<italic>feat2</italic> (for normal call) are available. For the full set of 
		<code>
			<keyword>visible</keyword>
		</code> options, see appendix D of 
		<italic>Eiffel: The Language</italic>. If you omit the clause 
		<code>
			<keyword>export</keyword>
		</code>, only the features with no export clause in the Eiffel code, will be available. The creation procedure of a visible class is always available.
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Building a CECIL archive
		</heading>The EiffelStudio compiler produces both C code and a "Makefile". The Makefile compiles and links that C code in a subdirectory one level below the EIFGEN directory of a project. For frozen/melted code, the Makefile is located in the W_code subdirectory. For finalized code, it is in the F_code subdirectory.
		<paragraph>To produce a CECIL library, you must: open a shell (unix) or the MS-DOS prompt (Windows), go to the subdirectory that contains the Makefile, and then type:</paragraph>
		<code_block>
		<bold>make cecil</bold> (on unix and on windows with Borland)<bold>
		nmake cecil</bold> (on windows with VC++)</code_block>
		<paragraph>This generates a CECIL archive whose name derived from the name &amp;lt;system name&amp;gt; of the Eiffel system, as follows:</paragraph>
		<code_block>
		lib&amp;lt;system name&amp;gt;.a (on unix)
		lib&amp;lt;system name&amp;gt;. lib (on Windows)</code_block>For example, the corresponding archive for an Eiffel system called "test", would be called either "libtest. a" (Unix) or libtest. lib (Windows).
		<paragraph>Note that through CECIL you can use an Eiffel system compiled in any of the Eiffel compilation modes:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Finalized C code. </item>
			<item>Workbench (melted/frozen) code, usually for development purposes. In this case you must copy the 
				<italic>&lt;system name&gt;. melted</italic> file ( where 
				<italic>&lt;system name&gt;</italic> is the name of your system) located in EIFGEN\W_code to the directory where you intend to execute your C application from.
			</item>
		</list>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: each time you melt the Eiffel system, the 
			<italic>&lt;system name&gt;. melted</italic> file is updated.
		</note>
		<warning>
			<bold>Caution</bold>: in the second case (workbench mode), it is not possible to call through the CECIL interface any routine that has been melted in the last compilation; this would raise the run-time exception:
			<line_break/><bold>  $ applied to melted routine</bold>
			<line_break/> The solution is simply to refreeze the system.
		</warning>
	</paragraph></document>
