<document title="Using a CECIL archive" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>Compiler</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Linking the CECIL archive into a program
		</heading>The CECIL archive already incorporates the Eiffel run-time. To use the functions provided in the CECIL archive, simply write the C programs according to the CECIL specifications of ETL, and then include the CECIL archive in the link line of your C application. This line looks like:
		<paragraph>on Unix/linux:</paragraph>
		<code_block>ld -o [name of your CECIL executable] [your C object files and archives]lib&lt;system name&gt;.a -lm</code_block>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: On Unix, linking with "-lm" is required since the Eiffel run-time uses the standard math libraries. You may need to link with other libraries (for example, on linux: with "-lbsd", in MT mode with "-lpthread" (posix threads) or "-lthread" (solaris)).
		</note>
		<paragraph/>
		<paragraph>on Windows, with MS VC++:</paragraph>
		<code_block>link [your link flags] -OUT:[name of your cecil executable] [your C object files and archives] lib&lt;system name&gt;.lib [other Windows libraries]</code_block>
		<paragraph/>
		<paragraph>on Windows with Borland:</paragraph>
		<code_block>ilink32 -ap -c -Tpe main.obj c0w32.obj, [name of your cecil executable],,EIFGEN\W_code\lib&lt;system name&gt;.lib CW32 IMPORT32 OLE2w32,,</code_block>
		<paragraph/>
		<paragraph>
			<bold>Notes for compiling CECIL C files:</bold>
			<line_break/>The CECIL library is built automatically, which is unfortunately not the case of the corresponding object files of the cecil program you wrote.
			<line_break/>The C flags to use are usually the same as the ones needed during the compilation of the generated C-code plus those which are relevant to your own C-code.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Typically, you will compile with your flags as below (if you are using gcc):</paragraph>
		<code_block>gcc -c -O -I$ISE_EIFFEL/studio/spec/$PLATFORM/include -I&lt;SOME_INCLUDE_PATH&gt; -D&lt;SOME_FLAGS&gt; your_file.c</code_block>
		<paragraph>or , if you are on Windows using MS VC++:</paragraph>
		<code_block>cl -c -nologo -Ox -I$ISE_EIFFEL\studio\spec\windows\include -I&lt;SOME_INCLUDE_PATH&gt; -D&lt;SOME_FLAGS&gt; your_file.c</code_block>
		<paragraph>or, if you are on Windows using Borland:</paragraph>
		<code_block>bcc32 -c -I$ISE_EIFFEL\studio\spec\windows\include -I&lt;SOME_INCLUDE_PATH&gt; -D&lt;SOME_FLAGS&gt; your_file.c</code_block>
		<sample>
			<bold>Sample</bold>: if you want to use the multithreaded facilities of Eiffel, you should define the EIFFEL MT flags by adding "-DEIF_THREADS" to the command line and follow the instructions of your C compiler and platform to find out which additional flags you may need 
			<bold>. For example:</bold> on Solaris you need to add "-DSOLARIS_THREADS -D_REENTRANT".
		</sample>
		<paragraph>You can specify a Makefile in your Ace file, so that your C files will be compiled automatically after the Eiffel compilation and before the final linking. Just add at the end of your Ace file in the external clause:</paragraph>
		<code_block>external:"$PATH_TO_MAKEFILE/your_makefile";</code_block>
		<paragraph>This makefile will be run from the $/EIFGEN/W_code or $/EIFGEN/F_code directory. You should not give the CECIL executable the same name as your system, because it will be replaced by the Eiffel executable when you run another compilation. </paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Initializing the Eiffel run-time
		</heading>Even though the main thread of control resides in the "C side" of the program, the Eiffel run-time must be initialized correctly before it can use CECIL facilities to communicate with the Eiffel world.
		<paragraph>In the C file containing the "main" C function, you must add the following line to include the header file "eif_setup. h" provided with this example:</paragraph>
		<code_block>
#include "eif_setup.h"  /* Macros EIF_INITIALIZE and EIF_DISPOSE_ALL */
#include "eif_eiffel.h" /* Exported functions of the Eiffel run-time */</code_block>
		<paragraph>Your "main" function must have the three standard arguments of the C "main" function: "argc", "argv" and "envp" and include the following macros that are defined in "eif_setup. h":</paragraph>
		<code_block>
int main(int argc, char **argv, char **envp)
	/* Please respect this signature: `argc', `argv' and `envp' are used * in EIF_INITIALIZE. */
{
		/* declarations of variables */
		/* Initialize the Eiffel run-time. */
	EIF_INITIALIZE(failure)
	
/* body of your "main" function */

	/* Reclaim the memory allocated by the Eiffel run-time. */
EIF_DISPOSE_ALL
}</code_block>
		<note>
			<bold>Notes</bold>:
			<line_break/>The above mentioned macros must imperatively be in the body of the "main" function for the Eiffel exception handling mechanism to work correctly.
			<bold/> You also need to add the Eiffel run time directory to the list of directories in which the C compiler searches for include files. You can do so by using the "-I" option of your C compiler.
			<bold/> You can only link one CECIL library into your C applications at a time.
		</note>
		<warning>
			<bold>Caution</bold>: Even though external object files and archives are correctly specified in the "object" clause of the Ace file, you will need to explicitly link them to your C application.
		</warning>
	</paragraph></document>
