<document title="CECIL - Eiffel to C" output="studio"><meta_data ><help /></meta_data><paragraph ><heading ><size >2</size>array</heading><paragraph >This example shows how to create a C array from an existing Eiffel array. </paragraph><paragraph >After you have done the appropriate steps to compile the example, you will get a `cecil.exe' on windows, or `cecil' on Unix. </paragraph><paragraph >Launch the program and you will be prompted for 10 integers that will be inserted in an Eiffel array, it will then initialize the C array and display it. </paragraph><paragraph >A typical output will be:</paragraph>
<code_block >
$ ./cecil
This example create n array on the Eiffel side and print it on the C side
Enter 10 integers:
1
2
3
4
5
6
7
8
9
10

Displaying from C
@1 = 1
@2 = 2
@3 = 3
@4 = 4
@5 = 5
@6 = 6
@7 = 7
@8 = 8
@9 = 9
@10 = 10
</code_block>



<heading ><size >2</size>object</heading>This example shows the Eiffel memory management and all issues when passing an Eiffel object reference to C. In the example, you can edit the file `root_class.e' to modify the example:
<code_block >
--	give_to_c (o1)
	give_to_c_by_pointer ($o1) -- Choose the way you pass it
</code_block>



When you choose the firt possibility (commented by default), give_to_c will use the CECIL API eif_adopt to keep a reference on the Eiffel object. When you choose the second possibility, give_to_c_by_pointer will use the CECIL API eif_protect to keep a reference on the Eiffel object. Until forget_from_c is called from the C side, the object o1 will not be collected since we have protected it through the call to give_to_c or give_to_c_by_pointer. At the end after the object o1 is collected, we try to perform an operation on it which will fail with a call on void target exception. A typical output will be:
<code_block >
$ cecil
Creating o1
Object string is o1
Give it to C
Losing reference to initial o1 from Eiffel
Collecting...
Display new o1:
Object string is o2
Display o1 given to C:
Object string is o1
Losing reference from C
Losing reference from Eiffel
Collecting...
An Eiffel object of type OBJECT is collected
Old o1 forgot from both C and Eiffel:
Raise a Void exception..

cecil: system execution failed.
Following is the set of recorded exceptions:

-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
Class / Object Routine Nature of exception Effect
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
ROOT_CLASS make @26 display:
&lt;30068030&gt; Feature call on void target. Fail
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
ROOT_CLASS make @26
&lt;30068030&gt; Routine failure. Fail
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
ROOT_CLASS root's creation
&lt;30068030&gt; Routine failure. Exit
-------------------------------------------------------------------------------
An Eiffel object of type OBJECT is collected
</code_block>



<heading ><size >2</size>string</heading>This example shows how to create a C string from an existing Eiffel string. After you have done the appropriate steps to compile the example, you will get a `cecil.exe' on windows, or `cecil' on Unix. Launch the program and you will be prompted for a string from Eiffel and a C string will be created and display. A typical output will be:
<code_block >
$ cecil
Enter a string to convert into a C string:
Hello World!

Here is the C string:
Hello World!
</code_block>

</paragraph></document>