<document title="EiffelBase Introduction">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_location>Class Libraries\EiffelBase</envision_location>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph> EiffelBase, covered by the open-source 
			<link>
				<url>/general/licenses/iffel.xml</url>
				<label> IFFEL License</label>
			</link>, is one of the principal contributions of Eiffel: a library of fundamental structures and algorithms covering the basics of computing, and resulting from a "Linnaean" effort at a general-purpose taxonomy of computing structures. 
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Components
		</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>The 
				<link>
					<url>content/10_kernel/index.xml</url>
					<label>Kernel</label>
				</link> cluster include core classes used in all Eiffel systems. These include a universal class providing facilities potentially useful for all classes: ANY. Every class is a descendant of this classes. The kernel also defines classes needed for exception handling, standard arithmetic operations, hashable elements for use with hash tables and basic arithmetic conversions.
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<link>
					<url>content/20_structures/index.xml</url>
					<label>Data Structure</label>
				</link> cluster provides implementations of fundamental data structures and algorithms: Abstract structures, describing broad categories; lists in their various forms; list elements; circular chains; sorted sets and lists; various trees and binary trees; cursor trees; hash tables (dictionaries); various stacks, queues and priority queues; and more.
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<link>
					<url>content/30_support/index.xml</url>
					<label>Support</label>
				</link> cluster provides helper classes for specific needs. These needs include basic math support, random numbers generation, and a few other topics such as the list of ASCII constants.
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<link>
					<url>content/40_desc/index.xml</url>
					<label>Dynamic External Shared Call (DESC)</label>
				</link> cluster provides mechanisms to call DLL functions at runtime.
			</item>
		</list>
	</paragraph></document>