<document title="EiffelStudio 6.1 for Mac OS X" output="studio">
	<meta_data></meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Requirements</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<table>
				<row><cell>Computer/Processor</cell><cell>G4</cell></row>
				<row><cell>Operating System</cell><cell>Mac OS X 10.4 (Tiger) or above</cell></row>
				<row><cell>Memory</cell><cell>512MB of RAM (1GB recommended)</cell></row>
				<row><cell>Hard Disk</cell><cell>400MB of hard disk space (1GB recommended) </cell></row>
				<row><cell>Drive</cell><cell>CD-ROM or DVD drive (not required when downloading EiffelStudio)</cell></row>
				<row><cell>Display</cell><cell>1024 x 768 or higher resolution video adapter and monitor</cell></row>
				<row><cell>Peripherals</cell><cell>Keyboard and mouse or compatible pointing device</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>ISE_PLATFORM</bold></cell><cell><bold>macosx-ppc</bold> or <bold>macosx-x86</bold>.</cell></row>
			</table>
		</paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Prerequisites</heading>
		<paragraph>Before installing EiffelStudio 6.1, it is necessary to install X11 for Mac OS X and the X11 SDK. They are available with the OS X CD. For more details check the Apple web site at:
			<list ordered="false">
				<item><link><url>http://www.apple.com/macosx/features/x11/</url><label>http://www.apple.com/macosx/features/x11/</label></link></item>
			</list>
			<paragraph>You also need to install the latest Apple Developer Tools (XCode) available as part of Mac OS X (Tiger or above)</paragraph>
		</paragraph>

		<heading><size>2</size>Installing the Free Edition</heading>
		<paragraph>After downloading the <bold>Eiffel61.dmg</bold> installation package, double click on it to mount the disk image. Then double click on the <bold>Eiffel61.pkg</bold> file to launch the installation procedure. Follow the steps indicated in the dialogs to complete the installation.</paragraph>

		<heading><size>2</size>Installing the Enterprise Edition</heading>
		<paragraph>Insert the CD into your CD-ROM drive. Open the CD-ROM contents and double click on the <bold>Eiffel61.pkg</bold> file to launch the installation procedure. Follow the steps indicated in the dialogs to complete the installation.</paragraph>
		<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/mac_setup.png</url><alt_text>Setup dialog</alt_text></image></paragraph>
			<paragraph>Run EiffelStudio, located at /Developers/Applications/Eiffel61/EiffelStudio. Enter the information located inside the box that contains your copy of the EiffelStudio Enterprise Edition. Once the information is correct, the <bold>Register</bold> button will be enabled. Click <bold>Register</bold> to actually register EiffelStudio.</paragraph>

			<paragraph>You now need to launch EiffelStudio to register your copy. Follow the instructions located in the <bold>Starting EiffelStudio</bold> section below. The first time you launch EiffelStudio, you will be asked for an activation key through the following dialog:</paragraph>
			<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/mac_registration.png</url><alt_text>Registration dialog</alt_text></image></paragraph>
			<paragraph>By clicking on the <link><url>http://activate.eiffel.com</url><label>http://activate.eiffel.com</label></link> URL, a new web browser will appear with the requested fields automatically filled in with the appropriate information. Simply click <bold>Activate</bold> and a new page with an activation code will appear. Copy and paste the activation code in the first field and the <bold>Activate</bold> button should be enabled to let you activate your copy.</paragraph><paragraph> You can activate your copy up to three times. Once you have reached this threshold and need to reinstall your copy, contact Eiffel Software to request one more activation.</paragraph>
			<paragraph>If no web broswer appears, it is most likely because Safari is not installed on your machine or is not in your path. Instead you should manually launch a new web browser and go to the page <link><url>http://activate.eiffel.com</url><label>http://activate.eiffel.com</label></link> and enter the information manually. Then follow the above instructions as if the browser had been properly launched.</paragraph>
			<paragraph>You may receive the following dialog when launching EiffelStudio:</paragraph>
			<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/mac_registration_error.png</url><alt_text>Registration incomplete</alt_text></image></paragraph>
			<paragraph>This probably means that the <bold>register</bold> program was not launched or did not succeed in storing data to the following file <bold>/Developer/Applications/Eiffel61/EiffelStudio.app/Contents/Resources/Eiffel61/install/limand/.ec_license</bold>. To solve this, rerun the <bold>register</bold> program with a user account that has permissions to write at <bold>/Developer/Applications/Eiffel61/EiffelStudio.app/Contents/Resources/Eiffel61/install/limand</bold> and enter your <bold>Username</bold> and <bold>CD Key</bold>.</paragraph>
	

		<heading><size>2</size>Starting EiffelStudio</heading>
		<paragraph>Now everything should be properly installed and you should be able to run the compiler. You can now launch EiffelStudio from the Finder under <bold>/Developer/Applications/Eiffel61/</bold>. If you are a new user to EiffelStudio, we recommend that you follow <link><url>../../general/guided_tour/studio/index.xml</url><label>the guided tour</label></link>.</paragraph>

	</paragraph>
</document>
