<document title="EiffelStudio 6.2 for HP OpenVMS" output="studio">
	<meta_data></meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Requirements</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<table>
				<row><cell><bold>Computer/Processor</bold></cell><cell>AlphaServer.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Operating System</bold></cell><cell>HP OpenVMS/Alpha version 7.3.2 with DECWindows and GTK+ 1.2.10.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>C compiler</bold></cell><cell>Compaq C compiler V6 or later.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Memory</bold></cell><cell>512MB of RAM (1GB recommended).</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Hard Disk</bold></cell><cell>1GB free disk space on an ODS-5 formatted volume, plus an additional 1GB of free space while performing the software installation.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Drive</bold></cell><cell>CD-ROM or DVD drive (not required when downloading EiffelStudio).</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Display</bold></cell><cell>1024 x 768 or higher resolution video adapter and monitor.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Peripherals</bold></cell><cell>Keyboard and mouse or compatible pointing device.</cell></row>
			</table>
		</paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Checking your environment</heading>
		<paragraph>EiffelStudio 6.2 requires GTK+ 1.2.10 or above to function properly. You can check that you have this installed correctly by typing the following command:<code_block>gtk-config --version</code_block>The command should succeed and the version number of GTK+ should appear. If it is not 1.2.10 or above then you cannot continue the installation of EiffelStudio. You first need to install GTK+ 1.2.10.</paragraph>

		<heading><size>2</size>Installing the Enterprise Edition</heading>
		<heading><size>3</size>From the Web</heading>
		<paragraph>After downloading the <bold>eif62vms.zip</bold> installation package, unzip the distribution into temp:[dir] where where temp:[dir] is the location of a temporary directory:</paragraph>
		<code_block>unzip eif62vms.zip temp:[dir]</code_block>
		<paragraph>And use the following commands to install the files into eiffel_installation_path where eiffel_installation_path is a device:[directory] on an ODS-5 volume:</paragraph>
		<code_block>set file/attrib=(org:seq,rfm:fix,lrl:9216) temp:[dir]eif62vms.save
backup temp:[dir]eif62vms.save/save eiffel_installation_path</code_block>

		<heading><size>3</size>From a CD</heading>
		<paragraph>You must mount the installation CD-ROM volume with the following qualifier:</paragraph>
		<code_block>mount cd_dev:/media_format=cdrom/undefined_fat=fixed:cr:9216</code_block>
		<paragraph>where cd_dev: is the CD-ROM device. And use the following commands to install the files into eiffel_installation_path where eiffel_installation_path is a device:[directory] on an ODS-5 volume:</paragraph>
		<code_block>backup cd_dev:[000000]eif62vms.save/save eiffel_installation_path</code_block>

		
		<heading><size>3</size>Completing the installation</heading>		
		<paragraph>You must define a system-wide rooted logical name to reference the installation directory, for instance:</paragraph>
		<code_block>define/system EIFFEL62 eiffel_installation_path:[directory.] /trans=conceal</code_block>
		<paragraph>To use EiffelStudio for VMS, run the setup procedure to define the environment:
		<code_block>@eiffel_installation_path:[000000]setup</code_block>
		This will define the logical names and DCL symbols required to run Eiffel.</paragraph>

		<paragraph>Once the files are copied and once the environment is setup up set, you need to register EiffelStudio. To do so type the following command:</paragraph>
		<code_block>RUN ISE_EIFFEL:[000000]register</code_block>
		<paragraph>A dialog asking for your <bold>Username</bold> and <bold>CD Key</bold> should appear as it does below:</paragraph>
		<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/unix_setup.png</url><alt_text>Setup dialog</alt_text></image></paragraph>
		<paragraph>Enter the information located inside the box that contains your copy of the EiffelStudio Enterprise Edition. Once the information is correct, the <bold>Register</bold> button will be enabled. Click <bold>Register</bold> to actually register EiffelStudio.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The first time you launch EiffelStudio, you will be asked for an activation key through the following dialog:</paragraph>
		<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/unix_registration.png</url><alt_text>Registration dialog</alt_text></image></paragraph>
		<paragraph>By clicking on the <link><url>http://activate.eiffel.com</url><label>http://activate.eiffel.com</label></link> URL, a new web browser will appear with the requested fields automatically filled in with the appropriate information. Simply click <bold>Activate</bold> and a new page with an activation code will appear. Copy and paste the activation code in the first field and the <bold>Activate</bold> button should be enabled to let you activate your copy.</paragraph><paragraph> You can activate your copy up to three times. Once you have reached this threshold and need to reinstall your copy, contact Eiffel Software to request one more activation.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>If no web broswer appears, it is most likely because netscape is not installed on your machine or is not in your path. Instead you should manually launch a new web browser and go to the page <link><url>http://activate.eiffel.com</url><label>http://activate.eiffel.com</label></link> and enter the information manually. Then follow the above instructions as if the browser had been properly launched.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You may receive the following dialog when launching EiffelStudio:</paragraph>
		<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/unix_registration_error.png</url><alt_text>Registration incomplete</alt_text></image></paragraph>
		<paragraph>This probably means that the <bold>register</bold> program was not launched or did not succeed in storing data to the following file ISE_EIFFEL:[install.limand].ec_license. To solve this, rerun the <bold>register</bold> program with a user account that has permissions to write at ISE_EIFFEL:[install.limand] and enter your <bold>Username</bold> and <bold>CD Key</bold>.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Once this is done you can jump to the next section "Using EiffelStudio."</paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>
