<document title="EiffelStudio 6.2 for Windows" output="studio">
	<meta_data></meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Requirements</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<table>
				<row><cell><bold>Computer/Processor</bold></cell><cell>PC with 300 MHz or higher Pentium II class processor or equivalent recommended.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Operating System</bold></cell><cell>Windows NT/2000/XP/2003/Vista (.NET support is for Microsoft Windows 2000, XP and 2003 only).</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Memory</bold></cell><cell>512MB of RAM (1GB recommended).</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Hard Disk</bold></cell><cell>500MB of hard disk space (1GB recommended). Hard disk space requirements will vary depending on configuration; custom installation choices may require more or less space. Space required for installation of the Microsoft .NET Framework will also be required.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Drive</bold></cell><cell>CD-ROM drive (not required when downloading EiffelStudio).</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Display</bold></cell><cell>1024 x 768 or higher resolution video adapter and monitor.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>Peripherals</bold></cell><cell>Keyboard and mouse or compatible pointing device.</cell></row>
				<row><cell><bold>ISE_PLATFORM</bold></cell><cell><bold>windows</bold> for 32 bits version of Windows, <bold>win64</bold> for 64 bits version of Windows.</cell></row>
			</table>
		</paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Installing EiffelStudio from the Web</heading>
			<paragraph>After downloading the <bold>Eiffel62.msi</bold> installation package, right click on it and select <bold>Install</bold>. This will launch the installation procedure. Follow the steps indicated in the dialogs to complete the installation.</paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Installing the Enterprise Edition.</heading>
			<paragraph>Insert the CD into your CD-ROM drive. If you have the autorun facility enabled, the installation process will automatically be launched. 
			Otherwise you can launch it by executing <bold>Eiffel62.msi</bold> located at the root of the CD. 
			During the installation you will be asked for your <bold>Username</bold> and <bold>CD Key</bold></paragraph>
			<paragraph>Enter the information located inside the box that contains your copy of the EiffelStudio Enterprise Edition, or that you will have received via email.
			 Once the information is correct, the <bold>Next</bold> button will be enabled. Click <bold>Next</bold> and follow the steps indicated in the dialogs to complete the installation.</paragraph>
			<paragraph>Once installed, the first time you launch EiffelStudio, you will be asked for an activation key through the following dialog:</paragraph>
			<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/windows_registration.png</url><alt_text>Registration dialog</alt_text></image></paragraph>
			<paragraph>By clicking on the <link><url>http://activate.eiffel.com</url><label>http://activate.eiffel.com</label></link> URL, a new web browser will appear with the requested fields automatically filled in with the appropriate information. Simply click <bold>Activate</bold> and a new page with an activation code will appear. Copy and paste the activation code in the first field and the <bold>Activate</bold> button should be enabled to let you activate your copy.</paragraph><paragraph> You can activate your copy up to three times. Once you have reached this threshold and need to reinstall your copy, contact Eiffel Software to request one more activation.</paragraph>
			<paragraph>You may receive the following dialog when launching EiffelStudio:</paragraph>
			<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment><image><url>../../images/installation/56/windows_registration_error.png</url><alt_text>Registration incomplete</alt_text></image></paragraph>
			<paragraph>This probably means that EiffelStudio was not properly installed using the <bold>setup.exe</bold> program. Uninstall EiffelStudio and rerun the installation procedure by making sure to launch <bold>setup.exe</bold> and enter your <bold>Username</bold> and <bold>CD Key</bold>.</paragraph>

		<heading><size>2</size>.NET Support</heading>
			<paragraph>To enable .NET support in EiffelStudio, it is necessary to install the Microsoft .NET Framework prior to starting the installation of EiffelStudio. EiffelStudio currently supports versions 1.0 and 1.1 of the .NET Framework. Partial support for the .NET Framework 2.0 beta has been added in this version of EiffelStudio.</paragraph>

		<heading><size>2</size>What about Windows 95, 98 and Me?</heading>
		<paragraph>EiffelStudio will not run on Windows 95, 98 and Me. Contact Eiffel Software directly if you need support for those OSes. EiffelStudio generated code could run on 95, 98 and Me if no UI is being used. If the UI is used it could run but it requires installing the Microsoft Layer for Unicode.</paragraph>

		<heading><size>2</size>Starting EiffelStudio</heading>
		<paragraph>Now everything should be properly installed and you should be able to run the compiler. You can now launch EiffelStudio from the Start menu or from the EiffelStudio shortcut on your desktop. If you are a new user to EiffelStudio, we recommend that you follow <link><url>../../general/guided_tour/studio/index.xml</url><label>the guided tour</label></link>.</paragraph>
			
	</paragraph>
</document>
