<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document output="envision" title="What's New in EiffelEnvision 2.6">
  <meta_data>
    <help>
      <toc>
        <envision_title>What's New in EiffelEnvision 2.6</envision_title>
        <envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
      </toc>
      <xml>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>What's New in EiffelEnvision</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>EiffelEnvision, What's New</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
      </xml>
    </help>
  </meta_data>
  <paragraph>
    <paragraph>
			The <bold>2.6</bold> release of <bold>EiffelEnvision</bold> brings with it a wealth of improvements and enhancements to features present in previous releases of EiffelEnvision/Eiffel ENViSioN! as well as a number of additions. 
			The items mention here are only some of the major additions and improvements made to EiffelEnvision. For a complete taxonomy of changes in EiffelEnvision, please review the <link><url>history/versions/eiffelenvision_26.xml</url><label>EiffelEnvision 2.6 Version History</label></link> document.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>project_properties</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Project Properties</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
		A <link><url>../using_eiffelenvision/eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/build_events.xml</url><label>Build Events</label></link> configuration dependent property page has been added to the project configuration properties. As a developer, pre and post-build actions can be supplied to executed when applicable.
	</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
    	Projects can now specify a project configuration dependent deployment/debug location for built output produced by and EiffelEnvision build. This supports the need to be able to compound multiple project outputs into one location for the purpose of debugging.
	</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
		The way projects are configured has also changed. EiffelEnvision 2.5 abstracts a number of <bold>Project Configuration Properties</bold> to create a set of <bold>Common Properties</bold> in order to facilitate users in configuring projects faster and with less errors when changing between <link><url>ms-help//MS.VSCC.2003/MS.MSDNQTR.2003FEB.1033/vsintro7/html/vxconBuildConfigurations.htm</url><label>Build Configurations</label></link>. In addition to this abstraction, a number of project Configuration Properties have been added, such as Eiffel <link><url>../using_eiffelenvision/compiling_projects/debug_clauses.xml</url><label>Debug Clauses</label></link> and advanced properties to tweak compilation.
	</paragraph>
    <anchor>compilation</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Compilation</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
		EiffelEnvision's now uses the Eiffel for .NET 5.6 compiler so project sources, including new 5.6 syntax, can be shared between EiffelStudio 5.6, EiffelEnvision 2.6 and Eiffel for ASP.NET 5.6.
	</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
    	EiffelEnvision's Eiffel for .NET compiler extends the 5.6 compiler to support non-<link><url>ms-help//MS.VSCC.2003/MS.MSDNQTR.2003FEB.1033/cpguide/html/cpconwhatiscommonlanguagespecification.htm</url><label>CLS-compliant</label></link> assemblies, type and their members.
	</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
		For changes to the Eiffel compiler, please see <link><url>../../eiffelstudio/reference/30_compiler/60_version_history/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel Compiler Version History</label></link>.
	</paragraph>
    <anchor>editor</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Eiffel Editor</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
			The <link><url>../using_eiffelenvision/eiffel_editor/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel Editor</label></link> has been improved over the previou versions of EiffelEnvision. There have been a number of bug fixes, ehancements to <link><url>../using_eiffelenvision/eiffel_editor/intellisense.xml</url><label>intellisense</label></link> features. The editor also has a fresher look with a new icon set for the <link><url>../using_eiffelenvision/eiffel_editor/browse_and_navigation.xml</url><anchor_name>feature_list</anchor_name><label>feature list</label></link> and completion box. Overall performance has also been improved upon so scrolling and selecting text regions is much faster and smoother.
	</paragraph>
	<paragraph>
			<link><url>../using_eiffelenvision/eiffel_editor/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel Editor</label></link> has also been updated to support all of the new Eiffel 5.6 syntax constuctors, paving the way to <link><url>http://www.ecma-international.org/publications/standards/Ecma-367.htm</url><label>ECMA-Eiffel</label></link>.
	</paragraph>
    <anchor>new_tools</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>New Tools</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
			New to EiffelEnvision 2.6 is the <link><url>../../compliance_checker/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker Tool</label></link>. The tools acts as an aid to verify assemblies produced by third-party vendors adhere to the new notion of 
			<link><url>../../../technologies/dotnet/eiffel_dotnet_language/20_language/85_eiffel_compliance.xml</url><label>Eiffel-compliance</label></link>. The tool can be used by both a consumer of a assembly and by those developers wishing to ensure that their
			classes and their interfaces can successfully be used from Eiffel for .NET.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>libraries</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Libraries and Samples</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
	    EiffelEnvision 2.6 comes complete with new Graph and Preferences library intorduced into the Eiffel 5.6 library set. With the addition of the libraries three new examples have been added; edraw, egraph and an example to show off the preferences library.
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>more</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>More...</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
			There are many, many more additions, enhancements and improvements in EiffelEnvision 2.6, which through reading this documentation, or using EiffelEnvision, you will discover. 
			EiffelEnvision will be intuitive for those who have used Visual Studio .NET before and have a knowledge of the <link><url>../../../technologies/dotnet/eiffel_dotnet_language/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel Language</label></link>. For those who have 
			not used Visual Studio .NET before should become accustomed to the plethora of features it provides, which EiffelEnvision integrates into and expands upon.Those who have not yet used 
			Eiffel and this is your introduction to it, then it is recommended you become familiar with the <link><url>../../../technologies/dotnet/eiffel_dotnet_language/20_language/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel Language</label></link> and read <link><url>../../../general/guided_tour/language/invitation-00.xml</url><label>An Invitation to Eiffel</label></link>.
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
      <line_break />
			We sincerely hope you enjoy the new features of EiffelEnvision 2.6,
			<line_break />
			EiffelEnvision 2.6 Team.
		</paragraph>
  </paragraph>
</document>
