<document title="Pick-and-drop mechanism" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>pick, drop, drag</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>Pick-and-drop is one of ISE's exclusive technologies and is provided by 
			<link>
				<url>/libraries/vision2/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Eiffel Vision2</label>
			</link>.In EiffelStudio it allows you to easily send data from a component of the interface to another.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You can pick every reference to a 
			<bold>development object</bold>(like a class, a feature or an execution object) with a single click on the 
			<bold>right</bold> mouse button. Then as you start moving the mouse around - not pressing any of its buttons - a pebble tracks the cursor position, and a line continuously connects the pebble to the object's original position. The pebble's shape indicates the type of the development object that you picked (oval disk for a class, cross for a feature, folder for a cluster...).
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelstudio/editor_pick_and_drop.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You may terminate this situation in either of two ways:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>If the pebble you are dragging is not crossed, you can right-click again to confirm the pick-and-drop and so effectively send the dragged development object to the targeted component. For a class, a droppable pebble looks like this:
				<image>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/class.gif</url>
				</image>
				<paragraph>Right-clicking when the pebble is crossed will only stop the pick-and-drop because the component you are hovering with the mouse does not accept your development object. For a class, a not droppable pebble looks like this:
					<image>
						<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/Xclass.gif</url>
					</image>
				</paragraph>
			</item>
			<item>If, for any reason, you change your mind, you can cancel the pick-and-drop by left-clicking anywhere or by pressing the Escape key.</item>
		</list>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>20_pick_and_drop_shortcut.xml</url>
				<label>Pick-and-drop shortcut</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>