<document output="studio" title="EiffelWeb Sample">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph> This sample shows how to retrieve and display information from a            basic form on a web page.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<note>
				<bold>Note:</bold> This sample requires a web server supporting CGI in            order to be run. Both the Internet Information Services web server            from Microsoft and the GNU Apache server may be used.
				<heading>
					<size>2</size>Compiling
				</heading>
				<paragraph> To compile the example: </paragraph>
				<list ordered="false">
					<item>Launch EiffelStudio. </item>
					<item>Select 
						<bold>Use existing Ace (control file)</bold> and click 
						<bold>OK</bold>. 
					</item>
					<item>Browse to 
						<italic>$ISE_EIFFEL\examples\web\basic\</italic>. 
					</item>
					<item>Choose 
						<italic>Ace.ace</italic> on Windows platforms or 
						<italic>Ace.ace</italic> on Unix platforms. 
					</item>
					<item>Choose the directory where the project will be compiled, by default the same directory containing the Ace file. </item>
					<item>Click 
						<bold>OK</bold>.
					</item>
				</list>
				<paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Installing
					</heading>
					<paragraph>The workbench version of the example (i.e. the version        compiled either by melting or freezing) relies on the file 
						<italic>        web_demo.melted</italic> to execute properly. However the process is        launched by the web server which means that this file will not be in the        
						<italic>path</italic> of the application. It is possible to set a registry entry        that will tell the Eiffel runtime where to find this file. The sample includes the file 
						<italic>web.reg</italic>        that you can edit by replacing the line:
					</paragraph>
					<code>"MELT_PATH"="c:\\eiffel55\\examples\\web\\basic\\EIFGEN\\W_code"</code>
					<paragraph>        with the path to the 
						<italic>W_Code</italic> folder where you have compiled the        example (the 
						<italic>W_Code</italic> folder is located underneath the 
						<italic>Eifgen</italic>        folder). Once you have edited the file, simply double click it to        register the changes in the registry (click 
						<italic>Yes </italic>when prompted).
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>        You should then copy the file 
						<italic>web_demo.exe</italic> in the 
						<italic>cgi_bin</italic>        directory of your web server and the file 
						<italic>sample.html</italic> in a        directory on the web server.
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>        Running
					</heading>
					<paragraph>        To run the example, access the page 
						<italic>sample.html</italic> that you copied        on the web server with a web browser (typically 
						<italic>        http://localhost/sample.html</italic>). Fill in the text field with a        username and click 
						<italic>Submit</italic>. You should see a page displaying the        name you jsut entered. Although not earth-shattering, this sample shows        the basis for building more complex forms processing in Eiffel.
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Under the Hood
					</heading>
					<paragraph> This basic sample has just one class <code><class_name>SAMPLE</class_name></code> which inherits from <code><class_name>CGI_INTERFACE. SAMPLE</class_name></code> implements execute which retrieves the name entered in the form and creates a new <code><class_name>HTML</class_name></code> page with it. </paragraph>
					<paragraph> </paragraph>
					<paragraph> See the 
						<link>
							<url>root_cluster/index.xml</url>
							<label>reference</label>
						</link> for the class interfaces. 
					</paragraph>
				</paragraph>
			</note>
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph></document>
