<document title="Tuning a program" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>The best way to speed up a program is of course to improve the algorithms and data structures you are using. Spotting the functions that slow down the execution and improving can change a lot in a program. 
			<link>
				<url>../50_running_and_debugging/70_profiling.xml</url>
				<label>Profiling</label>
			</link> can be used for this.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Try to keep the number of classes and objects in your system as low as possible to ensure maximum efficiency. This should never hinder the design of the system, though.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You can also use the functionality provided by the 
			<link>
				<url>/libraries/base/reference/kernel/classic/memory_chart.xml</url>
				<label>MEMORY class</label>
			</link> to tweak the garbage collector behavior according to your needs. However, be careful with this, since providing erroneous parameters might lead to memory leaks, huge memory consumption, or on the contrary a dramatic slow down of the application. If you are not entirely sure what a parameter is for, avoid changing it. The default values should fit for most standard applications.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>On top of that, EiffelStudio provides powerful optimizations, some being done automatically, others being configurable. To obtain a maximum efficiency, it is recommended to 
			<link>
				<url>10_generating_executables.xml</url>
				<label>Finalize</label>
			</link> your program from scratch and without using precompiled libraries.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>In the 
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/25_project_settings/60_advanced.xml</url>
				<label>Project Settings dialog advanced tab</label>
			</link>, try experimenting the 
			<bold>Inlining</bold> option, and setting the maximum size of features that should be inlined. Only Eiffel features are inlined by this option, to see how to inline the C functions you may be using in your program, please refer to your C compiler documentation.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>In the 
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/25_project_settings/60_advanced.xml</url>
				<label>Project Settings advanced tab</label>
			</link>, enabling the 
			<bold>Dead code removal</bold> will help produce smaller executables.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Removing the 
			<bold>Execution Trace</bold> will optimize the executable in size and speed, but in case of crash no information will be available.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You can also enable the 
			<bold>Array optimization</bold> option to slightly speed up array access.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>All these options are located in the 
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/25_project_settings/60_advanced.xml</url>
				<label>Project Settings</label>
			</link> dialog, under the 
			<bold>Advanced</bold> tab. They are only effective during finalizations.
		</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/> 
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/70_wizards_and_dialogs/10_profiler_wizard/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Profiler reference</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
