<document title="Execution replay" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
<paragraph>	
	<paragraph>This new feature allows the user to record the debuggee execution, and when it is stopped to replay the recording. One could see this feature as a rewind/forward, or undo/redo of the execution calls.
	In practise, the debugger is recording the effective routine calls, and keep the object's values; when you replay the debugger will restore the recorded object's values. This way you can use the debugger's tools to inspect the values.
	</paragraph>
	<warning>For performance reason, the debugger keeps only the last <code>{RT_DBG_EXECUTION_RECORDER}.max_record_count</code> object's records. For now, you can change that initial value by editing <code>{RT_EXTENSION}.new_execution_recorder</code>.
	</warning>
	<paragraph>This functionality is graphically available on the Call stack tool, or though the "Execution" menu (former "Debug" menu).
	</paragraph>
	<paragraph>When you start debugging, at some point you decide to start recording, click on the "record" button:</paragraph>	
	<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment>
	<image><url>../../../../images/eiffelstudio/debugger/exec_replay_00.png</url></image>
	</paragraph>

	<paragraph>During the debugging, we decide to stop and replay the recent execution recording, as you can notice the "Recording" button is enabled, thus we can start replaying by clicking the "Replay" button</paragraph>	
	<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment>
	<image><url>../../../../images/eiffelstudio/debugger/exec_replay_01.png</url></image>
	</paragraph>
	
	<paragraph>Now we are in "execution replay" mode, as you can notice the "Replay" button is enabled, and there is a new commands bar with "Replay Back", "Replay Forth", and the number of available "moves". <line_break></line_break>
	The red arrow show the replayed call stack level, and the call stack levels which can be replayed have a light blue background. 
	<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment>
	<image><url>../../../../images/eiffelstudio/debugger/exec_replay_02.png</url></image>
	</paragraph>
	
	<paragraph>Here we clicked on "Replay Back" twice, you can now also "Replay Forth" twice. When you execute a "Replay" operation, the debugger restores the related recorded values, and the various debugger tools are updated with tools values (including the watch tools)</paragraph>	
	<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment>
	<image><url>../../../../images/eiffelstudio/debugger/exec_replay_03.png</url></image>
	</paragraph>

	<paragraph>You can still select other call stack level as you do in normal debugging mode to inspect them, in this case the red arrow stick to the replayed call, and the green arrow show you the selected call stack level.</paragraph>	
</paragraph>	
	<paragraph><alignment>center</alignment>
	<image><url>../../../../images/eiffelstudio/debugger/exec_replay_04.png</url></image>
	</paragraph>					
		<warning>For now, EiffelStudio supports only  "Replay back" and "Replay forth" (finner replay might be added for 6.2).</warning>
		<warning>EiffelStudio 6.1 provides this feature only on classic system, this is not yet supported on dotnet (planned for 6.2).</warning>
 	</paragraph>
</document>
