<document title="EiffelASP.NET Installation">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		EiffelASP.NET is available for downloading for free at 
		<link>
			<label>http://www.eiffel.com</label>
			<url>http://www.eiffel.com</url>
		</link>.
		 Simply run the file and follow the installer instructions. It is recommended that Internet Information Services (IIS)
		 be deployed on the machine prior to installing EiffelASP.NET. If IIS is not deployed then the installation 
		program will display a warning message box. Click <bold>ignore</bold> to keep installing the product.
	
		<paragraph>		
			Without IIS, ASP.NET pages cannot be loaded and thus the samples will not be installed. It might still be useful
			 to install EiffelASP.NET without IIS if the Eiffel CodeDom Provider is going to be used through other 
			<link>
				<label>scenarios</label>
				<url>../codedom/scenarios.xml</url>
			</link>
			. If IIS is available then the installer will open an Eiffel ASP.NET page at the end of the installation process. 
			This page contains links to the documentation and samples. The installer will also put links to these documents
			 in the <italic>Start</italic> menu under 'Programs\EiffelASP.NET x.x' where 'x.x' corresponds to the version
			 number of EiffelASP.NET.
		
			<heading> <size>2</size><content>System Requirements</content></heading>
		
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>
					Windows 2000 Server or Advanced Server with Service Pack 2, Windows XP Professional
					 or 64-Bit Edition, or one of the Windows Server 2003 family products.		
				</item>
				<item>
					.NET Framework (1.0 or 1.1)
				</item>
				<item>
					Internet Information Services with ASP.NET (optional see above)
				</item>
			</list>

			<heading> <size>2</size><content>ASP.NET Installation</content></heading>

			Please consult the corresponding documentation (available online at 
			<link>
				<url>http://msdn.microsoft.com/asp.net/</url>
				<label>http://msdn.microsoft.com/asp.net/</label>
				<target>_blank</target>			
			</link>
			) for configuring ASP.NET properly. In particular, be aware that by default ASP.NET is disabled on Windows 2003 Server.
		</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See also:</bold> 
			<link>
				<url>getting_started.xml</url>
				<label>Getting Started</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
