<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document output="envision" title="Documenting Projects">
  <meta_data>
    <help>
      <toc>
        <envision_title>Documenting Projects</envision_title>
        <envision_pseudo_name>80</envision_pseudo_name>
      </toc>
      <xml>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>Documenting, Projects</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>Projects, Generating documentation</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>Generating documentation</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>HTML documentation generation</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
      </xml>
    </help>
  </meta_data>
  <paragraph>
		EiffelEnvision provides a means to document, in HTML, all types of projects created for EiffelEnvision in Visual Studio .NET 2003.
		<anchor>requirements</anchor><heading><size>2</size><content>Requirements</content></heading><paragraph>
			The only requirement of the integrated HTML documentation generation is to have the project you would like documentation generated for be compiled. 
			As long as the project has been built, documentation can be generated for it.
			<note><bold>Note</bold>: The documentation generated by EiffelEnvision is an Application Programming Interface (API) documentation set 
			for use by other Eiffel or EiffelEnvision projects. Due to the complexities of resolving multiple inheritance and generics, the interfaces 
			generated in the compiled assembly, by the Eiffel for .NET compiler, will be different from those interfaces generated in the documentation.
			<line_break />
			When referencing an EiffelEnvision project as a <link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/adding_references/precompiled_libraries.xml</url><label>precompiled project</label></link> from another EiffelEnvision 
			project, the documented interfaces will match the interfaces provided in the precompiled library.
			</note></paragraph><anchor>generating_documentation</anchor><heading><size>2</size><content>Generating Documentation</content></heading><paragraph>
			To generate documentation for a built EiffelEnvision project, select the <bold>Project Only</bold>, <bold>Generate Documentation</bold> context menu item from the corresponding project node, located in the <link><url>ms-help//MS.VSCC.2003/MS.MSDNQTR.2003FEB.1033/vsintro7/html/vxurfSolutionExplorerDialog.htm</url><label>Solution Explorer</label></link>. 
			Alternatively, select the corresponding project node and select <bold>Project</bold>, <bold>Generate Documentation</bold> from the main menu.
		</paragraph><paragraph>
			Provided the requirements have been met to generate a project's documentation, the HTML documentation generation dialog will appear and will immediately begin to generate the selected project's documentation. 
			You may cancel the documentation generation at any time by clicking on the <bold>Cancel</bold> button.
		</paragraph><paragraph>
			The HTML documentation generator will generate documentation only for project-specific source files that are reachable from the project's <link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/build.xml</url><anchor_name>root_class</anchor_name><label>Root Class</label></link> and <link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/build.xml</url><anchor_name>creation_routine</anchor_name><label>Creation Routine</label></link>. 
			If the specified <link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/general.xml</url><anchor_name>output_type</anchor_name><label>Output Type</label></link> for the project does not require a <link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/build.xml</url><anchor_name>root_class</anchor_name><label>Root Class</label></link> or a <link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/build.xml</url><anchor_name>creation_routine</anchor_name><label>Creation Routine</label></link>, then documentation will 
			be generated for all project-specific Eiffel classes.
			<note><bold>Note</bold>: Non project specific Eiffel classes (i.e. those not located in the project folder or in any of its subfolders) will not be included in the HTML documentation generation.
			</note></paragraph><paragraph>
			Upon successful generation of the HTML documentation, EiffelEnvision will open the root documentation HTML file in the Visual Studio .NET HTML editor for your review. All of the generated HTML and associated stylesheets are located in your project's 
			<bold>bin</bold>\<italic>configration_name</italic>\<bold>documentation</bold> subfolder, where <italic>configration_name</italic> is the name of the active project configuration. These files may be edited, at your own discretion, in or outside of 
			the Visual Studio .NET IDE.
			<warning><bold>Warning</bold>: Any editions will be overwritten if the documentation is generated at a subsequent time.
			</warning></paragraph><anchor>also_see</anchor><heading><size>2</size><content>Related Sections</content></heading><seealso><bold>See Also:</bold><line_break /><link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/adding_references/precompiled_libraries.xml</url><label>Precompiled Libraries</label></link><line_break /><link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/index.xml</url><label>Configuring Projects</label></link><line_break /><link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/build.xml</url><label>Build Property Page</label></link><line_break /><link><url>eiffelenvision_projects/configuring/project_configuration/precompiled.xml</url><label>Precompiled Property Page</label></link></seealso></paragraph>
</document>