<document output="envision" title="Debugging">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<table>
			<row>
				<cell>
					<paragraph>  Debugging is the process of tracing the execution of your Project while it is  running, to find any bugs that are occuring in the project. This is achieved by  stepping through the Projects source code, line by line, and comparing the  actual execution of the Project with the desired execution. When anomalies are  found, they cannot be fixed until the debugging process is ended as you must  end the debugging in order to edit the source code of the Project and  recompile. This process will often be repeated until all known bugs are found. </paragraph>
					<paragraph>  Rather than having to execute your Project line by line until you reach the code  that you wish to debug,  
						<link>
							<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/70_Debugging_Projects/breakpoints.htm</url>
							<label>break points</label>
						</link>  can be set, which allow you to execute the Project normally until a breakpoint  is reached, at which point the debugger will start. 
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>The Debug Menu
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  Below is a screenshot of the 
						<bold>Debug</bold> menu which contains a number of  options for debugging your Project: 
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<image> 
							<alt_text>debugwindow</alt_text> 
							<url>debugwindow.png</url>
						</image>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>  The following entries are available : </paragraph>
					<list ordered="false">
						<item>
							<bold>Windows</bold>  - This menu allows you to select which debugging related windows are displayed  in the Visual Studio Environment. The entries in this menu are dependent on  your current debugging status.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Start</bold> - Starts execution of the project, which will run until a  
							<link>
								<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/70_Debugging_Projects/breakpoints.htm</url>
								<label>Break Point</label>
							</link>  is reached.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Start Without Debugging</bold> - Starts execution of the project and ignores  all  
							<link>
								<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/70_Debugging_Projects/breakpoints.htm</url>
								<label>Break Points</label>
							</link>.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Processes...</bold>  - Displays a dialog allowing you to connect to an external process for  debugging.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Exceptions...</bold>  - Displays a dialog allowing you to set the exception checking levels, and  whether to start debugging when an exception occurs.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Step Into</bold>- If you are not currently debugging then selecting this  item will start the debugger, and step to the first line of execution.  Selecting this entry during debugging will step into the execution of the next  feature on the current line that has not yet been executed. If there is no  feature on the current line to step into, then this option will step to the  next line of execution in the current feature.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Step Over</bold>  - If you are not currently debugging then selecting this item will start the  debugger, and step to the first line of execution. Selecting this item while  debugging will step to the next line of execution in the current feature,  without stepping into the execution of any features on the current line.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>New Breakpoint...</bold> - Displays a dialog which allows you to add new  
							<link>
								<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/70_Debugging_Projects/breakpoints.htm</url>
								<label>Break Points</label>
							</link>  to your Project.  
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Clear All Breakpoints</bold> - Removes all assigned  
							<link>
								<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/70_Debugging_Projects/breakpoints.htm</url>
								<label>Break Points</label>
							</link>  from the Project. In the screenshot above, this entry is greyed out as there  are no  
							<link>
								<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/70_Debugging_Projects/breakpoints.htm</url>
								<label>Break Points</label>
							</link>  currently defined for the project.  
						</item>
					</list>
					<seealso>
						<bold>See also</bold>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./breakpoints.htm</url>
							<label>Break Points</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./BreakPointWindow.htm</url>
							<label>Break Point Window</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./CallStackWindow.htm</url>
							<label>Call Stack Window</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./LocalsWindow.htm</url>
							<label>Locals Window</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./WatchWindow.htm</url>
							<label>Watch Window</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/index.htm</url>
							<label>Using ENViSioN! Within Visual Studio.NET</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
					</seealso>
				</cell>
			</row>
		</table>
	</paragraph></document>