<document title="Debugger Preferences" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>This category contains preferences that are specific to the EiffelStudio Debugger and the debugger tool. These preferences are: 
		<line_break/>
		<table><border>1</border>
			<row>
				<cell><bold>Label in the preferences window</bold></cell>
				<cell><bold>Complete Description</bold></cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Critical stack depth</cell>
				<cell>Stack overflow detection: depth of stack at which execution will pause and ask whether it is ok to continue (only works in classic Eiffel).</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Debug output evaluation</cell>
				<cell>Display DEBUG_OUTPUT.debug_output for objects whose base class inherits from DEBUG_OUTPUT.</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Default displayed string size</cell>
				<cell>Default number of displayed characters of a STRING (increasing this value might slow down debugging).</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Default expanded view size</cell>
				<cell>Default number of displayed characters in the expanded view (increasing this value might slow down debugging).</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Default maximum stack depth</cell>
				<cell>Default number of call stack elements shown in Call Stack tool (-1 to show all of them).</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Delay before cleaning objects grid</cell>
				<cell>Delay in milliseconds before cleaning the Objects tool view.</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Dotnet debugger</cell>
				<cell>Which .NET debugger to launch.</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Expanded display background color</cell>
				<cell>Background color for expanded display view (default is white, change it to better see white spaces in displayed text).</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Generating type evaluation</cell>
				<cell>Display the base type of an object if enabled, otherwise just the base class (disabling it might speed up debugging).</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Interrupt every n instructions</cell>
				<cell>Number of instructions that will be executed before interrupting the execution.</cell>
			</row>
			<row>
				<cell>Max evaluation duration</cell>
				<cell>Number of seconds to wait before cancelling an evaluation.</cell>
			</row>
		</table>
	</paragraph></document>
