<document title="Required Permissions">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		The account running the Eiffel CodeDom Provider might have restricted permissions such as when 
		used through ASP.NET. This section aims at defining the security permissions required for the 
		execution of the Eiffel CodeDom Provider.

		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Eiffel Metadata Cache</content>
		</heading>

		Both when generating and compiling source code, the Eiffel CodeDom Provider needs to read and 
		write from and to the Eiffel Metadata Cache. This repository stores the mapping information between .NET and 
		Eiffel names for both types and their members. By default the Eiffel Metadata Cache is located in the 
		<italic>Assemblies</italic> subfolder of the Eiffel CodeDom Provider directory.
		
		<note>
			<bold>Note:</bold> The EiffelASP.NET installation program will grant read and write access 
			to the Eiffel Metadata Cache folder for the <italic>ASPNET</italic> (default ASP.NET worker process account 
			on Windows XP Professional) and the <italic>IIS_WPG</italic> (default ASP.NET worker process account on
			Windows Server 2003) accounts.
		</note>
		
		The path to the Eiffel Metadata Cache folder might be changed via the 
		<link><label>Eiffel CodeDom Provider Manager</label><url>../tools/manager.xml</url></link>, make sure 
		the new folder can be read from and written to by the account running the process that uses the Eiffel CodeDom 
		Provider.
		
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Precompile Cache</content>
		</heading>

		The same requirements apply to the Precompile Cache folder. By default the Precompile Cache folder is located 
		in the <italic>Precompile</italic> subfolder of the Eiffel CodeDom directory.

		<note>
			<bold>Note:</bold> The EiffelASP.NET installation program will grant read and write access 
			to the Precompile Cache folder for the <italic>ASPNET</italic> (default ASP.NET worker process account 
			on Windows XP Professional) and the <italic>IIS_WPG</italic> (default ASP.NET worker process account 
			on Windows Server 2003) accounts.
		</note>

		As with the Eiffel Metadata Cache folder, it is possible to change the location of the Precompile Cache folder 
		but the process running the Eiffel CodeDom Provider must always have read and write access to 
		the folder.
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Logging</content>
		</heading>

		Logging requires registry read access as well as event log write access. By default, the ASP.NET worker process 
		does not have these permissions. The easiest way to grant the required permissions to the ASP.NET worker process 
		is by using ASP.NET impersonation. This mechanism allows the ASP.NET worker process to run under a different 
		account. This is done by providing a <italic>web.config</italic> file in the root folder of the ASP.NET application. 
		The content of the configuration file needs to include the following declaration:
		
		<code_block>
&lt;configuration&gt;
    &lt;system.web&gt;
        &lt;identity impersonate="true" userName="Username" password="Password"/&gt;
     &lt;/system.web&gt;
&lt;/configuration&gt;</code_block>
		
		where <code><syntax>Username</syntax></code> is the name of an account which has all the required permissions and 
		<code><syntax>Password</syntax></code> the corresponding password. Refer to the .NET Framework SDK 
		documentation for additional information on ASP.NET impersonation.
		
		<paragraph>
			The solution described above might not be acceptable on a production web server. 
			However, it is possible to configure the Eiffel CodeDom Provider to log events on a different 
			machine (see <link><label>Eiffel CodeDom Provider Manager</label><url>../tools/manager.xml</url></link>). 
			The log machine should grant the appropriate permissions to the impersonated account for logging and could 
			only be accessible through the web server. This setting would avoid having to grant 
			additional permissions to the ASP.NET worker process account on the web server while still enabling 
			logging.
		</paragraph>	
	</paragraph>
</document>
