<document title="Web Service Client Project Wizard" output="envision">
	<meta_data>
		<help></help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>1</size>Web Service Client Project Wizard
		</heading>
		<paragraph>This wizard enables you to create an Eiffel project which communicates with an existing web service.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Navigation
		</heading>
		<paragraph>To navigate between the pages, select the 
			<bold>Next</bold> or 
			<bold>Back</bold> buttons available on each page.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>To cancel the wizard at any point, select the 
			<bold>Cancel</bold> button
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>To complete the wizard, using the current settings, select the 
			<bold>Finish</bold> button which is available from the Completion page.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Page content
		</heading>
		<paragraph>This wizard is comprised of the following pages:</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Welcome
		</heading>
		<paragraph>This page contains a welcome message. There are no settings on this page.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Web Service
		</heading>
		<paragraph>This page contains a text field into which you must enter a valid URL or path to the WSDL document, XSD schema or .disco map document from which you wish to generate your web service client project. URL locations should be entered directly into the text field, whereas if it is a file you are using to specify your project, you can click the 
			<bold>browse</bold> button to bring up a file browse dialog.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>At the bottom of the field is a combo box from which you can choose the protocol that you wish your project to use. You may select between SOAP, Http get and Http post.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Web service client service</alt_text>
				<url>web_service_client_service.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>:You must enter a location or file into the text field, otherwise, when you click 
			<bold>next</bold>, an error page will be displayed, stopping you from continuing with the wizard.
		</note>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Authentication
		</heading>
		<paragraph> This page is only displayed if you specified a http URL on the previous page. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>If the web service to which you are connecting, requires authentication, check 
			<bold>require  authentication?</bold> and then enter the username, password and domain required.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>If the web service requires a proxy, check 
			<bold>require proxy?</bold> and then enter the URL, user name, password and domain.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Web service client authentication</alt_text>
				<url>web_service_client_authentication.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Completion
		</heading>
		<paragraph> As soon as this page is displayed, verification of your settings begins. Please be patient, as the verification may take anywhere from a few seconds up to a minute or two, dependent on the factors involved.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<paragraph>If the verification completes successfully, then you may click 
				<bold>Finish</bold> to complete the wizard.
			</paragraph>
			<paragraph>If the verification failed, then an error message will be displayed and you may click 
				<bold>Back</bold> to modify the incorrect settings.
			</paragraph>
			<paragraph>
				<image>
					<alt_text>Web service client completion</alt_text>
					<url>web_service_client_complete.png</url>
				</image>
			</paragraph>
			<seealso>
				<bold>See Also</bold>
				<line_break></line_break>
				<link>
					<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/10_Adding_A_New_Project/index.xml</url>
					<label>  Adding a New Project</label>
				</link>
			</seealso>
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>
