<document title="HTML Report Project Wizard" output="envision">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>70</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>1</size>HTML Report Project Wizard
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Availability: Enterprise version only.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> This wizard will generate the requested HTML documentation for all or part of you compiled ENViSioN! project.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Page content
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> The wizard comprises of the following pages:
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item> Introduction Page - Introducing the wizard and its requirements </item>
			<item> Select ENViSioN! Project - The compiled ENViSioN! to document </item>
			<item> Choose Clusters - Select the clusters to generate documentation for </item>
			<item>  Summary - The summary of the wizard, and what happens next</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Requirements
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> The HTML Report Wizard requires that you use a compiled ENViSioN! project. For the best results ensure that you compile in the release configuration mode, or a configurationmode that has the '
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing\20_Managing_Projects\10_Configuring_A_Project\10_Project_Property_Pages\GeneralPage.htm#OptimizeCode</url>
				<label>
					<italic>Optimize  Code</italic>
				</label>
			</link>' project property set in the 
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing\20_Managing_Projects\10_Configuring_A_Project\10_Project_Property_Pages\GeneralPage.xml</url>
				<label>  Genera</label>
			</link>l properties.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>HTML Report Wizard Overview
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> The HTML Report Wizard will generate a set of HTML documents corresponding to the selected clusters you wish to document. A Table of Contents (TOC) will also begenerated with these files.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Eiffel ENViSioN Project Selection
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> The first page of the wizard asks for a compiled ENViSioN! project to generated the HTML documentation for. Simple enter the path compiled Eiffel Project File (*.epr)located in the relevant configuration directory of your project directory, or use the provided browse button.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Import EiffelStudio Wizard</alt_text>
				<url>html_report_wizard.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size> Clusters Selection
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> You may generate documentation for all or a subset of the clusters in your Project. The Clusters To Generate page allows you to select the project clusters containing thoseclasses to generate the documentation for.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The 'Excluded Clusters' list is the list of clusters that will not have documentation generated for them and the 'Included Clusters' list will. You can include/exclude clusters using one of thefour selection buttons '
			<bold>&lt;&lt;</bold>', '
			<bold>&lt;</bold>', '&gt;' or '&gt;&gt;'. 
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item> '&lt;&lt;' will exclude all of clusters. </item>
			<item> '&lt;' will exclude only those selected clusters in the Included Clusters list. </item>
			<item> '&gt;' will include only those selected clusters in the Excluded Clusters list. </item>
			<item>  '&gt;&gt;' will include all of the clusters.</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Import EiffelStudio Wizard</alt_text>
				<url>html_report_wizard_clusters.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break></line_break>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/10_Adding_A_New_Project/index.xml</url>
				<label>  Adding a New Project</label>
			</link>
			<line_break></line_break>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/20_Managing_Projects/30_Documenting_A_Project/documenting_a_project.xml</url>
				<label>  Documenting ENViSioN! Projects</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
