<document title="EiffelCOM Wizard Introduction" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The COM standard allows software components written in different languages to communicate with each other. 
			However, building COM compliant applications requires the development of a large amount of code only dedicated 
			to supporting the technology. The EiffelCOM wizard was designed to free Eiffel developers from having to write 
			the plumbing code.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The EiffelCOM wizard is a powerful tool that enables the fast development of COM components in Eiffel and 
			accessing COM components from Eiffel systems. It consists of a series of input fields, which ask about the 
			component's characteristics. The wizard needs the data to produce an Eiffel system skeleton, the code to 
			access or create a component, and the component-specific runtime libraries.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The wizard allows Eiffel developers with little COM knowledge to develop and reuse COM components. The design 
			of the generated code follows the Eiffel standards and will be familiar to experienced Eiffel users. The only 
			prerequisite to use the EiffelCOM wizard is an understanding of the <bold>Interface Definition Language</bold>. 
			<bold>IDL</bold> describes a component. Compilers can generate <bold>Type Libraries</bold> from 
			IDL files. Tools that need information on a given component, such as the EiffelCOM wizard, Visual Basic, etc. will 
			analyze the Type Libraries. The IDL syntax is very close to C so should be easy to learn for developers that are 
			familiar with this language.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The wizard generates code from a Type Library and additional information given by the user. The generated code 
			consists of Eiffel classes, C/C++ files, and library files. The wizard automatically produces library files from generated 
			C and C++ code. You do not need to modify generated C/C++ code to build your EiffelCOM system.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Code Generation Process</content>
		</heading>
		<image>
			<url>images/introduction.png</url>
		</image>
		<paragraph>
			The wizard can automatically compile the generated C and Eiffel code. To produce a Type Library corresponding to a given IDL file the wizard relies on  
			<bold>MIDL</bold>, the Microsoft IDL compiler. You may also provide the wizard with a Type Library directly. 
			The wizard can also be used to add a COM interface to an existing Eiffel project.  For the rest of the manual a 
			<bold>COM Definition File</bold> will refer to the input file given to the wizard (either an IDL file, a Type Library or 
			an Eiffel project file).
		</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>:
			<link>
				<url>guided_tour/index.xml</url>
				<label>Guided Tour</label>
			</link>, 
			<link>
				<url>reference/index.xml</url>
				<label>EiffelCOM wizard reference</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
