 <document output="envision" title="Compliance Checker">  
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Compliance Checker</envision_title>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\Tools\Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker\Using the Compliance Checker</envision_location>
				<envision_pseudo_name>30</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker, Compliance checker</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker. Reports</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>User interface, Compliance checker</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Reports, Creating</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Reports, Exporting</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data> 
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The <bold>Compliance Checker</bold> tab is used to built and view a compliance report. If your <link><url>20_project_settings.xml</url><label>Project Settings</label></link> are in order you can prompt the tool to build a compliance report by selecting the <bold>Check</bold> toolbar button or selecting the <bold>Check</bold> button, in the <bold>Report generation</bold> section of the page.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The <bold>Compliance Checker</bold> is split into two sections:
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item><bold>Report Pane</bold>: The white pane labeled <bold>Non-compliant assembly members</bold> dominant in the page. This pane will be populated with the results of a compliance check.<line_break/><line_break/></item>
			<item><bold>Report Generation</bold>: The section of the page dedicated to generating a compliance report.</item>
		</list>
				
		<anchor>generating_reports</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Generating Reports</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			There are a couple of options available to you before generating a compliance-report. A report will always show the non-Eiffel-compliant types and their members, after all the tools is used to check Eiffel-compliancy. You may optionally (on by default) show the non-CLS-compliant types and their members, which will also show all types and their members that are not CLS-compliant or are evaluated to be illegally CLS-compliant. To view the non-CLS-compliant types and their members ensure that the <bold>Show non-CLS-compliant</bold> option is checked. Alternatively you may show every type and every member from the specified assembly. For this, ensure the <bold>Show all</bold> option is checked.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			To start the compliance report generation, select the <bold>Check</bold> button. Selecting <bold>Check</bold> start to generate a report, in the report pane. The items in the report pane will be based on the options selected before selecting <bold>Check</bold>. If at anytime you need to cancel generation of the report, select the <bold>Cancel</bold> button that replaces the <bold>Check</bold> button.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			If the project has already been checked the <bold>Check</bold> button will say <bold>Recheck</bold> instead. This will simply discard the last generated report and recheck every type and their members.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			Upon full report generation completion you will be prompted with a message indicating the completion of the report.
		</paragraph>
		

		<anchor>reading_reports</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Reading the Generated Report</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			A report in generated in a dual-level tree, with a type being the topmost item and its children being members of the type. Every type and member has a name followed by three columns, with one of three marker icons:
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item><image><url>../images/check.ico</url></image> Compliant<line_break/><line_break/></item>
			<item><image><url>../images/cross.ico</url></image> Non-Compliant<line_break/><line_break/></item>
			<item><image><url>../images/caution.ico</url></image> Illegally Compliant<line_break/><line_break/></item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>
			<bold>Compliant</bold> refers to types and members that are Eiffel/CLS-compliant, <bold>Non-Compliant</bold> refers to those types and members that are not Eiffel/CLS-compliant and <bold>Illegally Compliant</bold> refers to those types and members that are marked or are assumed to be Eiffel/CLS-compliant but are not!
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			These marker icons will appear in the following columns:
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item><bold>Eiffel</bold>, short for "Eiffel-Compliant". This column indicates if the Eiffel for .NET complier will be able to consume the indicated type/member for use within Eiffel for .NET.<line_break/><line_break/></item>
			<item><bold>CLS</bold>, short for "CLS-Compliant". This column indicates if any CLS-compliant consumer (generally compilers) will be able to consume the indicated type/member for use within Eiffel for .NET.<line_break/><line_break/></item>
			<item><bold>Marked</bold>, short for "Is Marked with the <italic>System.ClsCompliantAttribute</italic> Attribute". This column indicates if the type/member has been explicitly marked with the <italic>System.ClsCompliantAttribute</italic> attribute. Type can be marked on assembly or type level as types can inherit their compliancy from the container assembly. Members can be marked on assembly, type or member level as members can inherit their compliancy from the container type or assembly.<line_break/><line_break/></item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>
			Each marker icon has a tool tip. Simply hover over the icon with the mouse cursor to find out more information about what the marker means and why it is there. For Non-CLS-Compliant and Illegally-Compliant markers the precise reason why they are what they are is explained in the tool tip.
		</paragraph>
		
		<anchor>exports_reporting</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Exporting and Copying Report Items</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			Once a compliance report has been generated the <bold>Export to File</bold> button becomes available. Selecting this button will export the report generated, even if generation was canceled (canceled reports will only export the report items that have been generated, no further analysis is done.) You will be prompted for a location on disk to save the project to. Select a location and file name and select <bold>Ok</bold>. The generated report will now be persisted to disk, in XML form, at the specified location.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			If you are only interested in copying a number of items from the report, select the items of interest from the report pane and press CTRL+C.
		</paragraph>		
		
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>:
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>../index.xml</url><label>Compliance Checker Overview</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>index.xml</url><label>Using the Compliance Checker</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>20_project_settings.xml</url><label>Project Settings Tab</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>10_using_the_toolbar.xml</url><label>Using the Toolbar</label></link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
 
