<document title="Build Tab">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Build Tab</envision_title>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\Tools\EiffelBuild\Reference\Preferences</envision_location>
				<envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>This tab contains information about the type of project you wish to build, and associated information.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Here is the appearance of the Build tab when 'build type' is selected as 'Project':</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelbuild/screenshots/project_build.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>If 'build'_type' is selected as 'Class', then the tab will have the following appearance:</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelbuild/screenshots/project_build_class.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The options available in this tab are as follows:
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>
					<anchor>build_type</anchor>
					<bold>Build type</bold>
					<paragraph>Select 'Project' if you wish to generate a complete project including an ace file, and an application class, which will launch the GUI you are developing.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>Select `Class' if you wish to generate a single class that represents the GUI you are developing. This option is useful if you wish to incorporate your current project into an existing Vision2 system.</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					<bold>Always rebuild ace</bold>
					<paragraph>This option causes the ace file to be completely re-generated every time you generate your project. If you do not wish the ace file to be re-generated, then disable this option. This check box is only available if 'build type' is set to 'project'.</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					<bold>Project name</bold>
					<paragraph>This entry will be added to the generated ace file as the SYSTEM attribute. The executable built from compiling this ace file will have this name. This option is only available if you have specified 'build_type' as 'Project'.</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					<bold>Application class name</bold>
					<paragraph>This entry will be the class name for the generated vision2 application which will launch your GUI. This option is only available if you have specified 'build_type' as 'Project'.</paragraph>
				</item>
				<item>
					<bold>Constants class name</bold>
					<paragraph>This entry is used as the name of the constants class generated by EiffelBuild to define all <link><url>../75_constants/index.xml</url><label>constants</label></link> contained in your project. Two classes are actually generated from this name, an implementation and an interface class. For example, if you specify a name "constants", two classes, <class_name>CONSTANTS_IMP</class_name> and <class_name>CONSTANTS</class_name> (inheriting from <class_name>CONSTANTS_IMP</class_name>) are generated, and all other classes generated by EiffelBuild, inherit <class_name>CONSTANTS</class_name> for access to these constants.

</paragraph>
				</item>
			</list>
		</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelbuild/reference/90_code_generation/index.xml</url>
				<label>Code generation</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>index.xml</url>
				<label>Project settings window</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>30_generation.xml</url>
				<label>Generation tab</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
