<document output="envision" title="Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker">  
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker</envision_title>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\Tools</envision_location>
				<envision_pseudo_name>30</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data>  
	<paragraph>
		<anchor>overview</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>Overview</content>
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			The <bold>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker</bold> tool can be used to verify assemblies written in other .NET languages; such as C#, VB.NET, IL, Cobolt, Delphi, etc. are <bold>Eiffel-Compliant</bold> and/or <bold>CLS-Compliant</bold>. The tool checks the Common Language Specification (CLS) consumer (generally a .NET compiler) related rules for CLS-Compliance and Eiffel's more lax consumer rules. That is to say Eiffel for .NET's ability to consume non-CLS-Compliant assemblies, types and their members.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			The <bold>Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker</bold> tool is for verification only! It will allow you, a developer or component vendor, to ensure any number of .NET assemblies can be used from within Eiffel. In addition it also highlights potential problems CLS-strict languages will have consuming assemblies you yourselves have developed. You may then go back to your code and mark assemblies, types and members with the <bold>System.ClsCompliantAttribute</bold> attribute, with the appropriate state flag. The tool will also indicate illegal compliance, indicating a <bold>System.ClsCompliantAttribute</bold> state flag is incorrectly specified or a require System.ClsCompliantAttribute attribute is missing.
		</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: The current version of this tool will only check .NET framework version 1.0 and 1.1 and who's Eiffel-compliancy relates to the following product versions: <bold>EiffelEnvision 2.6</bold>, <bold>Eiffel for ASP.NET 5.6</bold>, <bold>EiffelStudio 5.7</bold>
		</note>
		
		<anchor>in_this_section</anchor>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>
			<content>In This Section</content>
		</heading>
		
		<paragraph>
			<link><url>10_getting_started/index.xml</url><label>Getting Started</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			Information on how to launch the Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker application and the available command-line options. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<link><url>20_projects/index.xml</url><label>Compliance Projects</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			Describes the notion of a compliance project for persiting project settings between sessions.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<link><url>30_user_interface/index.xml</url><label>Using the Compliance Checker</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			A complete overview of the Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker application's user interface.
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>
