  <document title="Externals Options" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>../../../../images/eiffelstudio/project_settings/external_options.png</url>
				<alt_text>Externals dialog</alt_text>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>In most cases this is not needed but for some C/C++ externals and in some .NET projects it is necessary to specify additional includes, objects or resources.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>If you use a library, externals of this library are automatically included. E.g. if you use vision2 the externals for vision2 don't need to be added to the project itself.</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Include: This is where you can enter the location of the directories where the C/C++ compiler will look for the header files that are required. The header files which the C/C++ compiler will look for are the ones that appear in an encapsulation of a C/C++ external in an Eiffel class. Click 
			<link>
				<url>../30_compiler/30_external_features/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>here</label>
			</link> to have more information about C/C++ externals specification.</item>
			<item>Object: additional C/C++ object files</item>
			<item>Library: like object files, but will be added last, needed for some very strict C compilers</item>
			<item>Makefile: additional makefiles, if possible use tasks instead</item>
			<item>
				<paragraph>Resource: .NET resources</paragraph>
				<list ordered="false">
					<item>The .resx resource file format is a XML based format to include objects (such as images and other binary formats) and strings.</item>
					<item>The .txt resource file format can only contains strings.</item>
				</list>
			</item>
		</list>
		Externals have three properties:
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Location: location of the external, will be copied verbatim into the makefile</item>
			<item>Description: an optional description about the external</item>
			<item>Condition: allows the same configuration with externals to work in different situations (e.g. windows and unix) (see <link><url>020_target_general.xml</url><anchor_name>condition</anchor_name><label>conditions</label></link>) </item>
		</list>
	</paragraph>
</document>
