<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<document output="envision" title="Blank Eiffel Graphical Application Wizard">
  <meta_data>
    <help>
      <toc>
        <envision_title>Blank Eiffel Graphical Application Wizard</envision_title>
        <envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
      </toc>
      <xml>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>New Projects, Blank Eiffel Graphical Application</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>Blank Eiffel Graphical Application Wizard</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>EiffelEnvision, New Projects, Blank Eiffel Graphical Application</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>F</index>
          <term>ee.vs.project.projects.blank_eiffel_graphical_application_wizard</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
      </xml>
    </help>
  </meta_data>
  <paragraph>
    <paragraph>
			The <bold>Blank Eiffel Graphical Application Wizard</bold> creates a new simple <bold>EiffelVision 2</bold><link><url>../../structure/index.xml</url><label>Project</label></link>. The project will be added to an active or new Visual Studio .NET <link><url>ms-help//MS.VSCC.2003/MS.MSDNQTR.2003FEB.1033/vsintro7/html/vxconvisualstudiosolutionsprojects.htm</url><label>Solution</label></link>.
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
			The wizard is separated into two pages. <bold>Overview</bold> and <bold>System Settings</bold>. You may switch between the pages by clicking on the name of the page, located in the wizard's left pane.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>overview</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Overview</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
			The <bold>Overview</bold> page presents a basic overview of what is going to be generated for the project. The information detailed on this page reflects the information set of the <bold>System Settings</bold> page. If the defaults do not meet with your requirements, then please use the <bold>System Settings</bold> page to make the necessary changes.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>system_settings</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>System Settings</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
			The <bold>System Settings</bold> page allows you to modify the settings for the system created when the wizard is completed. The page allows you to modify features of the main window which will be launched by the application. The following settings may be modified:
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
      <bold>Menu Bar</bold>
      <line_break />
			If selected, a default menu bar and menus will be generated with File and Help menus.
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
      <bold>Tool Bar</bold>
      <line_break />
			If selected, a tool bar will be inserted into the main window of the application.
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
      <bold>Status Bar</bold>
      <line_break />
			If selected, a status bar will be inserted into the main window of the application.
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
      <bold>About Dialog Box</bold>
      <line_break />
			If selected, an about dialog box will be included in the project. If the menu bar option is also selected, then the dialog will be connected to the Help, About menu option.
		</paragraph>
    <paragraph>
      <bold>Winforms Container</bold>
      <line_break />
			If selected, a Windows Form container will be added to the main window permitting the use of Windows Forms controls inside your project.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>completing</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Completing the Wizard</content>
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
			Once you have set the appropriate settings for the new project, clicking <bold>Finish</bold> will create a new EiffelEnvision <link><url>../../structure/index.xml</url><label>Project</label></link> with the specified settings.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>also_see</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
      <content>Related Sections</content>
    </heading>
    <seealso>
      <bold>See also</bold>
      <line_break />
      <link>
        <url>../index.xml</url>
        <label>EiffelEnvision Projects</label>
      </link>
      <line_break />
      <link>
        <url>ms-help//MS.VSCC.2003/MS.MSDNQTR.2003FEB.1033/vsintro7/html/vxurfAddNewProjectDialog.htm</url>
        <label>Add New Project Dialog Box</label>
      </link>
    </seealso>
  </paragraph>
</document>