<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document output="envision" title="EiffelEnvision 2.6 Version Information">
  <meta_data>
    <help>
      <toc>
        <envision_title>EiffelEnvision 2.6 Version Information</envision_title>
        <envision_pseudo_name>98</envision_pseudo_name>
      </toc>
      <xml>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>Version History, EiffelEnvision 2.6</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
        <xmlkeyword>
          <index>K</index>
          <term>History, EiffelEnvision 2.6</term>
        </xmlkeyword>
      </xml>
    </help>
  </meta_data>
  <paragraph>
    <paragraph>
		This document lists the changes, including additions and enhancements, made between <bold>EiffelEnvision 2.5</bold> and 
		<bold>EiffelEnvision 2.6</bold>.
		</paragraph>
    <anchor>new_projects_and_items</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			EiffelEnvision New Projects and New Project Items:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
			<item>Removed obsolete Eiffel syntax from the EiffelEnvision new project and new project items templates.</item>
			<item>Fix precompiled project wizard not adding EiffelBase clusters when only EiffelBase is selected.</item>
			<item>Adding new WEL or EiffelVision2 items, to projects not containing the respective clusters, will now make the project compile the unmanaged code portion.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>project_configuration</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			EiffelEnvision Project Configuration:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
        <item>Added Build Events project configiguration property page to allow setting of pre and post build event actions.</item>
        <item>Added Output Path property to Build project configuration property page to allow alternative specification of a deployment location.</item>
        <item>Added a "Edit List" dialog for all list properties such as Debug Clauses and cluster Excluded Items.</item>
        <item>All path configuration properties are preserved as written, promoting portability, and not always converted to relative paths. The exception is the Output Path configuration property.</item>
        <item>Renamed Build property page to Building.</item>
        <item>Some very minor cosmetical changes in property descriptions and names.</item>
        <item>Include Subdirectories on the project cluster now correctly respects the associated property in the project configuration file.</item>
        <item>New projects and projects converted, using the EiffelStudio Project to EiffelEnvision Project Conversion Tool, are now created with the IL Verifiable configuration property set to <bold>No</bold>.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>eiffel_editor</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			Eiffel Editor:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">  
     		<item>Corrected casing for Result and Current.</item>
     		<item>Go to Definition now works for Precurors calls.</item>
     		<item>Go to Definition now works for inherited members not declared in a descendind class.</item>
     		<item>Fixed issue where the completion list failed to show uncompiled features of a compiled class after a completion list has been shown.</item>
     		<item>.NET features are no longer displayed with the externals icon representation, in the completion list.</item>
     		<item>Added complete brace matching.</item>
     		<item>Fixed editor corruption (black-outs).</item>
     		<item>Fixed false syntax error conditions, such as a class with no feature clause and no features.</item>
     		<item>Updated editor syntax to support new Eiffel 5.6 grammar.</item>
     		<item>Added special "[hide]" comment usage for feature clauses to automatically hide sections of code when opening an Eiffel source file.</item>
     		<item>Qualified access calls now complete on a static functions.</item>
     		<item>Added completion for bracketed creation expressions - (create {OPERATING_ENVIRONMENT}).di...</item>
     		<item>Uncompiled features in a compiled class now show up in the completion list.</item>
     		<item>Optimized editor refreshing to speed up edition, caret scrolling and selection.</item>
		<item>Update feature list and completion icons, and added more icons to represent features more specifically.</item>
		<item>Fixed highlighting of Intellisense Method Tip arguments after selecting the corrected overloaded feature related to what is being edited.</item>
		<item>Intellisense Method Tips now close when deleting an opening paranthesis, for overloaded features.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>object_browser</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			EiffelEnvision Object Browser:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
		<item>Added disambiguated Eiffel feature names under .NET Method for clarity.</item>
        <item>Fixed missing arguments for Infix routines.</item>
        <item>Fixed incorrect usage of Microsoft's private method and field icons for static methods and fields. .NET statics are now the same as would be shown in top-level assembly references.</item>
        <item>Fixed documentation hyper-linking for types belonging to an assembly with a class name prefix.</item>
        <item>Uncompiled .NET types and members can now be browsed to, from the Find Symbols pane, even if they have not been compiled into the repective project.</item>
        <item>Removed "Not Implemented" error messages when double left mouse clicking on .NET type nodes.</item>
        <item>Non-exported Eiffel creation routines now show up under the Creation Routines node.</item>
        <item>Update all Eiffel related feature and class icons.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>class_View</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			EiffelEnvision Class View:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
        <item>Update all Eiffel related feature and class icons.</item>
        <item>Class view project icon is now the same as the Solution Explorer/Object Browser project icon.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>eiffel_compiler</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			Eiffel Compiler:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
		<item>Add notion of Eiffel-compliant so now some non-CLS (common language specification) members can be used in EiffelEnvision.</item>
		<item>EiffelEnvision now uses an Eiffel 5.6 compiler.</item>
        <item>For all other improvements see <link><url>../../../../eiffelstudio/reference/30_compiler/60_version_history/index.xml</url><label>Eiffel Compiler Version History</label></link>.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>expression_evaluator</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			EiffelEnvision Expression Evaluator:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
        <item>Eiffel ARRAYs show count as content value.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>tools</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			Tools:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
        <item>Added Eiffel for .NET Compliance Checker tool for checking third party assemblies for Eiffel/CLS compliance.</item>
        <item>Update class generation of the EiffelStudio to EiffelEnvision project conversion tool so it does not generated obsolete syntax.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>  
    <anchor>libraries_and_samples</anchor>
    <heading>
	    <size>2</size>
	    Libraries and Samples:
    </heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
	      <item>Added Graph and Preference Eiffel Source libraries.</item>
	      <item>Added Examples for graph and preference libraries.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
    <anchor>misc</anchor>
    <heading>
      <size>2</size>
			Miscellaneous:
		</heading>
    <paragraph>
      <list ordered="false">
        <item>Eiffel source file (*.e) now use the Visual Studio .NET DDE an will open in an active instance of Visual Studio .NET, instead of creating a new Visual Studio .NET process for every file opened from the Windows Explorer Shell.</item>
      </list>
    </paragraph>
  </paragraph>
</document>
