<document title="Adding a cluster" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>cluster, add</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>It is possible to create new clusters from EiffelStudio. A dialog window has been designed to help you do so.
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<url>/images/eiffelstudio/dialogs_and_wizards/new_cluster_dialog.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>There are three ways to make this window appear. You can:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Click
				<image>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_new_cluster_color.gif</url>
				</image> in the 
				<link>
					<url>../../reference/05_general_interface_description/30_main_toolbars.xml</url>
					<label>standard toolbar</label>
				</link>.
			</item>
			<item>Click
				<image>
					<url>/images/eiffelstudio/icons/icon_new_cluster_small_color.gif</url>
				</image> in the 
				<link>
					<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/10_browsing_tools/20_cluster_tool/00_introduction.xml</url>
					<label>Cluster tool</label>
				</link>.
			</item>
			<item>Select 
				<bold>New cluster</bold> in the 
				<bold>Tools</bold> menu.
			</item>
		</list>Using this dialog, you can either create a subcluster of an existing cluster or a top-level cluster.
		<paragraph>If you decide to create a top-level cluster, you should give it a name and a path (if the selected path does not exist, it will be created). You can also choose its basic properties, such as whether it should be a library cluster and/or a recursive one (being a library cluster implies being recursive).</paragraph>
		<paragraph>If you want to create a subcluster, give it a name and select its parent in the list of available clusters (read-only clusters are not displayed). Giving it a path is not required. If you do not set a path for a new subcluster, it will be located by default in a subdirectory of its parent cluster, named after the subcluster name. This is the recommended way of creating a subcluster (since its path in the Ace file will be automatically relative to the parent), but it is not compulsory.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>To import an existing cluster, you can also go to the 
			<bold>Clusters</bold> tab in the 
			<link>
				<url>/tools/eiffelstudio/reference/25_project_settings/30_clusters.xml</url>
				<label>Project Settings dialog</label>
			</link> and click 
			<bold>Add</bold>. Although this solution may be slightly more tedious, it gives access to more options.
		</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>40_removing_a_cluster.xml</url>
				<label>Removing a cluster</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>