<document title="EiffelBase, Abstract Container Structures: The Taxonomy">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_location>Class Libraries\EiffelBase\EiffelBase\EiffelBase Data Structures Overview</envision_location>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph> A container data structure (or container in the sequel) is an object which serves to store and access collections of objects, called the 
			<bold>items</bold> of the container. All classes describing containers are descendants of the deferred class 
			<link>
				<url>../../reference/structures/access/container_chart.xml</url>
				<label>CONTAINER</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>A container can be studied from three viewpoints: access, storage and traversal.</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>The 
				<bold>access</bold> criterion affects how the clients of a container can access its items. For  example, in a stack or queue, only one item is accessible at any given time, and  clients do not choose that item; in contrast, clients of an array or hash table must  provide an index, or more generally a key, to access an item.
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<bold>storage</bold> criterion affects how the items are put together. For example some  containers are finite, others potentially infinite; among finite structures, some are  bounded, others unbounded.
			</item>
			<item>The 
				<bold>traversal</bold> criterion affects how, if in any way, the items of a container can be  traversed. A traversal is a mechanism which makes it possible to examine each  item of a container once, in a clearly specified order. For example some containers  can be traversed sequentially, in one direction or two; tree structures lend themselves  to preorder, postorder and breadth-first traversals.
			</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph> For each of these criteria the Base library offers a single-inheritance hierarchy of deferred classes. The top of the access hierarchy is class 
			<link>
				<url>../../reference/structures/access/collection_chart.xml</url>
				<label>COLLECTION</label>
			</link>; the top of the storage hierarchy is class 
			<link>
				<url>/libraries/base/reference/structures/storage/box_chart.xml</url>
				<label>BOX</label>
			</link>; the top of the traversal hierarchy is class 
			<link>
				<url>/libraries/base/reference/structures/traversing/traversable_chart.xml</url>
				<label>TRAVERSABLE</label>
			</link>. These three classes are heirs of the most general class, 
			<link>
				<url>../../reference/structures/access/container_chart.xml</url>
				<label>CONTAINER</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph></document>
