<document title="Introduction Dialog and Main Window" output="studio"><meta_data ><help /></meta_data><paragraph ><heading ><size >1</size>Introduction Dialog and Main Window</heading><paragraph > The EiffelCOMwizard can be launched from the Windows start menu:</paragraph>
<code_block >
Start-&gt;Programs-&gt;EiffelXX-&gt;EiffelCOMWizard
</code_block>

<paragraph > where EiffelXX corresponds to your Eiffel installation (e.g. Eiffel50). The following window will be displayed:</paragraph><heading ><size >2</size>EiffelCOM Wizard Main Window and Introduction Dialog</heading><image ><url >../images/com_image2.gif</url></image> <paragraph > The introductiondialog lets you choose between opening an existing project orcreating a new one either from a COM definition or from an Eiffelproject. Creating a new project will open the <link ><url >02_generated_code_type_d.xml</url></link>Generated CodeType Dialog. Opening an existing project will display an OpenFile Dialog from which you can select a previously saved EiffelCOMproject.</paragraph><paragraph >The four buttons at the bottom of the dialog <italic >Back</italic>,<italic >Next</italic>, <italic >Cancel</italic> and <italic >Help</italic> are common to alldialogs displayed throughout the execution of the wizard.<italic >Next</italic> validates all the values entered in the current dialogand activates the next one. <italic >Back</italic> discards all the valuesentered in current dialog and displays the previous one.<italic >Cancel</italic> exits the dialog and discards all the values entered.Finally, <italic >Help</italic> brings up this manual.</paragraph><heading ><size >2</size>EiffelCOM Wizard Main Window</heading><image ><url >../images/com_image3.gif</url></image><paragraph > The main windowincludes a toolbar and a menu. The first three buttons on thetoolbar correspond to the first three entries in the File menu:New, Open and Save. New resets all the information previouslyentered in the wizard. Open brings up an Open File Dialog that canbe used to retrieve a previously saved EiffelCOM project. Save isused to save the current project. A project is defined by all thevalues entered in the wizard. A project can be saved only after thewizard has been run. The file extension for an EiffelCOM project isewz.</paragraph><paragraph > The second menu,Build, includes the entries Launch Wizard and Generate (no wizard)corresponding respectively to the last two toolbar buttons. Theformer activates the Generated Code Type Dialog. while the laterlaunches the generation with the current settings and bypasses thedialogs. This last button can be used only when a project has beenloaded or when the wizard has been run once.</paragraph><paragraph > The third menu,<italic >Help</italic>, includes <italic >Help</italic> and <italic >About EiffelCOM</italic>.<italic >Help</italic> brings up this manual. <italic >About EiffelCOM</italic> brings<italic />About EiffelCOM Dialog that gives the version number.</paragraph><heading ><size >2</size>About EiffelCOM Dialog</heading><image ><url >../images/com_image4.gif</url></image><note > Note:Before you launch the wizard make sure you have a COM definitionfile or an Eiffel project ready for processing.</note><seealso >See Also: <link ><url >01_introduction_d.xml</url><label >Introduction Dialog and MainWindow</label></link>, <link ><url >02_generated_code_type_d.xml</url><label >Generated CodeType Dialog</label></link>, <link ><url >03_definition_file_d.xml</url><label >DefinitionFile Dialog</label></link>, <link ><url >04_eiffel_project_file_d.xml</url><label >EiffelProject File Dialog</label></link>, <link ><url >05_destination_folder_d.xml</url><label >Destination Folder Dialog</label></link>,<link ><url >06_idl_marshalling_d.xml</url><label >IDL Marshaling DefinitionDialog</label></link>, <link ><url >07_type_lybrary_m_d.xml</url><label >Type LibraryMarshaling Definition Dialog</label></link>, <link ><url >08_final_d.xml</url><label >FinalDialog</label></link>, <link ><url >09_com_definition_file_processing.xml</url><label >COMDefinition File Processing</label></link>, <link ><url >10_eiffel_project_processing.xml</url><label >Eiffel ProjectProcessing</label></link>, <link ><url >11_generated_files.xml</url><label >GeneratedFiles</label></link>, <link ><url >12_class_hierarchy.xml</url><label >Class Hierarchy</label></link>,<link ><url >13_accessing_component.xml</url><label >Accessing a Component</label></link>, <link ><url >14_building_component.xml</url><label >Building a Component</label></link></seealso></paragraph></document>