<document output="envision" title="Class View">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>  The Class View allows you to browse the Eiffel classes that are included in your  solution. You may only browse the classes of a compiled system that is  currently open in Visual Studio. As well as being able to view available  classes, the Class View allows you to see the 
			<link>
				<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/index.xml</url><anchor_name>feature</anchor_name>
				<label>features</label>
			</link>  of each class and the relationships between classes, for example, 
			<link>
				<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/index.xml</url><anchor_name>ancestors</anchor_name>
				<label>ancestors</label>
			</link>  or 
			<link>
				<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/index.xml</url><anchor_name>descendants</anchor_name>
				<label>descendants</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>General Property Page</alt_text>
				<url>General_class_view.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>  Looking at the screenshot, you can see that there is one root node in the Class  View, which corresponds to the fact that there is only one project, named  "sample", in the currently opened solution. If there is more than one project  in the current solution, then there will be multiple entries in the tree. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>  Each node in the tree is expandable, and expanding a node will allow you to see  the pertinent information regarding the current node that was opened. For  example, in the screenshot above, the cluster "root_cluster" is expanded, and  this allows the Class View to display all Eiffel classes within that cluster  (Only one in this case). In the case of an expanded tree node representing an  Eiffel class, you can see that information specific to classes has been  displayed, and is browsable. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>  You may browse as deeply within the Class View as is necessary, as there is no  limit to the depth of the nodes that may be opened. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>  Right clicking on any node in the Class View will display a 
			<link>
				<url>context_menu.xml</url>
				<label>context menu</label>
			</link> for the current node.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>  For details of the hierarchy displayed in the Class View, click 
			<link>
				<url>hierarchy.xml</url>
				<label>here</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
		<line_break/>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/20_Solution_Explorer/index.xml</url>
				<label>Solution Explorer</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/40_Object_Browser/index.xml</url>
				<label>Object Browser</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/index.xml</url>
				<label>Using ENViSioN! Within Visual Studio.NET</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
