<document output="envision" title="Assembly Info Property Page">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<table>
			<row>
				<cell>
					<paragraph>The Assembly Info Property Page allows you to embed information about the  project and any legality information into the compiled assembly manifest.
						<line_break/>
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Assembly Information
					</heading>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Title</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>The Title property gives the assembly a real title. It expands upon the System  Name given to the assembly.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Description </bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>This property expands upon the Title property and gives a more detailed  description of what the assembly is used for. This allows other developers and  co-workers to identify that they are using the assembly for what it was  intended for. </paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Company </bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>The name of the company who places ownership over the assembly .</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Product </bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>If the assembly belongs to a product or family of products then specify the  product information here.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Trademark </bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>The Trademark property allows you to embed any Trademark information into the  assembly.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Copyright</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>The Copyright property allows you to embed any Copyright information into the  assembly.
						<line_break/>
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Versioning
					</heading>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Version</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>The Version property is a compulsory property that defines the version number  for the assembly.</paragraph>
					<warning>
						<bold>Note:</bold> The version number must contain four  sections delimited by a period (.). Each section can only contain numerical '0'  to '9' characters. The four parts of the version number are: Major Revision,  Minor Revision, Build, QFE (Quick Fix Engineering).
					</warning>
					<line_break/>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Localization
					</heading>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Culture</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph> This property allows you to select from a number of cultures that will  designate the compiled assembly to a specific localization. </paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<seealso>
							<bold>See Also</bold>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>project_configuration.htm</url>
								<label>Property Page Overview</label>
							</link>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>general_ppg.htm</url>
								<label>GeneralProperty Page</label>
							</link>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>assertions_ppg.htm</url>
								<label>Assertions Property Page</label>
							</link>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>ExternalsPage.htm</url>
								<label/>
							</link>
						</seealso>
					</paragraph>
				</cell>
			</row>
		</table>
	</paragraph></document>