<document title="Assembly Info Page" output="envision">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>20</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>1</size> Assembly Info Property Page
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The Assembly Info Property Page alls you to embed information about the project and any legality information into the finally compiled assembly. This information is useful to provide for a project for a number of reasons. Firstly some of the information, if supplied, can be viewed from Windows simply by right clicking on the compiled assembly and viewing its properties. Secondly embedding information allows other developers, co-workers and customers to identify what the assembly is, what it is used for, ensure that they are using the correct version and more.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<paragraph>
				<image>
					<alt_text>Assembly Info Property Page</alt_text>
					<url>AssemblyInfoPPG.png</url>
				</image>
			</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>Assembly Information (Optional)
			</heading>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Title
			</heading>
			<paragraph>The Title property gives the assembly a real title. It expands upon the System Name given to the assembly.</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Description 
			</heading>
			<paragraph>This property expands upon the Title property and gives a more detailed description of what the assembly is used for. This allows other developers and co-workers to identify that they are using the assembly for what it was intended for. </paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Company 
			</heading>
			<paragraph>The name of the company who places ownership over the assembly .</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Product 
			</heading>
			<paragraph>If the assembly belongs to a product or family of products then specify the product information here.</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Trademark 
			</heading>
			<paragraph>The Trademark property allows you to embed any Trademark information into the assembly.</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Copyright
			</heading>
			<paragraph>The Copyright property allows you to embed any Copyright information into the assembly.</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>Localization
			</heading>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Culture
			</heading>
			<paragraph> This property allows you to select from a number of cultures that will designate the compiled assembly to a specific localization. For more information on cultures please refer here. 
				<heading>
					<size>2</size> Versioning
				</heading>
				<heading>
					<size>3</size>Version
				</heading>
				<paragraph>The Version property is a compulsory property that defines the version number for the assembly. The version number contains, and must contain, four sections delimited by a period '.'. Each section can only contain numerical '0' to '9' characters. The four parts of the version number are as following Major, Minor, Build, QFE (Quick Fix Engineering). For more information on version numbers please refer here.</paragraph>
				<seealso>
					<bold>See Also</bold>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>./ProjectConfiguration.xml</url>
						<label>Property Page Overview</label>
					</link>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>GeneralPage.xml</url>
						<label>General Property Page</label>
					</link>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>DebugPage.xml</url>
						<label>Debug Property Page</label>
					</link>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>ExternalsPage.xml</url>
						<label></label>
					</link>
				</seealso>
			</paragraph>
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>
