<document title="Cluster Page" output="envision">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>50</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>1</size>Clusters Property Page
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The Clusters Property Page allows you to add, edit and remove clusters to and from the configuration(s). This property page is more feature pack that it four preceding property pages. Tolearn more about what a cluster is an how they are an essential part of the Eiffel environment please 
			<link>
				<url>general/guided_tour/language/tutorial-04.xml</url>
				<label>  refer here</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
		<bold>Note</bold>: It is recommended that you add, edit or remove clusters to the current project with 'All Configurations' selected in the Configuration option at the top of the Property Page Dialog,unless you need different clusters for each one of the configurations. Doing this will save you time as you only need to add a cluster once instead of once for every configuration.
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Clusters Property Page</alt_text>
				<url>ClustersPPG.PNG</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>The Cluster Property Page
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> A good starting point is to explain how the clusters property page works is the essential parts of the page itself.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The clusters section of the property page is split into two panes. The left pane contains the Cluster Tree, which is a hierarchical view of the currently selected configurations, accompaniedby an Add and Delete button to add and remove clusters from the configuration. The right pane contains all of the cluster specific properties for the currently selected cluster in the cluster tree. Changing the selectedcluster will automatically redisplay all of the properties relevant to the new selection. The except to this is if the root node in the tree is selected, as this is not a cluster but the System Name.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Cluster Namespace
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The first of the cluster properties is the Cluster Namespace. This is an optional property, however if a namespace is supplied the it must conform to the same namespace rules defined forthe 
			<link>
				<url>GeneralPage.xml</url>
				<label>General Property  Page's</label>
			</link> '
			<link>
				<url>./GeneralPage.htm#DefaultNamespace</url>
				<label>
					<italic>Default Namespace</italic>
				</label>
			</link>' option. 
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Cluster Path
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The Cluster Path property is the location of the cluster. This property cannot remain empty. </paragraph>
		<bold>Caution</bold>: If a child cluster is using a relative path instead of an absolute path, then the path will be relative to the parent cluster and not the project directory.
		<line_break></line_break>
		<line_break></line_break>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Library And All
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Having either the Library or All property checked will recursive search all of the clusters sub-directories for classes, where as have both unchecked will only look in the directory specified in
			<link>
				<url>#ClusterPath</url>
				<label>
					<italic>Cluster  Path</italic>
				</label>
			</link>. Have either checked will enable the options to exclude directories and/or classes from any sub directory. The Library and All properties are exclusive and cannot be used together. TheLibrary property has the additional feature of making all of the classes found in the selected cluster read-only, so they cannot be edited from Visual Studio.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>If a cluster is part of the Eiffel Library then the Library and All properties cannot be changed.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Override
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The override option can only be applied to one cluster in each configuration. This property is to resolve any class name clashes between the selected cluster and any cluster in theconfiguration. The cluster that has the Override property checked will be cluster who's classes are used over any of the other clusters.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Exclude Subclusters&amp; Files
		</heading>
		<paragraph>If either the
			<link>
				<url>#LibraryAndAll</url>
				<label>
					<italic>All</italic>
				</label>
			</link> or
			<link>
				<url>#LibraryAndAll</url>
				<label> 
					<italic> Library</italic>
				</label>
			</link> property for the selected cluster have been checked then the compile will recursively look in all of the clusters sub-directories for classes. This may lead to one or more classes being locatedthat have the same name. In this situation you can choose to exclude any sub-directory or files from being searched by the compiler. A comma delimited summary shows all of the directories and file that have been selectedfor exclusion. To modify or add what should be excluded use the (...) button. Refer section on
			<link>
				<url>#HowToExclude</url>
				<label>How To Exclude Subclusters and Files</label>
			</link>. 
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Overriding Default Assertions
		</heading>
		<paragraph>It may be necessary to override the default assertions defined in the 
			<link>
				<url>AssertionsPage.xml</url>
				<label>  Assertions Property Page</label>
			</link>for the selected cluster. Simply check those assertions that are required by the cluster and the default assertions will become overridden. 
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Adding A Cluster
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> Adding a cluster is a very simple process, but it warrants a few rules regarding the next steps before finishing up with the newly added cluster. 
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Adding A Cluster
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Cluster a based on a hierarchical system where a single cluster may have zero or more child clusters and those clusters, if any, it turn may also have child clusters of their own. This meansthere are two ways to add a cluster. Add a cluster with a parent or without. To add a cluster to the root of the project (without a parent) simply click the root tree view node (this will displayed as the System Name set in theGeneral page) and then click the '
			<italic>Add</italic>' button. To add a child cluster simply highlight the corresponding parent cluster node in the tree view, then click the '
			<italic>Add</italic>' button.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You should now be presented with the option to edit the cluster name (by default the cluster name will be new_cluster(
			<italic>nth</italic>) where (
			<italic>nth</italic>) is the index ifnew_cluster already existing in any one of the projects configurations). You must enter a valid cluster name governed by the following rules
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item> Must begin with a character between 'a' to 'z' or 'A' to 'Z'. </item>
			<item> May only contain alphanumerical characters and underscores thereafter (no white spaces) </item>
			<item>  Must not already be in use by any other cluster in any one of the selected  configurations</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>If any of these rules a broken then you will be presented with an error dialog giving you an alternative cluster name that is valid.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The final condition that has to be met before you switch to another cluster, and another or apply the setting is to specify the cluster path. The path cannot remain empty! The (...) buttonnext to the cluster path provides the ability to browse for a cluster path.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>That is it. You have now added a cluster to your system.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Adding Eiffel Library Clusters
		</heading>
		<paragraph>If at any point you need to add a cluster from the Eiffel Library or Library.net folders (located in the installation directory) then these clusters will automatically be mark the library property,which cannot be changed. This prevents accidental changes being made to the Eiffel library classes through Visual Studio, which could lead to many problems in the future.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Modifying A Cluster
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> After a cluster has been successfully added it may be returned to at any point for modification. Every property of the cluster may be modified through the cluster properties paneon the right side of the dialog. To modify the cluster name itself double click on the relevant cluster in the cluster tree. From there you will be able to rename the cluster to any name that satisfies the rules for a cluster name(see Adding A Cluster for these rules).
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Removing A Cluster
		</heading>
		<line_break></line_break>
		<line_break></line_break>
		<bold>Note</bold>: Removing a cluster from the project is irreversible unless you click 
		<italic>'Cancel</italic>' on the Property Page Dialog.
		<line_break></line_break> Removing A Cluster
		<paragraph>To remove a cluster all that is needed to be done is to select the cluster to be removed from the project and click the '
			<italic>Delete</italic>' button below the tree of clusters. Onceclicked you will need to confirm the removal of the selected cluster. Clicking OK on the confirmation dialog removes the cluster, Cancel leaves the cluster in the configuration.
		</paragraph>
		<bold>Note</bold>: If the selected cluster has one or more children clusters, if you choose to remove the cluster all child clusters will also be removed from the current configuration. 
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>How To Exclude Subdirectories And Files
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break></line_break> As stated in the brief description of the
			<link>
				<url>#ExcludeSubClusAndFiles</url>
				<label>
					<italic>Excluded  Subdirectories&amp; Files</italic>
				</label>
			</link> property above, if the
			<link>
				<url>#LibraryAndAll</url>
				<label> 
					<italic> All</italic> 
				</label>
			</link>or
			<link>
				<url>#LibraryAndAll</url>
				<label>
					<italic>Library</italic>
				</label>
			</link> property are checked for a cluster then the compiler will recursively look in every directory for Eiffel classes. This can create a problem when the compiler finds two classes with the samename. By clicking on the ellipse button next to the list of excludes (...) you will be presented with the following dialog.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Exclude Subdirectories and File Dialog</alt_text>
				<url>ExcludeDirFile.PNG</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph> The dialog here is split vertically into two sections. The top half is the list of all subdirectories taken from the selected clusters path. All of the checked items in the list are those that havebeen chosen to be excluded. To add or remove a directory simple check or uncheck the corresponding folder respectively. 
			<bold>Note</bold>: If the cluster property page is being  used in multiple configurations wherethe selected cluster paths are not the  same, then the list of folder to exclude will be empty. The excluded  subdirectories will subsequently be added to the list of Files and Temp  Directories.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The lower half is the list of files and any temporary directories that need to be excluded. To add a file or temporary directory, enter the name only (not the full path) of the file or directory tobe excluded followed by click on the '
			<italic>Add</italic>' button. To remove a file or subdirectory highlight the item to be removed in the list and click '
			<italic>Remove</italic> '.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Once you are finished with the dialog click '
			<italic>OK</italic>' to confirm the changes and set the excludes or '
			<italic>Cancel</italic> ' to discard those changes made. 
			<heading>
				<size>2</size>Using The Cluster Property Page With Multiple Configurations
			</heading>
			<paragraph>
				<line_break></line_break> Viewing the cluster property page with multiple configurations will only show the common clusters, in the cluster tree, between all of the configurations. Select one ofthe common cluster the cluster properties will display what they can that is common to that individual cluster. Unlike the all of the property pages up until this point a 
				<bold>blank property does not denote  an uncommonproperty value</bold>, instead it simply means that no value has been given. For the '
				<link>
					<url>#ClusterNamespace</url>
					<label>
						<italic>Cluster Namespace</italic>
					</label>
				</link>' and '
				<link>
					<url>#ClusterPath</url>
					<label>
						<italic>Cluster Path</italic>
					</label>
				</link>' properties uncommon values will be displayed as
				<bold>&lt;Multiple Values&gt;</bold>. Uncommon values for each of the check boxes will show an undetermined state (ticked and lightly grayed out - not disabled!). Finally for the summary of '
				<link>
					<url>#ExcludeSubClusAndFiles</url>
					<label>  Exclude Subdirectories and Files</label>
				</link>', only those that are common to the selected cluster for all of the configurations will be shown.
			</paragraph>
			<heading>
				<size>3</size>Adding A Cluster With Multiple Configurations
			</heading>
			<paragraph> When adding a cluster to multiple configuration it is not possible to give the new cluster the same name as a any other cluster in any configuration. Attempts to do so will be metwith an error message suggesting a valid name, which will be the given cluster name suffixed with an index value. </paragraph>
			<paragraph>
				<seealso>
					<bold>See Also</bold>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>general/guided_tour/language/tutorial-04.xml</url>
						<label>An Eiffel Tutorial:  THE SOFTWARE PROCESS IN EIFFEL</label>
					</link>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>./ProjectConfiguration.xml</url>
						<label>Property Page Overview</label>
					</link>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>AssertionsPage.xml</url>
						<label>Assertions Property Page</label>
					</link>
					<line_break></line_break>
					<link>
						<url>AssemblyReferencesPage.xml</url>
						<label>Assembly References Property Page</label>
					</link>
				</seealso>
				<line_break></line_break>
			</paragraph>
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>