<document output="envision" title="Clusters Property Page">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>40</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>  The Clusters Property Page allows you to add, edit and remove clusters to and  from your projects the configuration(s).To learn more about what a  cluster is an how they are an essential part of the Eiffel environment please  refer to the 
			<link>
				<url>/general\guided_tour\language\tutorial-04.xml</url>
				<label>guided tour</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Recommended</bold>: It is recommended that you add,  edit or removeclusters to the current project with 'All Configurations'  selected in the Configuration option at the top of the Property Page Dialog,  unless you need different clusters for each one of the configurations. Doing  this will save you time as you will only have to add a cluster once instead  ofonce for every configuration.
		</note>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Clusters Property Page</alt_text>
				<url>clusters_ppg.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Cluster Hierarchy
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The Cluster Hierarchy shows all of the explicitly added clusters to the current  selected project configuration. To add or remove clusters from the hierarchy,  use the 
			<bold>Add</bold> and 
			<bold>Remove</bold> buttons located to the  right on the it.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Adding a Cluster
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Clusters are based on a hierarchical system where a single cluster may have zero  or more child clusters and those clusters, if any, it turn may also have child  clusters of their own. This means there are two ways to add a cluster. Add a  cluster with a parent or without. To add a cluster to the root of the project  (without a parent) simply click the root tree view node (this will displayed  asthe System Name set in the General page) and then click the 
			<bold>Add</bold>  button. To add a child cluster simply highlight the corresponding parent  cluster node in the tree view, then click the 
			<bold>Add</bold> button.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You should now be presented with the option to edit the cluster name (by default  the cluster name will be new_cluster
			<italic>nth</italic> where <italic>nth</italic> is the  index if new_cluster already existing in any one of the projects  configurations). You must enter a valid cluster name governed by the following  rules:
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Should begin with a character between 'a' to 'z' or 'A' to 'Z'.  </item>
			<item>Shouldonly contain alphanumerical characters and underscores thereafter  (no white spaces).</item>
			<item>Must not already be in use by any other cluster in any one of the selected  configurations.</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Removing a Cluster
		</heading>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: Removing a cluster  from the project is irreversible unless you click <italic>'Cancel</italic>' on the  Property Page Dialog.
		</note>
		<paragraph>To remove a clustersimplyselect the cluster to be removed from the  project configuration and then click the 
			<bold>Remove</bold> button, right  of the Cluster Hierarchy. Once clicked you will need to confirm the removal of  the selected cluster. Clicking 
			<bold>OK</bold> on the confirmation dialog  removes the cluster, 
			<bold>Cancel</bold> leaves the cluster in the current  configuration.
		</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: If the selected  cluster has one or more children clusters, if you choose to remove the cluster  all child clusters will also be removed from the current configuration.
		</note>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Renaming a Cluster
		</heading>
		<paragraph>It is also possible to rename cluster. Slowly double click on the cluster node  you would to change and you will be presented withan edit box for you to  enter the new name. Use the tab key or click else where in the property page to  continue.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Basic Cluster Properties
		</heading>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Cluster Path
		</heading>
		<paragraph>  The Cluster Path property is the location of the cluster where the compiler  will look for Eiffel class .e files. Every cluster must have a path.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>For clusters that are achild of another cluster, you may use a relative  path prefixed with a dollar symbol ($), which represents the pathof the  parent clusters. You must follow the $ with a backslash (\) as the directory  seperator or the the two paths will be concatinated and may cause a compilation  error or even have the cluster point to a undesired location.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Include Subdirectories
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Checking this option will inform the compiler to recursively traverse through  all the subdirectories located at the specified cluster path.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Namespace
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Be default the compiler will use the cluster name as the part of the overall  namespace in the assembly manifest. Specifying a namespace will override this  behaviour and make use of the specified namespace instead of the cluster name.</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: A namespaces must begin with an alpha  character and succeeded by and alphanumberical, underscore (_) or period (.).  The character following a period must also only be an alpha character.
		</note>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>General Properties
		</heading>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Override
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The override option can only be applied to one cluster in each configuration.  This property is to resolve any class name clashes between the selected cluster  and anycluster in the configuration without the need to 
			<link>
				<url>#cluster_excludes</url>
				<label>exclude</label>
			</link> individual files. The cluster that has the Override property  checked will be cluster who's classes are used over any of the other clusters  in the universe.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Library
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The Library property is similar to Include Subdirectories in that it traverses  through a clusters subdirectories. A library cluster, however, is a cluster  who's contents in compiled once per configuration. Any modification to any  class from a library cluster will not have any affect unless a Rebuild or a  Clean and then Build is performed on the project.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Cluster Excludes
		</heading>
		<paragraph>If either the 
			<link>
				<url>#include_subdirectories</url>
				<label>Include Subcdirectories</label>
			</link>  or 
			<link> 
				<url>#LibraryAndAll</url>
				<label>Library</label>
			</link> property for the selected cluster have  been checked then the compile will recursively look in all of the  clusterssub-directories for classes. This maylead to class name  conficts as different libraries may use the same name for classes.In this  situationyou can choose to exclude any subdirectoryfrom being  searched or any file being include by the compiler at compile time.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The current cluster excluded items list is located underneath the  
			<link>
				<url>#namespace</url>
				<label>Namespace</label>
			</link> property, accompanied by an 
			<bold>Add</bold> and a 
			<bold>Remove</bold>  button.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Adding an Item to Exclude
		</heading>
		<paragraph>To add a newitem to the list of excluded item, click 
			<bold>Add</bold> next  to the Excludes list. An edit box will appear at the end of the Excludes list  allowing you to enter the name of a file or directory to exclude.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Removing Excluded Items
		</heading>
		<paragraph>To remove one or more items, select the items you would like to have removed  from the list and click 
			<bold>Remove</bold> button next the the Excludes  list.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Renaming an Excluded Item
		</heading>
		<paragraph>To rename an already excluded item, slowly double click on the item you would to  change. And edit box will then appear for you to enter the new name.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Cluster Level Assertions
		</heading>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Use Defaults
		</heading>
		<paragraph>When Use Defaults is checked the assertion specified in the Assertions Property  Page are used for the cluster. If you want more fine grained control over  assertions on a per cluster level then uncheck this property. Unchecking Use  Default will enable the assertion check boxes below.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Require
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Checking this property will perform runtime precondition assertion verification  on all class located in the currently selected cluster.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Ensure
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Checking this property will perform runtime postcondition assertion verification  on all class located in the currently selected cluster.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Check
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Checking this property will perform runtime check  assertion verification on all class located in the currently selected cluster.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Loop
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Checking this property will perform runtime loop variant assertion  verification on all class located in the currently selected cluster.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Invariant
		</heading>
		<paragraph>Checking this property will perform runtime invariant assertion verification on  all class located in the currently selected cluster.Setting</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Using the Cluster Property Page with Multiple  Configurations
		</heading>
		<paragraph>When viewing the cluster property page using more that one configuration,  thecluster hierarchywill only show the clusters common to all  configurations. The common factor is simply the cluster's name and it's  position in the cluster hierarchy. For the individual cluster properties where  an uncommon value between all configuration is found the property remains  blank,check boxes will show and intermediate selected state andthe  cluster Exludes list will only show those common excluded items in the list.  You are free to modify and change any property, regardless of its state. Once  changed, the change will be reflected in all of the selected configurations.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>3</size>Adding A Cluster With Multiple Configurations
		</heading>
		<paragraph> When adding a cluster to multiple configurations it is not possible to give the  new cluster the same name as any other cluster in any of the included  configurations. </paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>project_configuration.htm</url>
				<label>Property Page Overview</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>assertions_ppg.htm</url>
				<label>Assertions Property Page</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>externals_ppg.htm</url>
				<label>External sProperty Page</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
