<document output="envision" title="Externals Property Page">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>50</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<table>
			<row>
				<cell>
					<paragraph>The Externals property page is used to add any project
						<link>
							<url>#include_paths</url>
							<label> include  paths</label>
						</link>and any external
						<link>
							<url>#object_files</url>
							<label> object files</label>
						</link> (*.obj  or *.lib) required when compiling the unmanaged C/C++ code in your project.
						<line_break/>
						<line_break/>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<image>
							<alt_text>Externals Property Page</alt_text>
							<url>externals_ppg.png</url>
						</image>
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Include Paths
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The Include Paths section allows any number of include paths to be defined to  allow the compiler to located the header definition files for any referenced  object files.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Adding an Include Path</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>There are two options available to add and include path. Firstly a path my be  physically entered via the supplied edit box located underneath the list of  include paths. Alternatively clicking the ellipse (...) button will open a  folder dialog where a specific folder may be located. Once an include path has  been chosen the corresponding 'Add' button become enabled. Click it will add  the include path to the end of the list.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Removing an Include Path</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>To remove an include path,select the item in the include paths list to be  removed and click the corresponding 'Remove' button. The remove button will  only become enabled once and include path has been selected. </paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Renaming Include Paths</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>To rename an include path do as you would in Windows Explorer and select the  item to rename and then click it again. The bounding box will then appear over  the selected item allowing you to rename the include path.
						<line_break/>
						<line_break/>
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Object Files
					</heading>
					<paragraph>Object files are pre-compiled binary files that can be linked with the header  files used by Eiffel external classes making use of C or C++. Failure to supply  and object file corresponding to a used header file will result in a linking  error when compiling any unmanagedC/C++ code. </paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Adding an Object File</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>Adding an object file works in the same way in adding an
						<link>
							<url>#include_paths</url>
							<label>  Include Path</label>
						</link>. There are two available ways to add an object file.  Through physically entering the object file path into the edit box located  underneath the list of object files, or by clicking the ellipse (...) button  next to it. Clicking the ellipse will open a file browse dialog where an object  file can be chosen. Once an object file has been entered or located through the  browse dialog, click the corresponding 'Add' button and the object file will be  append to the bottom of the object files list.
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Removing An Object File</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>To remove anobject file,select the item in theobject  fileslist to be removed and click the corresponding 'Remove' button. The  remove button will only become enabled once andobject filehas been  selected.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<bold>Renaming Object Files</bold>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph> To rename anobject filedo as you would in Windows Explorer and  select the item to rename and then click it again. The bounding box will then  appear over the selected item allowing you to rename the object files. </paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<seealso>
							<bold>See Also</bold>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>project_configuration.htm</url>
								<label>Property Page Overview</label>
							</link>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>clusters_ppg.htm</url>
								<label>Clusters Property Page</label>
							</link>
							<line_break/>
							<link>
								<url>advanced_ppg.htm</url>
								<label>AdvancedProperty Page</label>
							</link>
						</seealso>
					</paragraph>
				</cell>
			</row>
		</table>
	</paragraph></document>