<document output="envision" title="Project Property Pages Overview">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Project Property Pages</envision_title>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
					<paragraph>Eiffel for Visual Studio.NET provides the facilities to modify your projects  setting via a number of property pages. The property pages can be used to  modify a single projects configuration (debug, release, etc), modify all  configurations in a project, modify the configurations of multiple  projects in a multiple project solution, and even multiple configurations  for multiple projects. </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Understanding The Property Page Dialog
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The property page dialog is a common dialog to Visual Studio, it allows the  manipulate of your projects setting.To discover what each one of the  property pages does see the below section 
						<link>
							<anchor_name>property_pages</anchor_name>
							<label>The Property  Pages</label>
						</link>.
						<line_break/>
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Viewing in multiple configuration modes:
					</heading>
					<paragraph>There are two ways that a projects properties can be manipulated. Firstly  there's single configuration. This is a single selected project, where the  configuration property is set to either debug or release (or any other  configuration added to the project). The alternative way is to manipulate  multiple configurations. This is can be a single project with the configuration  property set to 'All Configurations' and/or multiple projects in the solution  are selected.</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<line_break/>
						<image>
							<alt_text/>
							<url>property_page_header.png</url>
						</image>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<line_break/>  When viewing in multiple configurations some previously entered values (in a  single configuration) may not be display, or displayed correctly. This is  normal as the property page cannot find a common value for each one of the  configurations and so leaves it blank or replaces the value with a value that  represents different values. And example of this would be to have two projects  in a solution. 
						<bold>ProjectA</bold> and 
						<bold>ProjectB</bold> . The  system names ( 
						<link>
							<url>general_ppg.xml</url>
							<label>General Property Page</label>
						</link>) for these  projects are ProjectA and ProjectB respectively. When each one of the projects  is selected individually the general property page will display the respective  system name. However if both projects are selected when viewing their  properties the system name will not display anything as the two system names  are different. If we were then to change this value, then both ProjectA's and  ProjectB's system name will be changed to new value.
					</paragraph>
					<warning>
						<bold>Recommended</bold> : It is recommended that when  making additions to your project(s) that the 'All Configurations' be selected  in the configuration drop down list box on the property page dialog. This is so  you can ensure that when adding a cluster, assembly reference, external or  setting any other basic property, all configurations will have these changes.  If these settings where to be made in a single configurations, then you will  have to switch to each one of the other configurations and reapply the settings  for each. Each one of the configurations modes (such as debug, release etc.)  should be reserved for use in setting configuration specific properties. An  example of a configuration specific property would be 
						<link>
							<url>debugging_ppg.xml</url><anchor_name>generate_debug_info</anchor_name>
							<label>Generate  Debug Info</label>
						</link> in the 
						<link>
							<url>debugging_ppg.xml</url>
							<label>Debugging Property Page</label>
						</link>..  For a release configuration there is no need to generate the debugging  information, as your project has already been debugged and is read to be  released.
					</warning>
					<line_break/>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Saving Your Configuration
					</heading>
					<paragraph>To save all of the changes made in the property pages click on the 
						<bold>Apply</bold>  or 
						<bold>OK </bold>button located at the bottom right of the property page  dialog.
					</paragraph>
					<warning>
						<bold>Note</bold>: Unless stated, any changes to the  properties in the property pages require a system re-compilation to reflect  those changes made.
					</warning>
					<line_break/>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Switch Configurations and Projects
					</heading>
					<paragraph>The property page dialog is a non-modal window so you are able to change the  project that is being configured to another project, simply click clicking on  the desired project node in the 
						<link>
							<url>/10_Developing\10_Getting_Started\10_Using_ENViSioN\20_Solution_Explorer\index.xml</url>
							<label>  Solution Explorer</label>
						</link>. The property page will automatically update with the  newly selected project settings. If any unsaved changes have been made to the  previous project, then you will be asked to save those project settings before  the project configurations are switched.
						<line_break/>
					</paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>The Property Pages
					</heading>
					<paragraph>In total there are seven independently configurable property pages for an Eiffel  ENViSioN! project. </paragraph>
					<list ordered="false">
						<item>
							<bold>General</bold>  - For all of the general (basic) project properties.
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Assembly Info</bold>  - Information about the project (version number, description etc.).
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Assertions</bold>  - The project wide Design By Contract settings.
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Clusters</bold>  - Allows manipulation of the projects clusters.
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Externals</bold>  - All of the object files and include paths for the project.
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Advanced</bold>- Advanced  project settings.
						</item>
						<item>
							<bold>Debugging</bold> - The debugging  options for the project.
						</item>
					</list>
	</paragraph></document>
