<document title="Import From EiffelStudio Project Wizard" output="envision">
	<meta_data>
		<help/>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<bold>Availability</bold>: Enterprise and Free versions.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>This wizard enables you to import an EiffelStudio (version 5.2 or greater) project into a new Eiffel ENViSioN!! project.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Page content
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The wizard comprises of the following pages:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>
				<bold>Introduction Page</bold>: Introducing the wizard and all of its requirements.
			</item>
			<item>
				<bold>Original EiffelStudio Project Page</bold>: The source EiffelStudio project and its configuration.
			</item>
			<item>
				<bold>Summary</bold>: The summary of the wizard and what is going to happens next.
			</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Requirements
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The Import From EiffelStudio Project Wizard at a minimum requires the EiffelStudio project ace file, used in the importing into Visual Studio.NET, to have been created for EiffelStudio version 5.2 or better. Supplying an corrupt or incorrect ace file will result in the presentation of the project wizards error page. You cannot continue past this point until a correct ace file has been specified.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>EiffelStudio.5 Enterprise or Free Edition Project Selection Page
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The first page of the wizard is the only functioning page for this wizard. It asks for the EiffelStudio project Ace file (*.ace) to import the project setting from. This must be an ace file used for a EiffelStudio.2 (or better) Enterprise or Free edition, and must be a valid Eiffel for .NET ace file.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>You may optionally select to duplicate the project files (Eiffel classes, resources etc.) by checking the 'Duplicate project files' option. If you do not want to duplicate the exiting EiffelStudio project files then they will be shared between Eiffel ENViSioN! and EiffelStudio, however each will have their respective independent project configuration file(s). Upon checking the 'Duplicate project files' option the 'Project Root Cluster Path' becomes active to allow you to specify the root path to copy the project files from. If you have chosen to duplicate the project files then this path must point to a valid project path and cannot be left empty.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Import EiffelStudio Wizard</alt_text>
				<url>.\import_eiffelstudio_page1.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>Click next to continue.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Summary Page
		</heading>
		<paragraph>When the finish button is clicked the wizard will being to import the EiffelStudio project into Visual Studio.NET as a new Eiffel ENViSioN! project. This may take some time depending on the size of your project and whether or not you are duplicating any project files.</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: Unlike other Eiffel ENViSioN! project the Import From EiffelStudio Project Wizard does not compile the project the first time it is opened. It is advisable to check that all cluster paths and assembly reference paths are correct before compiling for the first time.
		</note>
		<line_break/>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../../../../20_Managing_Projects/10_Configuring_A_Project/10_Project_Property_Pages/index.xml</url>
				<label>Property  Pages</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/10_Adding_A_New_Project/index.xml</url>
				<label>  Adding a New Project</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
