<document title="Import EiffelStudio Project Wizard" output="envision">
	<meta_data>
		<help/>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>Availability: Enterprise and Free versions.</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break/> This wizard enables you to import and EiffelStudio (version 5.2 or greater) project into Visual Studio.NET.
			<line_break/>
			<line_break/>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Page content
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break/> The wizard comprises of the following pages:
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item> Introduction Page - Introducing the wizard and its requirements </item>
			<item> Original EiffelStudio Project - The source EiffelStudio project settings </item>
			<item>  Summary - The summary of the wizard, and what happens next</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Requirements
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break/> The Import EiffelStudio Project Wizard requires that the project's ace file used in importing a project from EiffelStudio into VisualStudio.NET was created for/inEiffelStudio version 5.2 or better. Failure to supply a correct ace file will result in the wizard displaying an error page not allowing you to continue until a correct ace file has been specified. The wizard alsorequires a valid project path to read the contents of the original EiffelStudio project from. Again failure to supply a correct path will result in an error.
			<line_break/>
			<line_break/>
			<line_break/>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>EiffelStudio52. Enterprise or Free Edition Project Selection
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break/> The first page of the wizard is the only functioning page for this wizard. It asks for the EiffelStudio project Ace file (*.ace) to import the project setting from. Thismust be an ace file used for EiffelStudio5.2 Enterprise or Free edition, and must be a .NET ace file.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Import EiffelStudio Wizard</alt_text>
				<url>import_eiffel_studio_wizard.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>Cluster Selection
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break/> The next page of the wizard allows you to specify which classes you would like access to through the Solution Explorer. The classes are chosen on a clusterlevel, and all classes contain within those cluster will be visible in the Solution Explorer. By default all those clusters that are marked as library clusters or are clusters from the EiffelBase, WEL or EiffelVision areexcluded as there are many classes.
			<line_break/>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The 'Excluded Clusters' list is the list of clusters that will not have documentation generated for them and the 'Included Clusters' list will. You can include/exclude clustersusing one of the four selection buttons ' 
			<bold>&lt;&lt;</bold>', ' 
			<bold>&lt;</bold>', '&gt;' or '&gt;&gt;'.
		</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item> '&lt;&lt;' will exclude all of clusters. </item>
			<item> '&lt;' will exclude only those selected clusters in the Included Clusters list. </item>
			<item> '&gt;' will include only those selected clusters in the Excluded Clusters list. </item>
			<item>  '&gt;&gt;' will include all of the clusters.</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text>Import EiffelStudio Wizard</alt_text>
				<url>import_eiffel_studio_wizard_clusters.png</url>
			</image>
			<line_break/>
			<line_break/>
			<line_break/>
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>N.B.
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<line_break/> When the finish button is clicked, the wizard will being to import the EiffelStudio project supplied into Visual Studio.NET. This may take some time depending onthe size of your project.
			<line_break/>
		</paragraph>
		<bold>Caution</bold>: Please check that the paths to any references in your project are still valid. Such references are the cluster paths, include paths, object files and locallyreferenced assemblies. These can be verified using the ' 
		<link>
			<url>../ProjectConfiguration/GettingStarted/ProjectConfiguration.xml</url>
			<label>Property  Pages</label>
		</link>'
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/10_Adding_A_New_Project/index.xml</url>
				<label>  Adding a New Project</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>