<document title="EiffelBuild Version History">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>EiffelBuild Version History</envision_title>
				<envision_location>EiffelEnvision\Tools\EiffelBuild</envision_location>
				<envision_pseudo_name>30</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>6.2 Release
		</heading>
		<paragraph>No changes.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>6.1 Release
		</heading>
		<paragraph>No changes.</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>6.0 Release
		</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Code generation includes the facility of closing the application when last window is closed.</item>
			<item>The EiffelBuild binary has been renamed into <bold>esbuilder</bold>.</item>
			<item>Fixed crash when generating code which included a combo box in read-only mode.</item>
			<item>Fixed bug#12920 where pressing a digit while dropping was not adding x-time the selected widgets (where x is the digit pressed).</item>
			<item>Fixed bug#12210 where pixmaps set on a menu would be incorrectly displayed in the generated executable (The last added one will always be shown for all menu entries with a pixmap).</item>
			<item>Fixed bug#11878 where EiffelBuild would crash when saving a project just after removing an event.</item>
			<item>Fixed bug#11738 where EiffelBuild would crash  when picking and dropping a top level widget into the Generate button.</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>5.7 Release
		</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Fixed positioning bug when moving items within their current parent by dropping on another item in that parent with the shift key held down.</item>
			<item>Fixed bug where modifying the &quot;User can resize&quot; property of a window while the tools were always shown on top stopped the tools from being shown on top.</item>
			<item>Added support for multi-line tooltips.</item>
			<item>Added support for `is_item_expanded' from EV_SPLIT_AREA.</item>
			<item>Added the ability to specify a directory for generation, into which location all files are to be generated.</item>
			<item>Event selection dialogs now contain the name of the object to which they refer in their title for cases where multiple dialogs are open simultaneously</item>
			<item>The project settings dialog is now completely navigatable via the keyboard on Windows platforms.</item>
			<item>Added support for Ctrl+Z and Ctrl+Y to navigate through the history.</item>
			<item>The font selection dialog now shows the currently selected font when displayed.</item>
			<item>Deleting an object that is contained within an object editor now clears the contents of the object editor.</item>
			<item>Preferences window now has the focus when displayed so it is fully navigatable via the keyboard.</item>
			<item>Code generation improved to allow the modifying of constants and subsequent update of the interface, permitting multiple languages to be supported.</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>5.6 Release
		</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added support for the generation of any widget as a class. You now may place widgets within the &quot;Widget Selector&quot; to enable this. The &quot;Widget Selector&quot; is simply the old &quot;Widget Selector&quot; renamed.</item>
			<item>Added clipboard functionality, permitting the copying/pasting of objects.</item>
			<item>Added support for new constant types: Font and Color.</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>5.5 Release
		</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added support for EV_RICH_TEXT which has been added to EiffelVision2.</item>
			<item>Notebook item texts may now be set to string constants.</item>
			<item>Better support for corrupt installations with warning dialogs now displayed.</item>
			<item>Fixed bug with generated code for notebooks often hiding the first item when they were actually displayed.</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>5.4 Release
		</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added support for multiple windows, including dialogs.</item>
			<item>Added support for constants of type Integer, String, Directory and Pixmap.</item>
			<item>New tool, &quot;Widget Selector&quot; added to handle organization of windows, including the ability to define subdirectories in a project, and group windows accordingly.</item>
			<item>Tip of the day dialog added.</item>
			<item>Recent projects are now available from the &quot;File&quot; menu.</item>
			<item>The contents of EiffelBuild projects may now be imported.</item>
			<item>The ability to reset the minimum dimensions of widgets have been added. In the previous version, it was not possible to complete undo the effects of setting a widgets minimum size.</item>
			<item>Preferences added, which allow you to customize the default behavior of EiffelBuild. For example, dialogs may be displayed or hidden as desired.</item>
			<item>The layout of EiffelBuild and its tools is now maintained between sessions.</item>
			<item>Docking added, permitting the re-ordering of particular tools within the interface, including making them &quot;float&quot; externally.</item>
			<item>Smarter code generation options, permitting only named attributes to be exported.</item>
		</list>
	</paragraph></document>
