<document title="Defining derived metrics" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>Metric,new,derived,define</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>To define a derived metric, you must select the<bold> Metric Definition</bold> tab and click the <bold>New metric</bold> button. A menu appears asking you the kind of metric you want to define. 
		Select <bold>Basic metric</bold> and then the type of the results you are looking for (i.e. Class, Feature, Line, ...). Once done, you can perform the following steps:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="true">
			<item>Enter a name for the metric in the "Name" field. Next to the field you will see the type of metric as well as the unit for this metric.</item>
			<item>Enter a description for the metric. The description is shown as a tooltip when you navigate the list of available metrics.</item>
			<item>
				Choose your criteria by selecting the item with ... in the <bold>Criterion definition</bold> list. Once selected you can press Ctrl+Space to see the list of available criterion. 
				Once the criterion is set, you can add some properties (e.g. a property could be <class_name>STRING</class_name> if the criterion you have is to look for descendants of the <class_name>STRING</class_name> class).
			</item>
			<item>Once you have completed the metric definition you need to save your metric by clicking on the Save button.</item>
			<item>If you want to define another derived metric, repeat all the previous steps.</item>
		</list>
		
		<paragraph>For more information about criterion, read the <link><url>../../../../reference/60_metric_tool/20_definitions/99_criterion_reference.xml</url><label>Managing criterion</label></link> section.</paragraph>
		
		<paragraph>A summary of the metric you just defined appears in a textual representation in the <bold>Expression</bold> text field.</paragraph>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../20_managing_new_metrics/00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>Managing metrics</label>
			</link>
			<line_break></line_break>
			<link>
				<url>../../../../reference/60_metric_tool/20_definitions/99_criterion_reference.xml</url>
				<label>Managing criterion</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
