<EIFFEL_DOCUMENT>
<TOPIC ID="Tags">
	<HEAD>The defined tags</HEAD>

	<TOPIC ID="EIFFEL_DOCUMENT"><HEAD>EIFFEL_DOCUMENT</HEAD>
	<TEXT>You should use this tag as the first tag of you document.</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="TOPIC"><HEAD>TOPIC</HEAD>
	<TEXT>The topic tag lets you create a new help-topic. With a topic, you
must specify either an ID or a LOCATION. If you specify an ID,
this becomes the identifier of the topic. You must now provide
in this topic a HEAD and either subtopics or text. If you choose
to specify a location, you must enter the filename of the topic
you want to insert in the tree. The topic will substituted by the
root-topic of that file.</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="HEAD"><HEAD>HEAD</HEAD>
	<TEXT>Specify the head of a help-topic. You cannot use mark-up tags
within a HEAD tag, because it also will be displayed in the Tree-view.</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="TEXT"><HEAD>TEXT</HEAD>
	<TEXT>If a topic contains text, you can put the paragraphs in TEXT-tags. Within text-topics,
you can use these tags: FONT, BR, IMP, A, B, I, U. Underlined text is not
yet supported by the topic display area (EV_RICH_TEXT)</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="FONT"><HEAD>FONT</HEAD>
	<TEXT>With FONT you can specify NAME, SIZE and COLOR. Example:
<FONT NAME="Arial" SIZE="16" COLOR="blue">&lt;FONT NAME="Arial" SIZE="16" COLOR="blue"&gt;</FONT>
The NAME is not (yet) platform independent.
The NAME and SIZE are not implemented yet on Unix.</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="BR"><HEAD>BR</HEAD>
	<TEXT>The BR is a strange tag, because in XML a tag should always
have a end-tag. If you want to use this tag, use it as a
standalone-tag in this way: &lt;BR/&gt;</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="IMP"><HEAD>IMP</HEAD>
	<TEXT>All words that you put in a IMP-tag will show up in the
search-index and you will be able to find the topic in the
search-results list of that keyword. The search is
case-insensitive.</TEXT></TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="A"><HEAD>A</HEAD>
	<TEXT>You can use anchors in your body text. to make a link to another topic
within the ENTIRE system, use &lt;A TOPIC_ID="General"&gt;
Be sure to type the name correct. Case sensitive.
Not yet supported, but feel free to start using it: HREF</TEXT></TOPIC>

</TOPIC>
</EIFFEL_DOCUMENT>
