<EIFFEL_DOCUMENT>
<TOPIC ID="Help">
	<HEAD>Help on Help</HEAD>
	<TOPIC ID="General">
		<HEAD>ISE Help tool</HEAD>
<TEXT>Welcome to the help for this help-program. As you can see,
the <IMP>window</IMP> is divided in a <A TOPIC_ID="Left">left</A> and <A TOPIC_ID="Right">right</A> <IMP>section</IMP> divided
by a <IMP>splitter</IMP>. You can move the splitter if you want to enlarge
any of the two sections.</TEXT>

<TEXT>There is a program available that converts the FrameMaker 5.5.6 XML output into
our help-document format. Note: the current version only detects these tags:
Section headers: xx-chapter, xx-sec2, xx-sec3
Body text: xx-first, xx-normal, xx-small
Bulleted list items: xx-bull, xx-bullnum
The xx- part can be any character (nn-, bb-, ll-) or can be omitted.

It also displays text in tables, but not formatted at all.</TEXT>

<TEXT><FONT NAME="Tahoma" SIZE="15">This <FONT SIZE="18">is <FONT COLOR="blue">not</FONT> a test</FONT>, this is an actual <FONT SIZE="20" NAME="Arial">e<I>m</I>e<I>rge</I><B>ncy</B>!!!</FONT></FONT></TEXT>

	</TOPIC>
	<TOPIC ID="HelpDocuments">
		<HEAD>Help Documents</HEAD>
		<TOPIC ID="AboutXML">
			<HEAD>About XML</HEAD>

<TEXT>Help documents are written in XML. XML stands for eXtensible Markup Language.
For this help tool, some new tags were defined. These are the new tags:
<UL><LI><A TOPIC_ID="EIFFEL_DOCUMENT">EIFFEL_DOCUMENT</A>: Every help-file starts with this tag.</LI><LI><A TOPIC_ID="TOPIC">TOPIC</A>: Define a new help-topic.</LI><LI><A TOPIC_ID="HEAD">HEAD</A>: The title of the topic.</LI><LI><A TOPIC_ID="TEXT">TEXT</A>: The body text of a topic.</LI></UL>

Furthermore, in the TEXT-tag, you can use some tags that are also
available in HTML like:
<UL><LI>B: Bold.</LI><LI>I: Italic.</LI><LI>U: Underline. (does not work yet)</LI><LI><A TOPIC_ID="A">A</A>: Anchor.</LI><LI><A TOPIC_ID="FONT">FONT</A>: Font properties.</LI><LI>UL: Unnumbered list.</LI><LI>LI: List-item.</LI><LI><A TOPIC_ID="BR">BR</A>: Line break.</LI></UL>

There is one extra tag:
<UL><LI><A TOPIC_ID="IMP">IMP</A>: Add the words between these tags to the search-index.</LI></UL>

In a single file there can be only one (root)-topic. Every topic must
have a HEAD tag in it. There can be either subtopics or text contained
in a topic. You can put as many subtopics or text-paragraphs in it as
you want.
</TEXT>
		</TOPIC>
		<TOPIC LOCATION="helptags.xml"/>
	</TOPIC>

	<TOPIC ID="Interface">
		<HEAD>The Help-interface</HEAD>
		<TOPIC ID="Left">
			<HEAD>The left side</HEAD>
			<TOPIC ID="Tree">
				<HEAD>The first tab: 'Tree'</HEAD>

<TEXT>The first <IMP>tab</IMP> of the this help tool enables you to <IMP>browse</IMP> through the <IMP>topics</IMP> in a <IMP><I>hierarchical</I></IMP> way.</TEXT>

			</TOPIC>
			<TOPIC ID="Index">
				<HEAD>The second tab: 'Index'</HEAD>

<TEXT>The second <IMP>tab</IMP> lets you to <IMP>browse</IMP> through the <IMP>topics</IMP> in <I><IMP>alphabetical</IMP></I> order. Just type the first few <IMP>characters</IMP> of the <IMP>topic</IMP> and <IMP>select</IMP> it from the <IMP>list</IMP>.</TEXT>

			</TOPIC>
			<TOPIC ID="Search">
				<HEAD>The third tab: 'Search'</HEAD>

<TEXT>You can use the <IMP>search</IMP>-tab to search for <IMP><I>keywords</I></IMP>. The topics with that word then appear in the list.</TEXT>

			</TOPIC>
		</TOPIC>
		<TOPIC ID="Right">
			<HEAD>The right side</HEAD>
			<TOPIC ID="Display">
				<HEAD>The topic display area</HEAD>

<TEXT>On the right of the window the help topics are displayed. If you want to copy some text from it, select your text or source code and choose File|Copy from the menu.</TEXT>

			</TOPIC>
		</TOPIC>
	</TOPIC>
	<TOPIC LOCATION="helpother.xml"/>
</TOPIC>
</EIFFEL_DOCUMENT>
