<document title="CECIL: Introduction" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<meta_content>CECIL</meta_content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>This document provides an overview of the C-Eiffel Call-In Library (CECIL) as defined in Eiffel: The Language (ETL). The first section addresses how to compile and run a CECIL program, on the 
			<link>
				<url>10_compiling_a_system_for_cecil.xml</url>
				<label>Eiffel side</label>
			</link> and on the 
			<link>
				<url>20_c_side_compilation.xml</url>
				<label>C side</label>
			</link>. The 
			<link>
				<url>30_cecil_interface.xml</url>
				<label>second part</label>
			</link> contains a more precise description of the Eiffel types, the protection mechanism as well as how to write and use C externals. 
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>CECIL, designed by  Eiffel Software , is the C library that permits C and C++ applications (as well as applications written in other languages) to take advantage of almost all Eiffel facilities: create Eiffel objects, apply features to them. The basics of CECIL are described in chapter 24 of the reference book on Eiffel, Eiffel: The Language, which covers interfaces between Eiffel and other languages. Important material can also be found in the  Eiffel Software  manual Eiffel: The Environment. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>The CECIL documentation, man pages and examples are part of the standard delivery of EiffelStudio 5.0 and higher. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>The present document complements the descriptions of Eiffel: The Language. Note that CECIL has been revised and improved since that book was published, so the explanations below have precedence over those in the book. </paragraph>
		<paragraph>This document is intended for both Windows and Unix users. Only a few of the sections, clearly marked, are platform-specific. </paragraph>To access Eiffel mechanisms from C or other external languages: 
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Compile your Eiffel system so as to generate "Cecilized" code, that is to say code callable from the outside. See 
				<link>
					<url>10_compiling_a_system_for_cecil.xml</url>
					<label>Compiling your Eiffel system for CECIL</label>
				</link>. 
			</item>
			<item>In writing the external code that will use the facilities of the Eiffel system, use the CECIL functions as specified in chapter 24 of 
				<italic>Eiffel: The Language</italic>. See also 
				<link>
					<url>30_cecil_interface.xml</url>
					<label>The CECIL interface overview</label>
				</link>. 
			</item>
			<item>C-compile and link that code. See 
				<link>
					<url>20_c_side_compilation.xml</url>
					<label>Building a C system using CECIL</label>
				</link>. 
			</item>
		</list>
		<paragraph>For feature by feature specification, please have a look at 
			<link>
				<url>man_pages/index.xml</url>
				<label>the man pages</label>
			</link>. 
		</paragraph>
	</paragraph></document>
