<document title="Reuse or Generate an Execution Profile" output="studio">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph>The second screen of the wizard lets you reuse a previously generated 
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic> or generate a new 
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic> from a 
			<italic>Run-time information record</italic>.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>The profiler wizard has detected that one or more 
			<italic>Execution Profiles</italic> have already been generated for this system in this compilation mode. If you have executed your system after the generation of the existing profile, select 
			<bold>Generate a profile from Run-time information record</bold> to create a new 
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic> for the newly produced 
			<italic>Run-time information record</italic>.
		</paragraph>
		<note>
			<bold>Note</bold>: If you choose 
			<bold>Generate a profile from Run-time information record</bold> the generated 
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic> will be written into 
			<italic>&lt;project_directory&gt;/EIFGEN/W_CODE/profinfo.pfi</italic> if you have selected 
			<bold>Workbench mode</bold> in the first step, or 
			<italic>&lt;project_directory&gt;/EIFGEN/F_CODE/profinfo.pfi</italic> if you have selected 
			<bold>Finalized mode</bold>. If a file with the same name already exists its content will be destroyed and replaced.
		</note>
		<line_break/>
		<paragraph>However, if you have not executed your system since the generation of the last 
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic>, there is no need to generate a new 
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic>. If you are in the latter case, select 
			<bold>Use existing profile</bold> and choose the last
			<italic>Execution Profile</italic> you have generated.
		</paragraph>
		<tip>
			<bold>Tip</bold>: If you want to archive different 
			<italic>Execution Profiles</italic> (to compare them for example), rename the 
			<italic>profinfo.pfi</italic> file into a new name but keep the .pfi extension. The profiler wizard detects existing Execution Profiles by checking the file extensions.
		</tip>
		<line_break/>
		<image>
			<url>/images/eiffelstudio/dialogs_and_wizards/profiler_wizard_second_state.png</url>
		</image> 
		<line_break/>
		<line_break/>
		<paragraph>Clicking 
			<bold>Next</bold> will lead you to the 
			<link>
				<url>30_third_state.xml</url>
				<label>Third state</label>
			</link> if you have selected 
			<bold>Generate a profile from Run-time information record</bold>. On the other hand if you have selected 
			<bold>Use existing profile</bold> you will go to the 
			<link>
				<url>40_final_state.xml</url>
				<label>Final state</label>
			</link>.
		</paragraph>
		<line_break/>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../00_introduction.xml</url>
				<label>How the Profiler wizard works</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>../../../../how_to_s/50_running_and_debugging/70_profiling.xml</url>
				<label>How to profile a system</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>