<document title="Elementary and composite metrics" output="studio">
	<meta_data >
		<help >
			<meta >
				<meta_content >Metric,elementary</meta_content>
				<name >MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
			<meta >
				<meta_content >Metric,composite</meta_content>
				<name >MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph >
		<heading >
			<size >1</size>Elementary and composite metrics
		</heading>
		<paragraph >Some of our metrics will be elementary and some composite. An elementary metric is measured directly from the product or project record:</paragraph>
		<note >
			<bold >Elementary_metric</bold>
			<line_break />
			- An <bold >elementary product metric</bold> is a product metric whose values (integers) indicate the number of occurrences of a certain pattern in a product.
			<line_break />
			- An 
			<bold >elementary process metric</bold> is a process metric whose values reflect measurements drawn directly from project records.
		</note>
		<paragraph >An example of elementary product metric is the number of source lines. An example of elementary process metric is the number of incremental compilations of a system.</paragraph>
		<paragraph >Elementary metrics are provided by default by the metric tool. There is no means to remove them or to define new ones since they are not expressed as a combination of other metrics.</paragraph>
		<paragraph >From these elementary metrics we may define composite ones:</paragraph>
		<note >
			<bold >Composite metric </bold>: A 
			<bold >composite metric</bold> is a metric whose values are defined by a mathematical formula involving other metrics (elementary, or previously defined composite metrics).
		</note>A later section will introduce a number of operations for defining composite metrics out of elementary ones. 
		<paragraph > </paragraph>
		<paragraph >Again we may distinguish between product and process:</paragraph>
		<note >
			<bold >Composite product metric, composite process metric:</bold>
			<line_break /> - A 
			<bold >composite product metric</bold> is a composite metric defined entirely in terms of product metrics.
			<line_break /> - A 
			<bold >composite process metric</bold> is a composite metric whose definition involves one or more process metrics.
		</note>
		<paragraph >By convention, this definition treats as process metric a composite metric involving both product and process components.</paragraph>
		<paragraph >The classification introduced for metrics extends to measures, so that we may talk about an elementary product measure, a composite process measure and so on.</paragraph>
		<paragraph >The metric menu of the metric tool separates elementary and composite metrics: </paragraph>
		<paragraph >
			<image >
				<url >/images/eiffelstudio/metrics_png/metric_category.png</url>
				<border >0</border>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph >All metrics (elementary and composite) are not always sensitive. Their sensitiveness also depends on 
			<link >
				<url >70_scopes_scope_types.xml</url>
				<label >scopes</label>
			</link>
		</paragraph>
		<seealso >
			<bold >See Also</bold>
			<line_break />
			<link >
				<url >10_attributes_metrics_measures.html#Metric</url>
				<label >Metrics</label>
			</link>
			<line_break />
			<link >
				<url >70_scopes_scope_types.xml</url>
				<label >Scopes</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>