<document output="envision" title="Deployment Prerequisites">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_title>Deployment Prerequisites</envision_title>
				<envision_pseudo_name>10</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
			<xml>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>EiffelEnvision, Deploying projects</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
				<xmlkeyword>
					<index>K</index>
					<term>Deployment, Requirements</term>
				</xmlkeyword>
			</xml>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		Before deploying projects created using <bold>EiffelEnvision</bold>, you should ensure that your project 
		is in a state to be deployed. Failure to do so will result in incomplete <help_link>
			<keywords>vbconDeployingSolution</keywords>
			<tab_index>0</tab_index>
			deployment projects
		</help_link>.
		
		<anchor>deplyoment_requirements</anchor>
		<heading><size>2</size><content>Deployment Requirements</content></heading>
		<paragraph>
			Before an EiffelEnvision project can be deployed successfully using the integrated <help_link>
				<keywords>vbconSetupProjects</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Setup and Deployment projects
			</help_link> installed with Visual Studio .NET, the following list of conditions are required to be met.
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>
			<list ordered="true">
				<item>A project exists in the same <help_link>
					<keywords></keywords>
					<tab_index></tab_index>
					solution
				</help_link> as the <help_link>
				<keywords>vbconSetupProjects</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Setup and Deployment project
			</help_link>.</item>
			<item>The EiffelEnvision project can be successfully compiled.
				<note>
				<bold>Note:</bold> EiffelEnvision projects do not need to be built/compiled prior to deployment; however, 
				examining an added <help_link>
					<keywords>vbconFeaturesFilesFoldersDeployment</keywords>
					<tab_index>0</tab_index>
					project output
				</help_link> will not show all of the files generated at build time. Once built, an EiffelEnvision project output will show all of the files that will 
				be deployed.
				</note>
			</item>
			</list>
		</paragraph>
		
		<anchor>deplyoment_recommendations</anchor>
		<heading><size>2</size><content>Recommendations</content></heading>
		<paragraph>
			Although not necessary, it is recommended that before adding an EiffelEnvision project output to a deployment project, you build your 
			EiffelEnvision project(s). Projects that have been built prior to adding their output to the deployment project will 
			ensure all dependencies are evaluated and added to the deployment project automatically. It also serves to self-
			validate what will be included in the deployment project when built, by examining the project <help_link>
				<keywords>vxurfOutputsDialogBox</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				output
			</help_link>. EiffelEnvision projects are different from 
			C#, VB.NET and other such projects. EiffelEnvision's compiler is incremental and produces many additional assembly modules 
			when not <link><url/><label>*optimizing code</label></link>, which can only be evaluated and included into the deployment 
			project once built. If you choose not to build the EiffelEnvision project before adding its output to the deployment project, 
			all newly generated files will be added automatically to the deployment project when built.
		<paragraph>
		</paragraph>
			When deploying projects for distribution, it is recommended to configure your project to <link><url/><label>*optimizing the compilation</label></link> as this will create a 
			single deployment module resulting in faster load and execution times. It is also recommended to disable generation of a project's <link><url/><label>*debug 
			information</label></link>. This will dramatically reduce file size because the debug information will not be included in the deployment project automatically.
		</paragraph>
		
		<anchor>also_see</anchor>
		<heading><size>2</size><content>Related Sections</content></heading>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See Also:</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link><url>index.xml</url><label>Deploying Projects</label></link>
			<line_break/>
			<help_link>
				<keywords>vbconSetupProjects</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Setup and Deployment Projects
			</help_link>
			<line_break/>
			<help_link>
				<keywords>vxtskCreatingandEditingConfigurations</keywords>
				<tab_index>0</tab_index>
				Configuration Manager
			</help_link>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph>
</document>
