<document output="envision" title="Editor Advanced Settings">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<toc>
				<envision_pseudo_name>30</envision_pseudo_name>
			</toc>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<table>
			<row>
				<cell>
					<paragraph>  The features and style of the editor viewer can be configured to suit your  preferencesand needs. To configure these select
						<bold>Options..</bold>  from the Visual Studio
						<bold>Tools </bold>menu.This will display the Options  dialog, and in the list to the left of the dialog, select 'Text Editor' and  then 'Eiffel' to browse to the editor settings for Eiffel source code.  The dialog should then have the following appearance:
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>
						<image>
							<alt_text>General Property Page</alt_text>
							<url>General_editor_advanced_settings.PNG</url>
							<width>600</width>
							<height>376</height>
						</image>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>  From this dialog you may change the behavior of the editor when it  displays Eiffel source code. </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Statement Completion
					</heading>
					<list ordered="false">
						<item>  Auto list members: when selected, a list of available members of a given
							<link>
								<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/10_Terminology.htm#object</url>
								<label>object</label>
							</link>  or
							<link>
								<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/10_Terminology.htm#class</url>
								<label>class</label>
							</link>  displays at the appropriate places when you enter a line of code.
						</item>
						<item>  Parameter information: when selected, parameter information displays for the
							<link>
								<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/10_Terminology.htm#function</url>
								<label>function</label>
							</link>  or
							<link>
								<url>/20_Language/10_Eiffel_NET/10_Conventions/10_Terminology.htm#procedure</url>
								<label>procedure</label>
							</link>,  if any are available.
						</item>
					</list>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Settings
					</heading>
					<list ordered="false">
						<item>  Enable virtual space: when selected, allows you to move the cursor beyond the  physical end of a line of text into character spaces that do not exist. If you  move your cursor out into this area and begin typing, the void between your  current position and the end of the last word is automatically filled with  space characters. When this setting is not selected, you cannot move the cursor  beyond the last character in a line.  </item>
						<item>  Word wrap: when selected, lines that extend horizontally beyond the visible  range of the Editor are automatically wrapped to the next line.  </item>
					</list>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>Display
					</heading>
					<list ordered="false">
						<item>  Line numbers: when selected, a line number displays to the left of each line of  text.  </item>
						<item>  Enable single-click URL navigation: when selected, URLs embedded in the text  require only a single mouse click to navigate to their Web page.  </item>
					</list>
					<seealso>
						<bold>See also</bold>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./index.htm</url>
							<label>The Eiffel Editor</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./EditorFeatures.htm</url>
							<label>Editor Features</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>./EditorQuickInfo.htm</url>
							<label>Editor Quick Info</label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
					</seealso>
				</cell>
			</row>
		</table>
	</paragraph></document>