<document title="Release notes for EiffelStudio 5.5" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help></help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading><size>2</size>Graphical environment</heading>
			<heading><size>3</size>Improvements</heading>
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>Added full configuration of colors used in editor</item>
				<item>Added docking facilities for various tools. It permits the re-ordering of tools within the interface, including making them "float" externally <link><url>../../../eiffelbuild/reference/10_general_interface_description/50_docking.xml</url><label>(See EiffelBuild documentation on docking mechanism for more details)</label></link>.</item>
				<item>Ability to see when a class is deferred in the context tool formatters. It is shown by adding the `*' character at the end of the class name.</item>
			</list>
			<heading><size>3</size>Changes</heading>
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>One cannot add a .NET assembly from the GAC anymore, instead you have to specify the path to the assembly in the assembly references list.</item>
			</list>
			<heading><size>3</size>Bug fixes</heading>
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>Fixed a crash when performing feature completion on classes with errors.</item>
				<item>On Windows, prevented the EiffelStudio window to go to the back of all windows when you click Ok on the dialog box which appears when a syntax error occurs while compiling a project.</item>
			</list>
		<heading><size>2</size>Debugger</heading>
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>Enabled conditional breakpoint and expression evaluation for .NET</item>
				<item>Improved expression evaluation abilities (full range of Eiffel expressions are now supported).</item>
				<item>Improved object viewer window (word wrapping for large text, ability to see the whole content in one click without having to enter the lower and upper index of a range).</item>
			</list>
		<heading><size>2</size>EiffelBuild</heading>
			<list ordered="false">
				<item>Click <link><url>../../../eiffelbuild/version_history/index.xml</url><label>here</label></link> for the EiffelBuild release notes.</item>
			</list>
		<heading><size>2</size>Compiler</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Click <link><url>../30_compiler/60_version_history/05_55_release/index.xml</url><label>here</label></link> for the compiler release notes.</item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>2</size>Libraries</heading>
		<heading><size>3</size>CECIL</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added ability to query type of a generic class where an actual generic parameter is expanded although its base class is not. It suffices to prefix the class name with "expanded ". Reciprocally, you can use the reference version of an expanded class by prefixing with "reference ".</item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>3</size>EiffelBase</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Removed <feature_name>consistent</feature_name> and <feature_name>setup</feature_name> from <class_name>ANY</class_name></item>
			<item>Removed <feature_name>Void</feature_name> from <class_name>ANY</class_name> as <code><keyword>Void</keyword></code> is now a keyword.</item>
			<item>Added <feature_name>for_all</feature_name>, <feature_name>do_all</feature_name>, <feature_name>do_if</feature_name> and <feature_name>there_exists</feature_name> to <class_name>ARRAY</class_name>. As a consequence descendants of <class_name>ARRAY</class_name> which also inherit from <class_name>LINEAR</class_name> have to select the proper version of those routines as they also appear in <class_name>LINEAR</class_name>.</item>
			<item>Fixed <feature_name>dynamic_type_from_string</feature_name> from <class_name>INTERNAL</class_name> under .NET which was not working if you were using the .NET naming convention or if you specified a namespace.</item>
			<item>Added <feature_name>generic_count</feature_name>, <feature_name>generic_count_with_type</feature_name> in <class_name>INTERNAL</class_name> to find out how many generic parameter a type has.</item>
			<item>Added <feature_name>generic_dynamic_type_with_type</feature_name> in <class_name>INTERNAL</class_name> to find out the type of the i-th generic parameter of a given type.</item>
			<item>Added <feature_name>memory_map</feature_name> and <feature_name>memory_count_map</feature_name> to give you a precise accounting of all living objects in the running system. It will help you find out any potential memory leak because objects are still referenced where they should not.</item>
			<item>Improved performance of <class_name>FILE</class_name> objects creation by not allocating the <feature_name>last_string</feature_name> internal buffer until it is needed.</item>
			<item>On Windows, removed side effects of <feature_name>put</feature_name> from <class_name>EXECUTION_ENVIRONMENT</class_name>. Before it was setting also some registry keys, now it only set the environment variable for the running process and its children when launched.</item>
			<item>Allowed zero sized <class_name>MANAGED_POINTER</class_name>. Allowed <class_name>MANAGED_POINTER</class_name> to share a pointer rather than doing a full memory copy at creation time.</item>
			<item>Fixed issue with agents where GC did not collect passed arguments to <feature_name>call</feature_name> or <feature_name>item</feature_name> from <class_name>ROUTINE</class_name>/<class_name>FUNCTION</class_name>. Thus arguments stayed alive until the next call to <feature_name>call</feature_name> or <feature_name>item</feature_name>.</item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>3</size>EiffelNet</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added <feature_name>close_socket</feature_name> in <class_name>SOCKET</class_name>which only close the socket for the current process. It will not close it for all processes which are using this socket (e.g. obtained after a fork on Unix platform).</item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>3</size>EiffelTime</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Fixed incorrect display of the short year format when using the following code:<code_block>l_date: <class_name>DATE_TIME</class_name>
...
<keyword>create</keyword> l_date.<feature_name>make_now</feature_name>
<feature_name>print</feature_name> (l_date.<feature_name>formatted_out</feature_name> ("[0]mm/[0]dd/yy"))
</code_block>
			</item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>3</size>EiffelThread</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added a new C routine <feature_name>eif_thread_fork</feature_name> for Unix based system for users who would like to use a forking mechanism in a multithreaded system, as the default version of <feature_name>fork</feature_name> will most likely causes some deadlock.</item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>3</size>EiffelVision2</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item><link><label>Click here for EiffelVision2 release notes.</label><url>../../../../libraries/vision2/content/0-_revisions/index.xml</url></link></item>
		</list>
		<heading><size>3</size>WEL</heading>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>Added various missing constants in <class_name>WEL_*_CONSTANTS</class_name> classes.</item>
			<item>Added creation procedure <feature_name>make_permanent</feature_name> in <class_name>WEL_DLL</class_name> so that the loaded DLL is loaded until the very end of program's execution. Now <class_name>WEL_RICH_EDIT_DLL</class_name> and <class_name>WEL_COMMON_CONTROLS_DLL</class_name> are using this new creation procedure. It fixes the issue where a program using <class_name>WEL_RICH_EDIT</class_name> would crash when exiting.</item>
			<item>Fixed a possible C compilation error when using <class_name>WEL_RICH_EDIT</class_name> due to a bug in the Microsoft Platform SDK header file for RichEdit.</item>
			<item>Fixed <class_name>WEL_SCROLL_BAR</class_name> to return a valid position when position is more than 65535.</item>
			<item>Added <feature_name>string_size_extended</feature_name> in <class_name>WEL_FONT</class_name> to better know where to draw a string using a specified font on screen,</item>
			<item>Added <feature_name>height_in_points</feature_name>, <feature_name>height_in_pixels</feature_name>, <feature_name>height_in_twips</feature_name>, and <feature_name>log_font</feature_name> in <class_name>WEL_CHARACTER_FORMAT</class_name>.  Made <feature_name>height </feature_name> and <feature_name>set_height</feature_name> obsolete.</item>
			<item>Changed implementation of <class_name>WEL_REGISTRY_KEY_VALUE</class_name> in order to fix <feature_name>set_dword_value</feature_name>which was writing incorrect data to the registry keys. Enhanced the typing of values, thus making the non-typed routines obsolete.</item>
			<item>Made <feature_name>default_key_value</feature_name> obsolete in <class_name>WEL_REGISTRY</class_name>.</item>
			<item>Properly defined <feature_name>is_equal</feature_name> and <feature_name>copy</feature_name> in <class_name>WEL_STRUCTURE</class_name>, possibly causing some compilation errors while analyzing the inheritance structure of your classes.</item>
			<item>Changed signature of non exported routine <feature_name>cwin_destroy_window</feature_name> from <class_name>WEL_WINDOW</class_name> to now return a value.</item>
			<item>Fixed issues when using WEL in a multithreaded application. It would crash if a non WEL thread was trying to destroy a WEL window.</item>
		</list>
	</paragraph>
</document>
