<document title="Creating a new component from an Eiffel project" output="studio">
	<meta_data>
		<help>
			<meta>
				<content>EiffelCOM</content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
			<meta>
				<content>EiffelCOM Wizard</content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
			<meta>
				<content>EiffelCOM Wizard, Guided Tour</content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
			<meta>
				<content>EiffelCOM Wizard, Guided Tour, Creating a new component from an Eiffel project</content>
				<name>MS-HKWD</name>
			</meta>
		</help>
	</meta_data>
	<paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>1</size>Creating a new component from an Eiffel project
		</heading>
		<paragraph>The second tutorial describes creating a COM component from an Eiffel system. The tutorial example 
			<italic>String</italic> is almost identical to 
			<italic>StringManipulator</italic> of the previous tutorial. In the 
			<italic>StringManipulator</italic> example the wizard starts from IDL file and builds an Eiffel System; in contrast, the 
			<italic>String</italic>example takes an Eiffel system and generates an IDL file and the required plumbing code to make the Eiffel project accessible to COM runtime. You do not need to modify any Eiffel or C code.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size> Step by step instructions
		</heading>
		<list ordered="true">
			<item>Create a new Eiffel project in the directory
				<italic>$ISE_EIFFEL\examples\com\wizard\e2idl\eproject</italic> where $ISE_EIFFEL represents the path to your EIFFEL50 directory.
			</item>
			<item>Select Ace file from the same directory and compile.</item>
			<item>Launch the EiffelCOM Wizard (from the Start menu, open Programs then EiffelXX and click EiffelCOM Wizard)</item>
			<item>Choose 
				<italic>Create a new project from an existing Eiffel project</italic>.
			</item>
			<item>Click 
				<italic>Next</italic>
			</item>
			<item>Click 
				<italic>Next</italic> again
			</item>
			<item>Click the top Browse button and open the file
				<italic>$ISE_EIFFEL\examples\com\wizard\e2idl\eproject\string.epr</italic>where $ISE_EIFFEL represents the path to your EIFFEL50directory.
			</item>
			<item>Click the second Browse button and open the file
				<italic>$ISE_EIFFEL\examples\com\wizard\e2idl\ eproject\Ace.ace</italic>where $ISE_EIFFEL represents the path to your EIFFEL50directory.
			</item>
			<item>In the third entry field enter 
				<italic>string_manipulator</italic>.
			</item>
			<item>In the forth entry field enter 
				<italic>root_cluster</italic>.
			</item>
			<item>Click 
				<italic>Next</italic>.
			</item>
			<item>Click the Browse button and select the directory where you want to create the project (the destination folder). Choose
				<italic>$ISE_EIFFEL\examples\com\wizard\e2idl\generated</italic> where $ISE_EIFFEL represents the path to your EIFFEL50 directory. If you work on a Windows 9x machine, please choose a directory with a shorter path, for example c:\e2idl.
			</item>
			<item>Click 
				<italic>Next</italic>
			</item>
			<item>Choose Automation</item>
			<item>Click 
				<italic>Next</italic>
			</item>
			<item>Click 
				<italic>Finish</italic>
			</item>
			<item>Wait until the wizard is done.</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size> First look at the generated code
		</heading>The only generated Eiffel class is 
		<code>
			<class_name>COM_&lt;Name_of_system&gt;_REGISTRATION</class_name>
		</code>. You do not need to modify or implement any classes. The wizard produces a ready-to-use component. 
		<tip>Tip: In most Eiffel systems functionality is spread out throughout the system. No single class exposes the full functionality of the system and can serve as a Facade to the outside world. Running the wizard on any such class would not be practical. Before starting the wizard write an Eiffel class that acts as a Facade and forwards client calls to the appropriate subsystems. Enter the Facade class name into "Enter Eiffel class name" field of the third dialog (Eiffel Project File Dialog). The wizard generates an IDL file from this class.</tip>
		<seealso>
			<link>
				<url>01_new_from_com.xml</url>
				<label>Creating a new COM component</label>
			</link>
			<link>
				<url>03_accessing.xml</url>
				<label>Accessing a COM component.</label>
			</link>
		</seealso>
		<paragraph> </paragraph>
	</paragraph>
</document>