<document output="envision" title="Solution Explorer Context Menus">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<paragraph> Right clicking on a node in the 
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/20_Solution_Explorer/index.htm</url>
				<label>Solution Explorer</label>
			</link>  will bring up a context menu that allows you to perform certain actions  relative to that node. For an Eiffel Project there two main types of  context menus, one for the Eiffel project itself, and one for the files  contained within your project directory, be it either an Eiffel Class or a  miscellaneous file.
		</paragraph>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>  Project Context Menu
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text/>
				<url>./solution_explorer_project_node_context_menu.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>  In the image above we can see the context menu for the Eiffel project 'My Eiffel  Project'. The entries available on the context menu perform the following  actions:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>  
				<bold>Build</bold>: Builds the Eiffel project (
				<link>
					<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/60_Compiling_Projects/index.htm</url>
					<label>Compiling</label>
				</link>).
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Rebuild</bold>: Rebuilds the Eiffel project (
				<link>
					<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/60_Compiling_Projects/index.htm</url>
					<label>Compiles</label>
				</link> completely from scratch).
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Add</bold>: This allows you to
				<link>
					<url>/10_Developing/20_Managing_Projects/20_Adding_New_Project_Items/index.htm</url>
					<label> Add a New or Existing Item</label>
				</link> to the Eiffel project.
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Add Reference</bold>: This allows .Net assembly references to be added to the system.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Set as StartUp Project</bold>: Sets the project to be the one that is launched on solution execution.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Debug</bold>: Allows you to execute or step in to the Eiffel project.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Save My Eiffel Project.eifp</bold>: This saves the project file associated with this project.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Remove</bold>: Removes the project from the current solution  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Rename</bold>: Allows the project name to be changed  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Properties</bold>: Display the main Property Page for the project.  
			</item>
		</list>
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>  File Context Menu
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text/>
				<url>./solution_explorer_class_node_context_menu.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>  In the image just above we can see the context menu for the Eiffel class file  'root_class.e'. The entries available on the context menu perform the  following actions:</paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>  
				<bold>Open</bold>: This opens the file in the default editor.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Open With</bold>: This allows you to choose which editor you want to open the file  with.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>View Code</bold>: Brings up the Code View for an Eiffel Class  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>View Designer</bold>: Brings up the Design View Eiffel Classes representing Forms  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Remove</bold>: Remove the file from the project.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Rename</bold>: Change the name of the file.  
			</item>
			<item>  
				<bold>Properties</bold>: Bring up the property page for the file  
			</item>
		</list> 
		<heading>
			<size>2</size>  References Context Menu
		</heading>
		<paragraph>
			<image>
				<alt_text/>
				<url>./solution_explorer_reference_node_context_menu.png</url>
			</image>
		</paragraph>
		<paragraph>  In the image just above we can see the context menu for the Mscorlib Assembly reference.  The entries available on the context menu perform the following actions. </paragraph>
		<list ordered="false">
			<item>
				<bold>Remove</bold>: This allows the assembly reference to be removed from the current project
			</item>
			<item>
				<bold>Properties</bold>: This will bring up the Reference Properties pane showing information relating to the referenced assembly
			</item>
		</list>
		<line_break/>
		<seealso>
			<bold>See also</bold>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/20_Solution_Explorer/index.htm</url>
				<label>Solution Explorer</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
			<link>
				<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/index.htm</url>
				<label>Using ENViSioN! Within Visual Studio.NET</label>
			</link>
			<line_break/>
		</seealso>
	</paragraph></document>
