<document output="envision" title="Solution Explorer">
	<meta_data/>
	<paragraph>
		<table>
			<row>
				<cell>
					<paragraph>  The Solution Explorer allows you to explore and interact with the structure of  the projects contained within your solution. When browsing an Eiffel project  within your solution, the Solution Explorer allows you to add, view and remove  files that are included in your project directory, as well as showing the .Net  Assemblies referenced in your Eiffel system. </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Solution Explorer Structure 
					</heading>
					<paragraph>
						<image> 
							<alt_text/> 
							<url>./solution_explorer.PNG</url>
						</image>
					</paragraph>
					<paragraph>  From the picture above we can see that we have a Solution open called 'My  Solution', contained within is an Eiffel Project named 'My Eiffel Project'. The  Solution Explorer for Eiffel projects allows you to view the three different  types of files that are included/referenced in 'My Eiffel Project'. These files  types are distinguished within the project by having their own folder, the file  types available being: </paragraph>
					<list ordered="false">
						<item>  References - These are the .Net assemblies that are referenced by your project  </item>
						<item>  Eiffel Source Files - These are the Eiffel Source files that have been added to  your project  </item>
						<item>  Other Files - These are miscellaneous files such as Text and Bitmaps.  </item>
					</list>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  References 
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The References folder shows all of the .Net assemblies referenced from the  Eiffel project, they are listed in alphabetically and may be either reference  assemblies located in the Global Assembly Cache or locally. Double clicking on the  Assembly node will bring up browseable information relating to the assembly in the  Object Browser. New assembly references may be added by right clicking on the  References folder and then clicking 'Add Reference' from the context menu that pops up. </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Eiffel Source Files 
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The Eiffel Source Files folder contains all of the Eiffel source files that are  contained within your project directory. These files may be viewed by double  clicking on the file node (root_class.e in the picture above) or right clicking  on the file node and using the context menu (see context menus) </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Other Files 
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The Other Files folder holds any files that are not Eiffel class files. Examples of  these files being a text file such as Readme.txt that may contain information  about the project. Double clicking on this file will launch the appropriate  editor, in the Readme.txt's case it would be a basic text editor. If the file  was a bitmap, the default graphics editor within Visual Studio would launch. </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Renaming Nodes 
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The Solution Explorer allows you to change the name of the nodes relating to a file, by doing so  the name of the file that the node represents also changes. To rename a node  you can perform two single-clicks on the node and a floating label should pop  up to allow you to change the name. Another way to perform this change is to  right-click on the node and then use the Rename menu item in the context menu. </paragraph>
					<heading>
						<size>2</size>  Deleting Nodes 
					</heading>
					<paragraph>  The Solution explorer allows nodes to be deleted/removed from the current project, this includes  file nodes and assemblies. Nodes may be deleted either by highlighting the node in the Solution  Explorer and pressing the Delete key, or by right clicking on the node and using the Context Menu. </paragraph>
					<seealso>
						<bold>See also</bold>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/30_Class_View/index.html</url>
							<label>  Class View  </label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/40_Object_Browser/index.htm</url>
							<label>  Object Browser  </label>
						</link>
						<line_break/>
						<link>
							<url>/10_Developing/10_Getting_Started/10_Using_ENViSioN/index.htm</url>
							<label>  Using ENViSioN! Within Visual Studio.NET  </label>
						</link>
					</seealso>
				</cell>
			</row>
		</table>
	</paragraph></document>